Long Story Short

WAR DEPARTMENT FIELD MANUAL
TACTICS AND TECHNIQUE OF DELVING THE LONG STAIRS

REGARDED CLASSIFIED BY
AUTHORITY OF DOD DIR. 5200. 1 R

BY Lt. Ralkers ON 01-17-1991

Section I
General

Purpose and Scope — This manual is designed for the use of the fireteam leader in training members of the fireteam in missions which pass through HELLMOUTH and into the LONG STAIRS. It is to be used as a guide to achieve orderly, disciplined, and efficient execution of action, and precision, accuracy, and speed in the service of target identification, threat suppression, and retreat with minimal losses.
Training Principles — Training in fireteam drills will stress the importance of the prompt execution of results-driven protocol (RDP) at all times, the necessity of following stochastic modeling (SM) of LONG STAIRS layout, proper consideration of and defenses against memetic and antimemetic (MAM) threats, and new-threat mindset (NTM).

Section II
Fireteam Composition

Composition — The fireteam should consist of five (5) members: a fireteam commander, a battle wizard, a medic and specialist in biological manipulations (hereafter referred to as a medic), a designated artillery unit, and an untrained rookie (hereafter referred to as a rook). The rook’s inclusion is part of RDP.
Formations — The fireteam commander and designated artillery unit form a front rank, three paces in front of the back rank, which consists of the battle wizard to the left of the rook and medic to the right of the rook. Where possible, ranks will be at a close interval (2 feet). In scenarios where this formation cannot be maintained, such as a narrow corridor, the fireteam commander should go first.
Supplemental Forces — In the event missing personnel are encountered in the LONG STAIRS, extra personnel will temporarily join the fireteam. Extra personnel will form an additional rank between the normal ranks of the fireteam. Movement through the LONG STAIRS with more than five people is not advised.
Equipment — Each fireteam will be outfitted with weapons and equipment prior to any mission. Weapons and equipment with LSP designations will be assigned to team members only after proper training and analysis. LSP functionality may change in the course of an exploration action, and in that case, multiple pieces of LSP which fulfill the same role should be taken in order to ensure coverage of needs.

Section III
Results Driven Protocol

Definitions — Results-driven protocols are created by the War Department through consultation with rigorous data analysis of fireteam actions over hundreds of exploration actions (delves). For a list of specific results-driven protocols, see the current RDP document. Individual RDP are given RDP designators.
Protocol — Results-driven protocols are expected to be followed without deviation or question. Fireteam members who fail to follow RDP are subject to immediate extermination at the discretion of the fireteam commander. If the fireteam commander fails to follow RDP, he may be put on immediate leave by the medic. RDP are often given without explanation, and it is often the case that no explanation is known to the War Department.
Classification — Some RDP are classified and known only to the fireteam commander or specific members of the fireteam.
Collection — After-action reports are a vital part of developing new RDP. All fireteam members are obligated to provide full, complete, and honest accounts of the event of any exploration action (delve).

Section IV
Mapping and Stochastic Modeling

Definitions — The LONG STAIRS consists of a series of rooms and doors. Every room has at least one door, and every door leads to another room. The connections between rooms and doors are not consistent. Connections between rooms cannot be locked or held open (see LSP #0019). The LONG STAIRS cannot be mapped, but the randomness of the LONG STAIRS can be predicted.
Stochastic Modeling — Analysis of doors and rooms can allow for prediction of subsequent doors and rooms in a traversal. Stochastic Modeling (SM) is the primary method of LONG STAIRS navigation. Once the fireteam is past HELLMOUTH, determining location is impossible, but it is still possible to determine which direction is most likely to produce movement across probability distributions.
Maps — Both the fireteam commander and the medic are tasked with consultation of maps provided by the War Department. Maps should be verified at regular intervals for contamination from memetic or antimemetic (MAM) threats using standard protocols. Observations of rooms should be made whenever they are cleared.
Rooms — Rooms range in size from one hundred (100) square feet to six hundred thousand (600,000) square feet. Rooms have between one (1) and forty-eight (48) doors. Rooms are typically one (1) floor, but those with up to ten (10) stories have been observed. All numbers are currently known upper bounds. Rooms may contain sentients, entities, and/or entity items.
Landings — Landings are special areas of the LONG STAIRS consisting of multiple rooms and open areas that do not show the same variability as the rest of the LONG STAIRS. All known landings are inhabited. All landings require special protocols. The current number of known Landings is four (4), but this is a lower bound.
Distance — The concept of distance is incoherent in the Long Stairs. Instead, the metrics of probability are used. Areas where doors are less probable to lead to HELLMOUTH are considerably more dangerous and more likely to be populated with phenomena, entities, and sentients of a higher threat level.

Section V
Phenomena, Entities, and Sentients

Phenomena — Phenomena contrary to established understanding of the world exist within the Long Stairs. These phenomena can be divided into Pervasive Phenomena (PP), those which exist through the Long Stairs, and Individual Phenomena (IP), those which are present only in specific rooms or items. Phenomena are given LSP designators. Some phenomena cannot or should not be recorded.
Entities — Entities are the primary hostile found within the Long Stairs and the primary cause of mission failure and/or casualties. Entities vary greatly in size, number, and abilities. Entities are given LSE designators. Unknown entities should be approached with extreme caution. Some entities cannot or should not be recorded.
Sentients — Sentients are any entity within the Long Stairs which thinks like a human, including humans. Known varieties of sentients are given a Sentient Class (SC). Individual sentients are given LSS designators. Sentients are often found moving between rooms of the Long Stairs. On interrogation, they will show a coherent but false understanding of the world.

“Too long, didn’t read,” said Craig, though he was still skimming it as he said it.

“How long did this take?” asked Arthur, looking over the document. He looked up at me. “Are we supposed to follow this?”

“Not really, no,” I said. “I was thinking I’d mention stuff when it came up. And I’m not going to actually make a list of a thousand entities or phenomena or rules, because I’m not insane.”

“I’m confused about RDP,” said Craig, staring down at the paper.

“Remote Desktop Protocol?” asked Reimer.

“It’s basically a long list of things that you have to do in certain cases,” I said, ignoring him. “Even if it makes no sense, and maybe even if it doesn’t make sense to the people who made the protocol. Example?”

“Sure, example?” asked Craig.

“Okay,” I said. “The War Department’s been sending in fireteams since pretty much the beginning of this whole thing, after a few other things didn’t work. They’ve been taking in after-action reports, making lists of rooms, doors, entities, sentients, whatever. Mortality rates are fucking terrible, but it’s the most exciting thing that the military has ever seen, and some seriously powerful magic can be pulled from the Long Stairs, so they’re fine making the whole thing a mass grave if they have to. Anyway, one day, some guy is sitting around looking at these reports, and he notices something he’s noticed before, which is a fireteam seeing a white mouse — and killing it.”

“Why’d they kill it?” asked Arthur. He was always good about asking the questions I obviously wanted asked.

“Because they were spooked,” I said. “Or they were worried it was going to turn into a monster and eat them or something. Hard to say. So, he looks at this other report he’d seen, which says, basically, the same thing, that the team saw a white mouse and immediately killed it. So then he goes looking through all the reports, and by this point there are hundreds of them, and he finds seven more matching descriptions, all of them talking about a white mouse, found in different rooms, but immediately killed by the fireteam. He goes around asking questions, seeing if anyone knows anything, seeing if the grunts can tell him much, and eventually, after scratching his head, he comes to a curious conclusion: no one has seen a white mouse in the Long Stairs without killing it within five minutes.”

“So … mental effect?” asked Reimer, looking up from the paper. “Compulsion or something?"

“A good first thought,” I said, giving him my most ‘elementary, dear Watson’ voice. “But no, they ran a test. They gave orders to half the fireteams, saying, basically, if you see a white mouse, you let it live, and capture it if you can. To the other half, they gave the order to kill it with prejudice within five minutes. The test was called off after two weeks though, because TFMs — that’s Total Fireteam Mortality — had nearly doubled for the group that was told to not kill the mouse. They had no idea what was happening or why, but they didn’t want to keep throwing away lives and resources, so they put in the first Long Stairs Protocol, LSP #0001, White Mouse Protocol. If you see a mouse, you kill it immediately, before any other task, including fighting hostiles.”

“And no one knows why?” asked Reimer. “So there are a bunch of random rules that someone came up with by looking at the logs and thinking to themselves, hey, looks like that worked?”

I nodded.

“And … in practice?” asked Reimer. “In the game?”

“In practice,” I said. “I’ll tell you the rules when they come up. Sometimes you’ll come into a room, and I’ll say ‘oh, RDP says that you have to do this’. You won’t know why, either because you weren’t briefed, or because the people who wrote the rule don’t know either. Some of the RDP have had follow-up studies to try to figure out why the effect is there, but those studies cost lives, and if it’s not a big deal, the War Department thinks it’s better to just canonize a new rule.”

“You know that the War Department was a real thing, right?” asked Craig. “Disbanded in like … 1946?”

“1947,” I replied. “There was a secret provision in the restructuring act, and for reasons of both fudging the budget, staying covert, and having a place within the then-new National Military Establishment, which would later be renamed —”

“Is this relevant?” asked Reimer.

“Not even a little,” I said, smiling at him. I turned back to Craig. “It was renamed to the Department of Defense, or DoD.”

“We know what the DoD is,” said Craig.

“Right,” I said. “And the War Department is subordinate to that for the purposes of this game, though like I said, not gonna matter, just kind of … there, if you want to poke around a bit. For all I know, we’re going to start with this as delving into an endless shifting dungeon and end with you guys trying to assassinate the president of the United States.”

“Which is still Obama?” asked Arthur. “Because I mean, we’re technically in alt history, right?”

“Technically,” I shrugged. “But the kind of alt history that’s completely unnoticed by people on the ground? Like, a world that’s got us in it somewhere.”

“I love this,” said Arthur. “It’s got that new campaign smell to it, a Juniper that’s all full of energy and enthusiasm.”

“I’ll probably hate it in a month,” I said. “It’s not meant to be a long-term one. But right now, yeah, I’m eager.”

“I’ve got a ton of questions,” said Reimer. “Especially about party composition, and if we’re all meant to be soldiers brought in by this ‘War Department’.”

“It’s not meant to be that strict,” I said. “I mean, if you want to do a bunch of research on military stuff, sure, great, but there’s a lot of leeway because of both the Long Stairs and RDP. You have to be from Earth, but you can be twisted and warped by whatever forces are in the Long Stairs, and if you want a background that’s not just ‘soldier’, you can have some other thing that got you brought into the program, like a doctor or a math PhD, and we can run with it.”

“This is going to be amazing,” said Arthur. “I love it.”

And it was amazing, at least for a time. I’d written out a bunch of stuff for it in a spurt of creativity, rooms for them to go through, entities and phenomena for them to encounter, arbitrary rules they have to follow as part of RDP, weird experiences … and then after a handful of sessions, I started leaning harder into the arbitrariness and pointlessness of war, the way soldiers were treated as cannon fodder for the whims of political and business interests, the way nothing ever got better, or changed at all, not when it came to the endless state of war. The War Department didn’t understand the denizens of the Long Stairs, and was making things harder for basically everyone involved. The problem with this, from the perspective of the players, was that it wasn’t actually very fun, and if they weren’t having fun, then I usually wasn’t either, and eventually everyone felt like it was a grind, so we stopped.

The second time we played, there was no attempt to make it ‘about’ anything, it was just room after room of monsters, traps, and unfair things, nothing super creative, nothing that was making an effort to be cool, and if anyone had fun with it, it must have been more about their own mindset than what I was bringing to the table.

“We’ll be at the ‘bottom’ of the stairs,” I had said at an early planning meeting, three years prior. “Except that the Long Stairs weren’t really designed to have a ‘bottom’ or a ‘top’, it was more … who am I explaining this for?” It was all in the copious notes I’d given to Amaryllis, and she had translated it all into a more ordered document, with my input.

“Pallida,” said Amaryllis, nodding in her direction.

“Because she refuses to read background material?” I asked.

“I don’t refuse, but come the fuck on, put it in language a twelve-year-old could understand,” said Pallida. “The fuck is with you people and your ‘probability distribution gradients’, fuck off with that.”

“The terminology is wrong,” said Grak.

“Is it?” I asked. “I mean, it’s a gradient, in the sense of an increase or decrease of some property from point to point, right?”

“Mmm,” replied Grak.

I looked at Pallida. “Fine. The point is … you’re in the Long Stairs, you’re looking at a door, and you take a look at the various features of the door, and the room that you’re in. You take everything into account, the width of the door, the height, the types of hinges, whether it swings in or out, the material it’s made of, whether it has a cross brace, everything. You look at the room and how many chairs it has, whether stuff is oriented with the walls, whether there’s some moss, all kinds of things like that. That doesn’t let you know what’s behind the door, but it does let you know what might be behind the door. You’ve got a list of options with probabilities listed next to them. Since the Long Stairs haven’t been run an infinite number of times, you don’t know what the actual probabilities are, especially for the more rare variety of doors, and maybe it won’t be anything that’s on your list.” I took a breath. “Navigation then, if you want to get to a specific area of the Long Stairs, like one of the Landings, or back to Hellmouth where you come in, or a specific room, is a matter of picking doors which maximize your odds of opening up a room which might have a door that might lead you to where you want to go.” I stared at Pallida. “Does that help?”

“The rooms repeat,” she said.

“Yes,” I nodded. “But … also not. In terms of lore, there were supposed to be more than ten thousand cataloged, and you’d encounter the most common rooms quite a bit, but in any individual delve you’re likely to encounter at least two or three new ones, which help refine the probabilities, assuming you survive. When I ran it, I actually wrote a little script that would go through different rooms, doors, and scenarios.”

“Neat,” said Pallida, rolling her eyes in a way that made me suspect that she didn’t find it neat.

“It wasn’t actually programming,” said Amaryllis. “It was just randomly pulling things from an array in javascript.”

“Well,” I said. “Yeah. More complicated than that, in my opinion.” I felt slightly deflated, but also like it was probably necessary that I be deflated. Anything that I could whip up in an afternoon was probably not actually impressive.

“We don’t have what they had,” said Amaryllis. “We have no map of probabilities, not like a fireteam should canonically have. So how are we going to find Uther? How are we even going to navigate?”

“We have the uniform of an American soldier,” I said. “TFMs are canonically common in the Long Stairs, but a lot of them are assumed rather than actual, and you sometimes get people lost, trying to find their way back without a map, which wouldn’t help us, or who have gone crazy, which might. And if the relief on the door is anything to go by, we might be able to just get to the first — last — Landing and work out a deal with the denizens there, or find some clues.” The fourth landing, if I remembered it right, probably wouldn’t have anything we could use, but the third might. “That’s two methods. Actually finding Uther, if he’s still got on the amulet of non-detection, which it seems like he does, would be an issue, but I think we can at least solve general navigation.”

“You’re actually optimistic,” said Amaryllis.

“He likes talking about his games,” said Raven.

“Not games,” said Grak. “Ideas.”

“I’m going to take this as complimentary,” I said.

“It was,” said Raven, giving me a smile that faded quickly. “But I’m not optimistic.”

“On the plus side,” I said. “It was a pretty low level campaign, no more than level ten, in D&D terms. And we should be going in with almost all the firepower Aerb has to offer.”

“There’s nothing beyond these walls,” said Bethel, reaching out to touch one with her illusory arm. She had largely been ignoring me, and I had largely been ignoring her. I think the reality that we were close to Uther was setting in for both of us.

“It’s all magically inert,” said Grak. He waved his hand briefly. “Velocity wards should still work.” I flashed on my magic vision with what scraps of vibration magic I still had left after the fight, just to confirm and get a sense of what he was seeing. While it was on, I glanced at the toad on my shoulder. He looked at me, and then slowly licked his own eyeball. For all I could tell, he wasn’t in the slightest bit magical.

“Sense deadening?” asked Amaryllis, looking at me. Next to Bethel, I had the best senses, and I also knew as much as anyone about the Long Stairs.

“No,” I said, taking my eyes off the toad. “The rooms don’t really, uh, exist without us. Our presence is what makes the Long Stairs. Anyone you meet, aside from those who have delved, is created the moment you open a door, and vanishes as soon as you leave their presence. Nothing will ever come through a door and surprise you, unless it’s a fireteam. Oh, or if you open a door on a monster and try to close the door, that doesn’t work. Landings are the other exception. I don’t know. It’s a giga-dungeon, and I think we should be at the tail end of it, at least, uh, logically. Not that the Long Stairs are big on logic.”

“Communications with the outside world aren’t working,” said Bethel, glancing back at the door we came in.

“Radio should still work,” I said. “But every channel is going to be full of various kinds of screaming.” I had always been a fan of that detail. I looked at the door ahead of us. “Be ready for fighting. Lots and lots of fighting, actually. And finding Uther in all this might be a matter of luck.”

The Dorises had used their probability magic in order to find Uther, but given the difficulty we were having, and how faint the signal they’d gotten, I wondered whether what they’d been getting was the probability that he would somehow get back to the room we were now standing in. With a unique dimension like this, it was hard to say. The only reason to think that it might eventually lead to Earth was the uniform we’d found.

“I think the only thing left is to go forward,” I said.

“So we have no idea what’s behind this door,” said Amaryllis, regarding it with understandable mistrust.

“No,” I said. “Or, we know that it will be some kind of room, probably one with a few doors, and then … maybe an entity, meaning a monster, or a sentient, or some phenomenon, or … uh, memetics, antimemetics, maybe a squad of American soldiers who have been warped and twisted by the Long Stairs into orcs and elves and stuff, and are decked out with magically modified rifles.”

Amaryllis nodded. All this was known to everyone, but the Long Stairs Plan (LSP) was something of an addendum to the FSP. The LSP was the only part of it that had survived intact, with the rest wiped out by a powerful antimeme that I had probably deployed, possibly by the mechanism of the vorpal blade, which was now hanging from my belt in a sheath.

“We don’t have a map of any kind,” said Amaryllis. “Our list of entities, sentients, and phenomena are woefully incomplete. We have very limited RDP, and Reimer never played any of it, so this is all coming by way of Juniper’s memories. And even then, it might not match.”

“FS and the door were supposed to be the hard part, weren’t they?” asked Fenn. “I mean, the thinking, in the thingy, was that we would breeze through?”

“I did not, and would never put it like that,” said Amaryllis. She looked around. “Is everyone ready for phase two?”

“Not in the slightest,” said Fenn, smiling at her.

“Ready,” said Grak. “The inability to see beyond the walls is unsettling.”

“Kind of normal though, right?” I asked. “I mean, in terms of how walls work.”

He nodded.

“We need to make sure we don’t go past him,” said Raven. She was staring at the door.

“Well, no sense waiting,” I said, striding forward to the door. I was going ahead, if no one else was. I placed my hand on the door, and Bethel came up beside me, looking human. Though we’d been avoiding each other, I had been getting used to her presence, at least a little bit. She had been in most of the meetings, though we hadn’t been social, and obviously we’d gone through some combat and movement together, during whatever had led up to the events that ended with me in hell. Still. There was a part of me that didn’t trust her, that thought her being reformed was all an act, or even if it wasn’t an act, that people couldn’t actually change. It wasn’t the kind of tension that I really wanted to be carrying into this, but I had done my part in trying to make sure we could have the necessary working relationship.

We were going to have to have a talk before we found Uther.

I put all that aside and opened the door, my primary sword at the ready, and the vorpal blade as back-up.

Bethel blasted the thing in the room down to a cinder before I could even get a good look.

“What was that?” I asked, blinking away the afterimage of lancing fire.

“This,” said Bethel, holding out a hand to display an illusion. She’d done something to the image quality, making it see-through and with some artifacts, which I thought was probably to make clear that she was showing something that she’d seen.

It was a monster of some kind, one with a thick skull plate and enormous tusks. His red hide was dotted with little white bumps, making him seem like he was covered with oversized pimples.

“Okay,” I said, stepping into the room.

The largest rooms of the Long Stairs were as big as the biggest aircraft hangars, so by that standard, this one was mid-sized, maybe a hundred feet by fifty feet, oriented so that the other end of it was the long way away from us. It had a high ceiling and thick sandstone columns to give the ceiling support, and as I walked in, I saw doors placed at regular intervals on the side walls. There was no light but that which was provided by Bethel. The floor was made up of millions of tiny stones with a waxy appearance, mostly red, and they formed an imperfect layer above something wet.

“Which way?” asked Amaryllis.

“That door,” said Fenn, pointing at one of the side doors, though I was pretty sure Amaryllis had been talking to me. “The power of luck compels us.”

“You’re sure?” asked Amaryllis.

“I’ve got a feeling,” Fenn shrugged.

“Then we’ll go through,” I said. “I’m going to check how the other doors look though, just to see if something jogs my memory.”

It took some time to do that, but a lot of the doors had been randomly generated when I’d been running things, and those had left my memory fairly easily. None of the doors I remembered were in this room.

While I was looking around, Grak was making a ‘scan’. If Uther was wearing the amulet of nondetection, then he couldn’t be detected by almost any means, and the amulet itself was under the same power. You could find it, and its wearer, using second order effects, or you could do what Grak was doing, which was creating a focused anti-entad ward that covered the whole room, then rapidly cycling through all entads, with a second ward conditional on the first which would ping him if it started working. All of our gear, plus Bethel and all that she contained, had to be excluded, but in theory, we would be able to find the entad by nullifying it. I had compared it to hitting the “scan” button on a car radio, and Grak hadn’t said that was incorrect. Because wards against a single specific entad were very cheap, and because Grak was boosted by entads and also a phenomenal warder, this process could be repeated for up to a hundred rooms a day, if we didn’t also need other warding.

When Grak gave the all-clear, we went to the door Fenn had picked out. “Alright,” I said. “One down, probably like … a thousand left to go.”

There were, to be clear, a fuckton of rooms. Most of them we didn’t spend more than a few minutes in, just long enough for Grak to run a scan and for us to figure out the gimmick, if there was one. It was, in a sense, classic dungeon crawling, without any constraints on it being logical or possible or fitting in with any coherent theme or aesthetic.

We went through a mail room, one with no obvious place for the mail to go to or to have come from, but lots of letters and packages. The packages were all non-magical curios, while the letters were addressed to us, all from dead people, speaking their piece. We didn’t read them.

We went through a wine cellar, which had hundreds of bottles of wine lined up. A quick look at the labels showed that they were written in an alien tongue, but an analysis by Bethel suggested that it probably was wine. We each drank a bit of wine, which was a part of RDP. I gave the tiniest sip to the toad, because I wasn’t sure whether he was included as a part of the party.

We passed through a very plain ten foot by ten foot room which had two doors on each wall and no other features.

We went into an enormous treasure room, with gold coins piled up all over the place, big jeweled goblets, amulets, and a treasure chest in the center. Absolutely everything in there, down to the last gold coin, was a mimic, and Bethel killed them all.

We went into another very plain ten foot by ten foot room with eight doors.

We went down a six hundred foot corridor, filled with traps that we easily avoided or tanked.

We went through a room that had six lizards in separate stained glass tanks, which we left alone. It also had a white mouse, which we killed immediately.

We went through a room that had a horrible monstrosity with a dozen clawed arms sticking out from bushy hair. Bethel killed it before it could break free from its shackles and attack us.

We went through a room that had a banquet prepared on a long table. According to Bethel, most of it was poisoned, but she picked out a handful of things that seemed like they weren’t, and we ate a bit, because it was part of RDP. Again, I fed the toad a tiny scrap.

We came to a room with thousands of knives hanging from the high ceiling by threads. They fell, and we were protected by Grak’s velocity wards, though we had lots of other protection as well. Grak picked out two of the knives and said they were magic, registering as entads. One was a simple returning knife, at least so far as we could tell, and the other would teleport into a person’s chest if you kept the tip pointed at them for ten seconds. I had been the one to get the knife in the ribs, and Fenn barely apologized at all.

We went through those ten rooms without breaking a sweat. Where there were monsters, Bethel killed them, and following that, Grak would break out his amulet finder. The differences between the rooms were wild, and the whole thing had a feel of being cobbled together without much thought, the kind of thing you’d expect to be spit out of a script written by a teenager and pulled from an array of descriptors and objects. None of them really left an impression. When it was time to pick a door, we went with whatever Fenn said, though she didn’t seem terribly happy to be relegated to the level of door picker.

“Just pretend you’re on Monty Hall,” I said.

“Jesus dick-fucking Christ Juniper,” said Fenn, shaking her head. “First, I get that you love your Earth references, but second, Monty Hall was a guy who hosted a show called Let’s Make a Deal, and third, have you ever even watched an episode?”

“I don’t understand how you’ve seen so much obscure television,” I grumbled. “Besides, I only know it from the Monty Hall problem.”

“It was on network television for nearly thirty years,” said Amaryllis. “Hardly obscure.”

“Yeah, see?” asked Fenn. “Network television. ABC, from 1942 to 1973. Read a book, Joon.”

“None of that was correct,” said Amaryllis.

“Juniper reads books,” said Raven. “That he hasn’t been focusing on the arcana of Earth television seems like it should be to his credit.”

Fenn raised an eyebrow at that, but said nothing, for which I was grateful.

The eleventh room had sentients.

There were a dozen of them, but not all the same. Half were blue-skinned with legs that seemed to fold back and forth with six knees, all dressed in neatly tailored clothing, and blind, or at least without eyes. The other half were tall, pale white, wearing nothing but loincloths, and chained up. As soon as we’d opened the door, they all turned to us, and there was calamitous conversation from them, lots of shouting over each other.

The room itself was a corridor, maybe ten feet across, with only a single door at the other end. The dozen people were between us and it, and we had no way to talk to them, because Amaryllis hadn’t been able to buy or steal one of the Terridoc linkages or similar.

“They’re prisoners,” I said. “The only question is whether they’re justly imprisoned or not, which we’re not in a position to judge.”

“This is our first dilemma room,” said Amaryllis. I nodded.

“Does deep scan show anything?” I asked Bethel.

“Signs of abuse on the tall ones,” she said. “Abrasions and unnatural breaks in the bones that have now healed. But also … it seems like they ate some of the blue people, going by their stomach contents.”

“Is there any reason not to let them go on their merry way?” asked Fenn.

“Would you let slave traders pass?” I asked.

“I mean, they’re not real,” said Fenn. “They were just … randomly generated here. They don’t have a map, do they?”

“No,” said Bethel.

“The point isn’t whether they’re real or not,” I said. “The point of the dilemma rooms, and most of the sentient rooms, is what you do. It’s about you, not them.”

“But,” said Raven. “What we do is influenced by what we think of them. If we think they’re just going to fade out of existence when they close the door behind them, why should that reflect on us?”

“Treat it like it matters,” said Amaryllis. “They were put in front of us for a reason.”

“We don’t have mutually intelligible languages,” I said. “We can’t gather information. I think we have to let them go.”

“They sound like cannibals,” said Grak.

“Technically it’s not cannibalism if it’s another species,” said Fenn.

Through all this, the other group was just standing there, talking amongst themselves and sometimes shouting something unintelligible to us.

“So we let them pass,” I said. They looked like they wanted to pass, and there was only one way for them to be going. “Unless someone can give me a compelling reason not to. And yes, we are inserting ourselves into their business, and yes, we are treating them like people.” Both of those were parts of the overall plan for the Long Stairs, but it was definitely true that less effort had been put into that side of things, probably because we’d all assumed that FS was the more difficult of the two.

We let the people pass, stepping aside for them and ignoring the pleas of the people in chains. I had no idea whether that was the right thing to do or not. Maybe the blue guys were slave traders, or maybe the white guys were criminals, but people being in chains really wasn’t enough. Once they were past us, they went out the door we’d come in through, and from there, it was pretty likely we would never see them again.

“This really doesn’t seem intended for us,” said Raven.

“No?” I asked.

“Yeah,” said Fenn. “It feels like we’re wandering through a campaign that really wasn’t meant for us. It’s uncanny.” She shivered a bit. “Bethel’s just killing everything anyway. It’s not a challenge, it’s just … weird.”

“Weirdness is part of the Long Stairs vibe,” I said.

The fourteenth room we opened was identical to the first room we’d gone in, with the same sandstone columns and the same pimple-skinned creature in the center, which Bethel killed, the same as she had before.

“Alright, looks like I suck at directions,” said Fenn.

“Not necessarily,” I said. “It’s the same room, but it’s also … not. It’s like we were never here, and the doors are different. So like … let’s say we were trying to maximize probability to get to the nearest Landing. Maybe this is the best room to have a chance of getting there, but it didn’t spawn the right door the first time. The best route might have been the one that brought us right back here. In theory, anyway.”

“I’m gonna feel real bad about leading us if it turns out we’re just going in circles,” said Fenn.

“Or it could be a misfire,” I said. “Meaning, maybe the most lucky thing is for us to go in circles and never find Uther at all, for certain values of lucky.”

“I do want to find the guy,” said Fenn. “I mean, not on a personal level, since it seems like there’s going to be a lot of drama, but sure, I want to find him.”

“What a roaring endorsement of your commitment to the mission,” said Amaryllis.

“We might need a different strategy,” said Raven.

“We can follow Fenn’s intuition,” said Amaryllis. “At least for another ten rooms. The only resource we’re spending is time.”

“We’re spending risk,” I said. “Each room is another roll of the dice.”

“Well, not like we actually know how to get out of here, is it?” asked Fenn. “So we don’t really have a choice.”

“We could go faster,” said Bethel.

“I need time to clear,” said Grak.

“We could go faster until we reach something of interest, then double back,” said Bethel.

“That’s not how it works,” I said. “I mean, there’s no doubling back, there’s just, uh, where you currently are.”

“I think it’s worth a try,” said Amaryllis. “We wouldn’t be clearing the rooms, but … in theory, if Uther was trapped here, if we’re not in an extreme time warp right now, then it should be obvious once we come across whatever trapped him, even if we don’t see the man himself.”

“It would mean deviating from the plan,” I said, raising an eyebrow.

“The plan was loose,” said Amaryllis. “Contingent on what we found here.” She raised an eyebrow of her own, and I could feel us having an unspoken conversation.

“Alright,” I said. “We zip through until we find something that can point us in another direction. From what was on the front door, there are four Landings, which is as many as I designed. It’s pretty unlikely we’d be able to skip one, even if it’s possible in theory. We shouldn’t need full dilation.” I looked over at Fenn, then back at Bethel. “You’ll be able to take directions from Fenn?”

Bethel gave me a nod.

“Good,” I said. “Then let’s do it.”

The rooms went faster after that. Fenn called out doors to Bethel, and Bethel blasted through them. I got to see some monsters, only briefly. We passed through another clear ‘dilemma room’, this one with a few malnourished people begging for scraps, and we gave them food, water, and first aid kits. When there was a room with some bit of RDP I remembered, I had us get out and do it. The biggest one was food and drink: if there was something presented to you, everyone had to partake. You didn’t have to every time, but cumulative times missing it would lead to some bad end that I’d never specified to the players. I’d had some idea that a wild person, or group of people, would chase you down through the Long Stairs, trying to pour ale down your throat or stuff your mouth with food until you drowned or choked, but it had never actually come up.

It took us thirteen rooms to get right back to where we started.

“Okay,” I said, as we contemplated that. “Fenn, what’s the most dangerous door?”

“You know that it might be really fucking dangerous, right?” she asked. “I mean, we could pick a medium danger door.”

“Point taken,” I said. “I’m worried that if we do that, we won’t find Uther.”

“Fuck,” said Fenn. She scanned the room. “Alright, fine, that one there, the door with the demon head on it.”

“Uh, no,” I said, looking at the door. It was stylized, the kind of demon you’d expect to see on a Japanese samurai suit in one of those over-exaggerated depictions of feudal Japan. “Pick a different one, that one is against RDP.”

“At least we know inverted luck sense works,” said Amaryllis.

“Wait, what happens if we go through?” asked Fenn. “We just … die?”

“Not necessarily, no,” I said. “But the way RDP works is … did I tell you about that thing with the planes?”

“Looking at bullet patterns?” asked Fenn. “Yeah.”

“I never heard that one,” said Raven.

“Right,” I said. “So, briefly, in World War II, they sent out a bunch of planes, and a bunch of them came back with bullet holes. They were looking at the places the bullet holes were, trying to figure out where to put armor, which they couldn’t put much of on, because they had to worry about weight. They figured out that instead of having to put armor where the bullet holes were, they needed to put armor where the bullet holes weren’t, because those were the places where, if a bullet hit it, the plane just didn’t come back at all.” I gestured at the door. “So that door has been seen before, maybe a hundred times, but no one has ever been recorded as going through it, even though statistically, you’d think that they had. That door is a spot with no bullet holes on the planes that came back.”

“Except that this is all in your head,” said Grak.

“It’s what I know of the Long Stairs,” I said. “But yes, all in my head. We’ll need to encounter some actual soldiers in order to get an understanding of this interpretation of the Long Stairs. Sorry.”

“No need to apologize,” said Grak. “I was clarifying.”

I nodded. “I liked the Long Stairs,” I said. “There were some neat ideas in there.”

“So are we doing the demon door or not?” asked Fenn. “Because it seems like the kind of thing that might have been able to trap the great and terrible Uther Penndraig.”

“We’ll give it more time,” I said. “I’d like another circuit to see whether or not we’re actually going in circles. If we are, we lose an hour, but I think it’s worth it.”

“Sure,” nodded Amaryllis.

Fenn gave me a look, but said nothing. Maybe she was thinking that this was how it was now, that I was comfortable dictating our course of action, even after three years of being gone.

We sailed through the Long Stairs once more. Raven was keeping notes, but I was desperately hoping that we wouldn’t have to make our own map, especially since in the canonical Long Stairs, every bit of information was won with blood.

With Fenn guiding us, it took sixteen rooms to get back to the beginning, again with a different configuration of doors. This time it had a different creature inhabiting it, a serpent large enough to wrap himself around one of the big sandstone pillars. Bethel killed it. We went with a random route after that, avoiding any doors I thought looked like death, and those that Fenn thought were horrible ideas.

It took us twenty rooms to finally find something of note: it was someone dressed in the same outfit as the one I’d pulled from a closet in Glassy Fields, a uniform that was recognizably that of an American soldier. He was, unfortunately, dead, his lower half rent to shreds, though if he’d been alive, I had no idea what I would have said to him. Hey, I’m an American too, can we make a copy of your map? He wasn’t quite human, with the quibble being necessary mostly because of the green hue of his skin and the way his teeth had started growing into tusks. He wasn’t quite like an orc though, because every tooth was a tusk, and they were all competing for space, crowded in together in a way that must have made eating difficult and speaking nearly impossible. The blood was fresh, which it always was in the Long Stairs, because every dead soldier was frozen in the moment they expired, the room waiting, timeless, for someone else to come along and display the body.

“Do we trust this map?” asked Bethel as she moved a hand in front of her, showing a visualization of it. As maps went, it was bizarre, since it was all based on probabilities of getting certain rooms, which might lead to other rooms. There were a few rules layered on top of base probability, ways that a seasoned adventurer could at least navigate between Landings, if nothing else, and of course some pieces of RDP that would presumably avoid a terrible fate.

“Some of this is stirring something in my memory,” I said, looking through the book. “‘RDP #0931: Chair Rule’, I know that one. You’ll end up in a Landing faster if you bail out on rooms that have more chairs than the one you’re in. Uh, ‘RDP #0041: Compulsory Purchase’, always buy something if a vendor offers. ‘RDP #0119: Rug Rule’, all rugs should be rolled up, starting from the short end, before you leave the room, unless there’s furniture on them.” I looked up. “I’m pretty sure I remember writing all these.”

“We’ll need to read through it in full,” said Amaryllis, rubbing her forehead.

“So we do trust it?” asked Fenn.

“No,” said Amaryllis. “But it’s not likely to be a serious detriment if we follow every rule.”

She was technically right, so I held my objections. The memes and antimemes in the Long Stairs meant that information could degrade over time, sometimes in serious ways, but based on what we knew, it was unlikely that we would run into problems from following a corrupted rule, if there was one. The dead body was suspect, but it happened in the Long Stairs, from time to time. It was the nature of the TFMs that they had to be assumed, since the base had no way to track anyone once they were past Hellmouth. It was nearly impossible to recover a corpse.

We each got our own copy of the information in the book, and spent some time reading through it. The clock was ticking back on Aerb, but in theory … well, I was still hopeful that godhood was on the table, but the Dungeon Master hadn’t explicitly said so, and the game stuff seemed to be gone for good, even if the benefits remained.

“Should we have our own rookie?” asked Fenn. “I mean, should we have brought in someone who knew nothing?”

“Does the toad count?” I asked, glancing at the toad. He was still riding on my shoulder, and hadn’t made a single contribution to the discourse. I expected he took after his mother in that regard.

“I don’t know,” said Fenn, eyeing the toad. “Are we sure it’s … I mean, it is a locus, right?”

“Labels,” I said, clucking my tongue. “Just accept his presence.”

I didn’t actually know if he was my son, because Aerb didn’t have paternity tests that could work on a locus, but he seemed content to ride on my shoulder.

“Anyway, about the rookie, we don’t really know,” I said. “We’re coming up the Long Stairs, not down, and what counts as a rookie for us is anyone’s guess. Or, I mean, my guess is probably better than a generic guess, but — no way of knowing, and it would have been hard to get someone almost totally ignorant, then deliver exposition to them when asked, especially because we’re not veterans.”

“He didn’t come here with a fireteam,” said Raven. “He would have known the rules. So why?”

“I don’t know,” I said. “Maybe he thought that he could blast through everything. Maybe he knew that there would have to be goodbyes. Maybe he was doing his best to dodge the narrative, or he had some kind of plan — it’s all guesswork until we actually find him.”

“Which we will,” said Raven, nodding. Her face fell a bit as she looked at the next door. We’d been seeing a lot of doors. “It might take some time though.”

It did, in fact, take a lot of time, and without following Fenn’s hunches, we had a lot worse luck on the rooms. Bethel was incredibly powerful, stuffed full of hundreds or maybe thousands of entads, and she’d been jailbroken as much as possible by Grak, but there were still limits on her offensive power, and we’d started to run into them.

“How was an Earth fireteam supposed to take care of these things?” asked Fenn, after Bethel had been forced to use another of her foot-thick beams of focused energy on a mini-Godzilla. They were one of the few that used charges.

“They weren’t,” I said. “Some of the rooms are just meant to kill the whole team, or make them have to shut the door and try to put distance between themselves and the threat. This kind of thing, you’d probably be able to close the door, hoping that it couldn’t get through, but then it would detach both arms, which would independently go after you as you ran through room after room trying to escape them. But I also want to say that these weren’t normal military fireteams, they’re adventuring parties, with mages, magic items, all kinds of things to help them.”

“And how would Uther have fared, do you think?” asked Raven. “With the amulet of nondetection, he could have walked past a majority of this.”

“I don’t know,” I said. “We’re kind of taking it as a given that he was doing his best to head towards Earth. What stopped him — if anything did stop him, is hard to say. Could be that he’s up on Earth right now, having a grand old time.”

“Unlikely,” said Amaryllis.

“Possible,” said Grak.

They exchanged a look, but said no more, and I had to imagine that this was a conversation that had passed between the two of them a lot during the three years I missed.

We continued on through the endless rooms, following the map as best we could. There was plenty to see, and Fenn had a point, a lot of it would have killed even a well-equipped fireteam outright. Bethel was too powerful though, inviolable, immune to most memes and antimemes, capable of incredible offensive power. I wondered how we would have done the Long Stairs without her, and it seemed like the answer was ‘with great difficulty and pain’.

“Bethel, can we sidebar?” I asked, after she’d killed another monster, this one composed mostly of vaguely vaginal flaps that were letting out clouds of acid.

She looked at me for a moment. “Of course.”

We went to one side of the room while Grak set up his scan, leaving the others to talk amongst themselves. Fenn almost immediately went to Raven, which I wasn’t sure was such a good idea.

“Will the toad be joining us?” asked Bethel.

“Oh,” I said, looking down at where he still sat on my shoulder. “Yeah, I guess.” I looked back at her. “Look,” I said. “About Uther, and what’s going to happen when we find him?”

She raised an eyebrow. “You’re worried that I’ll kill him,” she said. “Or attack him and have it be proven just how much raw power he has.”

“No,” I said. “Valencia wouldn’t have cleared you to go if she’d thought there was a risk of that. And from all accounts, you’ve been living the life you wanted, as a good person.”

“I won’t pretend I don’t know where your skepticism comes from,” said Bethel. “I understand it.”

“But when we find him,” I said. “If we eventually do?”

She looked at me. “Did Valencia tell you that I still have an instinct toward violence?” she asked.

“She, uh, did,” I said. “Hopefully she didn’t say that in confidence.”

“I don’t think the problem is Uther,” she said, looking past me toward the others for a moment. “I think the problem is me. Of course he’s responsible for the way I am, responsible for leaving me empty, for adding in so many entads I didn’t want, for bonding with me and then removing himself entirely, but … his part in my life is over. I’ll confront him, if I get the chance. I’ll tell him what a shit he was. I’ll try to make him understand how horrible it was for me, and how he could have and should have done better. Perhaps it will help me a bit, but I rather doubt it. Valencia helped me to see that placing the responsibility on myself was better for me. Blaming Uther was a way of not taking responsibility for my own thoughts and actions.”

“That’s very mature,” I said.

“No,” she replied. “Understanding the philosophy doesn’t require much maturity. Repeating it back is something a parrot could do. Living it, there’s the rub. These past three years, I haven’t been challenged, so aside from the assurances of my soul-challenged colleague, it’s hard to say whether I’m any better. I’ll accept the compliment once I’ve been put to the test. But I will do my best. I don’t intend any harm to Uther. If I hadn’t promised Amaryllis, if I thought I wasn’t needed, I wouldn’t have even come.”

“Okay,” I said. I sighed. “Thank you.”

“I appreciate the second chance you’ve given me,” said Bethel, bowing her head. “I know that you didn’t have much choice, but being able to have a civil conversation …” she looked up at me. “I wish that I could undo what was done.”

“Yeah,” I said. I shifted from one foot to the other. A part of me wanted to apologize, but I didn’t owe that to her. “I do think he deserves a confrontation from you,” I said, changing gears. “Maybe even retribution, but at least to be called out, and hopefully, I guess, he would change. I just wanted to make sure that things were in order,” I said.

Bethel nodded, then when I had no more to say, she walked back over to the group.

I looked over at the toad, which was possibly my son. “We have some history,” I said to him. “Sorry, a lot of that probably went over your head.”

He stared at me, then tensed up for a moment and let out a little squeak of a fart.

“Gross,” I said, smiling at him.

A Certain Kind of Longing

Naturally, the easy ride couldn’t last long, but at least it was for a reason we’d seen coming.

“Halt,” I said, and Bethel spat us back out, into a room with cerulean blue tiles and a large bathtub in the middle, one with an octopus that hadn’t done anything yet. I was keeping my eye on him though, since he had a shifty look to him.

“Problem?” asked Amaryllis.

“I’ve lost still magic,” I said. “Bethel, run a diagnostic check, please. Grak, same.”

“Three entads are non-functional,” said Bethel, frowning at me.

“I believe still magic and air magic are … missing,” said Grak.

“Okay,” I nodded. “I was kind of wondering whether something like this would happen.”

“You were?” asked Amaryllis, narrowing her eyes at me.

“Not before we came in,” I replied. “But seeing how little true resistance there was … yeah.”

“And what’s the theory?” she asked.

“Well … one of the core premises of the Long Stairs is that it gets worse the further down you go,” I said. “I mean, it doesn’t have a true ‘down’, but as you go from room to room, it’s less likely that you’ll be able to get back to base, so up and down are proxies for whatever you’d call that. You go down, you find better loot, tougher monsters, and have less of a chance of making it back. Things get more magical, and some of those magical things stop working when you bring them up, or they only work ‘past’ a certain Landing, or … we never really did that much with that aspect of the game, because players hate it when they lose items or powers, but it was always meant to be there, just to make sure that there was some kind of incentive to go ‘deep’. Otherwise you’d just sit there next to Hellmouth, opening and closing the front door until you got something good, minimizing danger.”

“That doesn’t help me connect the dots,” said Amaryllis, still frowning at me.

“It gets more magical the further down the Long Stairs you get,” I said. “We’re at the far end, so the further up we go, the less magical it gets. That includes all of the magic that we already have, which is considerable.”

I was worried the frown would stay etched on her face.

“It works on the object level,” I said. “Because it’s a known quantity of the Long Stairs. But I think it’s also meant to be there on a narrative level, because my guess is we’ll be losing powers faster than the dungeon will be getting safe. By the time we reach Hellmouth, if we end up having to go that far, we might be struggling to fight off a band of goblins.”

“Fuck,” said Amaryllis.

“I do think we’ll be alright,” I said.

“Bows aren’t magic,” nodded Fenn.

“No, it’s not that,” said Amaryllis. “It’s that I should have seen it coming. I should have figured it out before you, once we were here, or before. I wasn’t thinking in terms of structure. I’d considered the possibility of loss of powers, naturally, but not in the context of story shape. This helps things click into place.”

“We could lose warding?” asked Grak. It wasn’t often he sounded worried. He often was worried, but usually he delivered it in a flat tone.

“Maybe,” I said. “I would have thought we’d lose the most powerful first, but still magic and air magic … that I don’t know about. Still magic is my greatest defensive power. Air magic kind of sucks.”

“Uther would have lost the use of his entads?” asked Raven.

“Maybe,” I said. “When you think about it, it might be a clue as to where he got trapped in the Long Stairs. At a certain point, something as powerful as the amulet of nondetection would shut off, so in theory, that means that he’s somewhere before the ‘first’ Landing. Maybe.”

“I have this sick feeling that we’re going to have to open one of the danger doors,” said Fenn.

“He should have known,” I replied. “I mean, he played the campaign. There were some changes, but the stuff I know is probably the same stuff he knew. I guess he never played the second iteration of it, but I didn’t add that much, mostly just new generators and some ideas I’d been kicking around since before he died.”

“Okay,” said Fenn. “First, I reserve the right to say I told you so, and second, I’m not actually arguing in favor of a danger door, they seem like they suck, I’m just saying I have a bad feeling that’s what we end up doing.”

We went through more rooms, room after room, door after door, following the instructions in the book as best we could, ‘moving’ in the ‘direction’ of the ‘nearest’ Landing. Some of that was just taking the right doors, but we were also looking for lichen growing on pillars, the number of chairs in each room, the hue of the lanterns or lights, all kinds of things. It went faster than it should have, with Bethel killing everything, but it was still fairly slow.

I lost water magic, and though it hadn’t been extending into the other rooms, its loss was immediately noticeable. We stopped to do another diagnostic, to make sure we hadn’t lost anything else.

“It feels like the Library,” said Raven.

“In what way?” I asked.

“In how arbitrary it is,” she replied. “In the endless sets of rules that have to be carefully uncovered. It’s random at first blush, but the more you experience it the more you’re able to find the patterns in it, until eventually you’re navigating it through your sense of it alone. In the Library, we have magic to help us find the patterns, and it resets whenever we leave, but here … in theory you could uncover every pattern, map every room, have perfect probabilistic knowledge of what’s behind every door before you open it.” She looked over at me. “The focus on memes and antimemes is even the same.”

It was possible we had run across some without knowing it. Bethel was blurring all the text we could see and running things through a filter. Bethel wasn’t immune to all memes, we didn’t think, but she was immune to a lot. Anything that could affect a book could in theory affect her, but Raven’s estimation was that there were a lot of things that affected books but didn’t affect Bethel. In terms of the antimemes, her sensorium was so large that it would have to be really all-encompassing for her to not notice. We were coming into the Long Stairs pretty stacked.

I did wonder how Uther had done, and why he’d chosen to do this alone. He’d had his Knights, who would have been invaluable in a dungeon crawl, and if he’d wanted to, he could have set up shop at the door and sent his own fireteams in. He’d elected not to do that.

We went through another fifty rooms before we got to the Landing. I lost gem magic and fire magic along the way. The deterioration was alarming but coming to be more expected. We hadn’t lost any vital entads, but Bethel was diminished, with less and less offensive and defensive punch. Just prior to the Landing, she’d lost the ability to be inviolable, which was worrying.

The Landing was one I’d thought up, thankfully, and not some new area. It was a semi-aquatic place with lots of octopus people, none of whom spoke English. I’d taken a lot of inspiration from what I knew about Asian wet markets, which admittedly wasn’t much. As soon as we were through the door, the smell of fish would have smacked me in the face if I was being stupid enough to breathe in particulates. Arrayed before us were lots and lots of colorful stalls, each of them with some kind of aquatic thing in front. I saw mussels, bits of coral, fish, oysters, lampreys, and in a few cases, seaweed. There were other, more exotic things too, some of which might have been from Earth, but weren’t recognizable to me, giant long claws of something, fronds that were still moving, and a creature with suckers trying to escape from its tank. More wares were hung from the sides of the stalls, much of it looking mundane but unrecognizable. I saw wooden-handled bits with squiggly metal pieces sticking out, and it was almost something you’d see on Earth. The wet market wasn’t all there was to the Landing either. There were coves that the octopus people who ran the stalls called home, places of recreation, all kinds of things, but the wet market was the only place I’d expected players to go, and it had gotten most of the attention.

The octopus people weren’t anthropomorphic octopuses, they were people made of octopuses, maybe five or ten octopuses each. The original concept had been brain suckers, except that the brain suckers were sucking each other, like some kind of brain sucker orgy that somehow managed to have enough cognition to approximate a person, if you were being generous about what you called a person.

“We really don’t have a universal translator?” I asked. “In D&D, that’s a first level spell.”

“Sorry Joon,” said Amaryllis. “I did send Pallida after the Terridoc linkages, but after a year of trying, she wasn’t able to make it happen.”

“No, sorry,” I said. “I didn’t mean to be flippant, it’s just … going to make this harder than it should be. Don’t let them slip an octopus on you.”

“Does this technically qualify as Japanese?” asked Fenn as she looked around. “Lots of hentai-looking monsters.”

“Uh, Asian inspired, definitely,” I said. “But thought up by someone who has never been to Asia and didn’t really want to do a bunch of research.”

“So like you did with elves, got it,” said Fenn.

“I’m serious about the octopuses,” I said. “They might try to sell you one, or just stick one on you, and — it was all in the briefing, I’ll shut up.” I cut myself off before Fenn ended up rolling her eyes out of her head.

“Per our notes, everyone needs to split up and make a purchase,” said Amaryllis. “It’s unclear if that includes Bethel or the toad.”

“Well I’m not letting him wander around on his own,” I said.

Amaryllis nodded. “Just barter for whatever you feel like and then we can leave.”

“Be on the lookout for something that can help tell us where Uther is,” I said.

“In a fucking wet market?” asked Fenn.

“Stranger things have happened,” I said, gesturing out at the octopus people and their wares.

We weren’t the only ‘customers’. There were other people milling about and looking at the goods, sometimes engaging in pantomime and barter with the octopus people. There were lots of species in the Long Stairs, including the white and blue guys we’d seen earlier, who were getting along in this context, or at least not actively eating or enslaving one another, and the felheim, who were stationed out of a later Landing. The designs — and that was the frame I was looking at them through — were as far away from humanoid as you could get while still calling them humanoid, and the whole place couldn’t have been done with human actors in rubber suits. There were skinny, triple-jointed arms, ten-foot tall people stooping so they wouldn’t hit their heads, and a creature that used balloon sacks to float above the floor. I watched a woman with hairy forearms waddle by me, and tried not to stare at the pups hanging off her six exposed boobs.

“This place is bizarre,” I said to Amaryllis. We had both set off and ended up walking down the same aisle. “The whole Long Stairs is, it’s so … transitory. It’s a dungeon crawl taken to the limits, bits of unmoored worldbuilding, species that don’t actually exist, they’re just … decoration.” My eyes were moving around the room. “On Aerb you could look at a crystal floating by and dig into it, you know? You could learn about the magic, how it had been used, where the partial exclusion zone was, all kinds of things like that. Here it’s just detritus. Some of it is literally just taken from single lines of a doc I had for ideas that needed development.”

“It’s coming at the same time you’ve lost access to the game,” she replied as her eyes drifted over a sheaf of eyeballs, which had been braided together using the optic nerves. “It’s not a coincidence.”

“Tell me what you’re thinking,” I said. “It’s a breakdown of order?”

“The common thread is things being stripped away,” said Amaryllis. “Not just the game layer, not just the wider world, but pieces of magic too. It’s a flensing.” She looked at me. “Companions are probably next.

“You think there’s a risk of death?” I asked.

“I don’t know,” she replied. “I think at the end, it will be you and Arthur, alone together. It’s possible you’ll have to make a choice.”

“Maybe,” I replied. I didn’t know exactly what kind of choice she was thinking, but my mind immediately went to the hard choices. If it came down to saving Arthur or saving her … I would probably save her. Or maybe the choice could be something different, like choosing to reject godhood, or choosing to go back to Earth, but it was hard to think of what might be in front of me.

“Look,” said Fenn, coming up to us. “It’s a thingy.” She was carrying what looked a bit like a parasol, except where there should have been fabric there was black mesh, and there didn’t seem to be any way to unfold it. “It only cost me ten thousand dollars.”

“Actual American dollars?” I asked.

“Yup,” she replied. “I always keep a fat stack of cash in my pocket, just in case. I was also offered a tiny octopus to place on my head, which I declined.” She sighted down the end of the parasol, holding it like a gun, which for all I knew, it was.

“We’ll make our barters soon and then get out of here,” said Amaryllis. She looked at me. “Per protocol, we should split up.” She slipped her arm into Fenn’s and they took off together, leaving me alone.

I really was hoping for a map to Uther, or failing that, something that would help us. The wet market wasn’t just seafood, but it was a rare stall that didn’t have a tank full of something in front of it. I was looking for maps, or at least something on paper, though without Bethel filtering things, it was remotely possible that anything I read would endanger me. The Landings were supposed to be relatively safe though.

I wondered how much the toad counted as a part of our team for the purposes of the wet market, or the Long Stairs in general. For the most part, he hadn’t moved from my shoulder, and just made a clicking sound every once in a while.

I was looking at a bunch of small, bright yellow fish in one of the tanks when the octopus people spoke to me.

“Hello, what can I get for you?” they asked.

I stared at them, not sure which of the sets of eyes to look at. Everything was quite moist in the wet market. The tuung would have loved it. “You speak English?” I asked.

“Oh,” they replied. “No, I speak only Anglish, sorry.”

“They’re practically the same language,” I said, not really sure why I was getting into it with them. “Wait,” I said. “Sorry, you speak Anglish, how is that possible?”

“I speak many languages,” the pile of octopuses replied. It was hard to get a handle on where it was speaking from, or how, and that was with me using vibration magic to check. “Those are babel fish in front of you. They’re very rare, and available for a good trade.”

“Babel fish,” I said, pointing down at the tank with the bright yellow fish. “Meaning … fish capable of letting you hear any language?” That still wouldn’t have explained how the octopus pile spoke Anglish.

“Ah, no, my apologies, I’m afraid not,” they replied, wiggling some tentacles. “These fish, if put into your ear, will make everything another person says sound like gibberish.”

“Ah,” I replied. “Babble fish. And if two people with babble fish in their ears talk to each other, they’re suddenly mutually intelligible?”

The octopus pile swayed from side to side. “No.”

“Okay,” I said. “And … why do I want that?”

“I don’t know your business,” replied the octopus pile. “Why do you want them?”

I looked down at the fish. “Uh,” I said. “I guess … it would help to keep me from hearing things I didn’t want to hear?”

They burst into applause, which in this case was a bunch of tentacles wetly slapping against equally wet flesh. “Very good! I hadn’t thought of that.”

“But then why,” I began, then thought better of it. “Alright, I’ll buy one. But, you need to explain to me how you speak Anglish.”

“You drive a hard bargain!” they hummed. “What do you have to offer?”

I had an extradimensional space, and I started pulling things from it. Almost everything I had was for either combat or utility of some kind, and the octopus person didn’t seem to want any of it. I’d thought a length of rope might be up their alley, or maybe a small bell and a piece of string, but they kept waving their tentacles and saying ‘no’. I wondered how long this could go on without them getting bored and shooing me away, but apparently this particular clump of octopuses had a lot of patience for the bartering process.

“You should offer him a hot dog,” said Fenn as she approached me.

“A what?” I asked.

“From the wishes?” she asked. “Or did you use them all?”

I stared at her for a bit. “I was kind of saving them,” I said. “Also, I maybe forgot about them a little bit.” It was pretty rare for them to come up.

“I remember you were really intent on hoarding them,” nodded Fenn. “So if you don’t want to try using one now, I’d understand. Maybe in the future there will be something you need ninety-seven hot dogs for, and you’ll only have ninety-six hot dog wishes, yeah?”

“Uh,” I said. “I guess.” I held out my hand. “I’m not even sure if it will work.” I stared at my hand for a moment. “I wish for a hot dog.”

A very plain cafeteria hot dog materialized in my hand. I looked it over for a bit, then offered it to the octopus pile, which lunged forward so quickly I almost drew my sword and sliced it up. They plucked the hot dog from my hand and slipped it between the octopus bodies, then immediately went to work preparing one of the babble fish for me. I have no idea why I’d been expecting the fish to be put into a small plastic bag, but the octopus person deftly slipped it into a small glass bowl instead, and pushed a cork into the top of it.

“And the other half?” I asked. “How did you come to learn Anglish?”

The pile of octopuses wavered slightly. “A man came through here, some time ago,” they said. “We plopped onto his head for a bit and learned Anglish from him."

“You extracted memories from him?” I asked. “Will he — would he still be able to speak Anglish?”

The octopus pile wavered. “It would come back to him,” they said.

“Describe him, please,” I replied.

“He was a tall man in simple armor,” they replied. “He carried a sword. He had curly hair that was hard to dig into, and two times he had a wife with the legs of a spider.”

“Uther Penndraig,” I said, frowning. And his wife? What?

“Yes,” nodded the pile of octopuses. “That was his name. He came through here five times.”

“Wait,” I said. “Five times?” Fenn was standing beside me, giving the pile of octopuses a skeptical look.

“All some time apart,” they replied, bobbing.

“How long ago?” I asked.

“Time,” they replied, wiggling slightly and flapping their tentacles around. “Hundreds of years?”

“Are you,” I started, then squinted slightly. “Immortal?”

“We pass down knowledge,” they replied. “The better to serve our customers.”

“Huh,” I said. “So, hundreds of years ago, this guy came through, five times?”

“Coming and going,” bobbed the octopus. “Years apart. Not always with the woman. But, time,” they wiggled and flapped again.

“Alright,” I said, casting a glance at Fenn.

“This thing was on Uther’s head?” asked Fenn. “An intentional clue for us, or … what?”

“Unknown,” I said. “He might have been going through here blind. I can’t remember if the Landing made it into any of the sessions he played.” I turned to the octopus person. “Actually, can I have a second fish for another hot dog?”

It wobbled in what I assumed was confirmation. As soon as I produced another hot dog, it lunged forward and grabbed it again, then produced a second bowl for me.

“This one is for you,” I said, holding the bowl up for the toad on my shoulder and removing the cork to let him see.

Without missing a beat, the toad shot his tongue out of his mouth and snatched the small fish up. It took him a bit to eat it, and Fenn and I watched him the whole time.

“You’re the last one,” said Amaryllis. She was holding a small gilded pen, which seemed like it must have been expensive, or possibly had been traded away for pocket lint. “We’re all done.” She pointed at the bowl. “What’s that?”

“Babble fish,” I said. “Makes everything into gibberish if you put it in your ear. Also, that creature spoke Anglish, and I think probably sat on Uther’s head for a bit.”

“Uther, at the height of his power, would only do that intentionally,” said Raven, who had come through the wet market to us.

“I don’t think he was at the height of his power,” I said. “Five times through this Landing would mean three times in total, if he came through both coming and going, which wouldn’t necessarily need to happen. Also, they said his wife was with him, or at least someone with spider legs, which really narrows it down.”

“Let me talk to him,” said Raven. She went over to the octopus people, and I gave her some space. She might be able to pin down when and in what condition Uther came through here, but I wasn’t too hopeful.

“It would make sense that his last time through wasn’t the first,” said Amaryllis, nodding. “And three times through, having set his affairs in order the last time … I can see the attraction.”

“Does it substantially change anything?” asked Bethel. If she’d made a purchase, she’d put it into extradimensional storage.

“No,” I said. “It’s just … a piece of the picture, I think.”

“Do we continue on?” asked Bethel. “Is he before or after this Landing?”

“After, I think,” I said. “Or at least, naively, I would think after.”

“We need to take that exit then,” said Amaryllis, pointing down the wet market to another door. She waited patiently for Raven to finish arguing with the octopus person though, and when Raven came back over, there was only stony silence.

We made our way and moved along, through more doors and more rooms, hoping to find Arthur. I definitely had some questions.

We lost more as we went along, and eventually we had to go on foot, because Bethel couldn’t keep up the sensory fuckery she’d been using to let us see everything as we rode along. Even if we’d been willing to ride blind, there was a chance that her extradimensional powers were going to collapse at some point, and we didn’t want to be inside her when that happened.

“If warding leaves,” said Grak. “It may be time for me to turn back.”

“Turn back?” I asked. “What, by yourself?”

“I’d probably go with him,” said Fenn. “Losing warding is going to make it a fuckload more difficult to find Uther, and as much as I want to help, I don’t plan on dying here.”

“Splitting the party is the wrong move,” said Amaryllis.

“It usually is,” I said.

“Do you really want us to be braving these tunnels with no magic?” asked Fenn. “Because I have to say, the things that Bethel’s been killing for us don’t seem like they’ve been getting all that less hard to kill.”

“They have been,” said Bethel. “But I’m slowing down.” By her estimation, she’d lost ten percent of her entads, and most of them had been good ones. She’d been reduced to using razor sharp telekinesis as her primary form of attack, with only five or six good backups if that didn’t work.

We kept following the map, trying to move toward the next Landing, mostly for a lack of better options. I wasn’t convinced that we would find any clues, and I was worried that we’d lose too much magic. At a certain point, Bethel might not be able to continue. I was also worried that we were going to run into one of the American fireteams that surely had to be moving around the Long Stairs.

Eventually, we came to a problem.

“The ‘map’ says to go this way,” said Amaryllis, staring at the door.

“It’s against RDP,” I said, looking at the Celtic knotwork pattern on the door. “Or it should be. But if we don’t go through, we might be looking at another fifty rooms or so. I wouldn’t think we’d lose more magic doing that, but,” I looked at the door. “Every room is a risk. And there’s a chance we’ll end up back at the wet market Landing, if I read the map right.”

“It’s also unclear what happens if we violate this RDP,” said Amaryllis, looking through her copy of the notes we’d taken. “They give a list of instructions, but don’t say what happens when there’s a violation.” It wasn’t the first time she’d mentioned it. I knew she found it frustrating.

I turned to Fenn. “How are we feeling about this door?” I asked.

She looked at it and flinched. “Good,” she said.

“Then why the flinch?” I asked.

“I should have good luck, right?” asked Fenn. “I should be damned near the luckiest elf that ever lived?”

“I don’t know,” I said. “Maybe. Probably.”

“There’s a texture to it,” said Fenn. “You know when you do D&D, you can do weal, woe, or weal and woe?”

“Sure,” I said. “Fifth edition auguries work like that.”

“Yeah,” said Fenn. “This is definitely an ‘and’ kind of situation. Like, we should go in there, but it’s a bad time coming. Or it’s a bad time with a fabulous reward at the end.”

I nodded, then strode toward the door, with the party trailing after me. Fenn’s analysis wasn’t really the kind of thing that you wanted to hear, but it left me a little hopeful, because at least it was something. The Long Stairs were huge, infinite, for some senses of the word, and it was possible that we’d need to spend enormous amounts of time looking around before we found the one room we were looking for, if Arthur was even in a single room and not moving around himself. We only assumed that he was stationary because otherwise what had he been doing for five hundred years?

My hand touched the door, and it burst open with a flash of blue sparks.

The floor of the room was covered in a green liquid, but I could only tell that it was liquid because I’d kicked a rock forward that disturbed the surface. If not for that, I would have thought that it was a lacquered floor. Above that, there was a broad dome. It was rare to have a circular room, but this one seemed to be.

“Slowly,” I said. I didn’t recognize the room, and it wasn’t in our abbreviated catalog, not that there was more than a line of shorthand for each of the rooms.

We floated on a platform created by Bethel, just above the liquid.

“Marble test,” said Amaryllis. She pulled a marble from Sable and held it out over the liquid, then dropped it in, stepping back. The marble fell, and when it was an inch above the surface, the surface extended a pseudopod in order to snatch it.

“Doesn’t seem so bad,” said Fenn. “I mean, right? We just sail right over and we’re on our way.”

“The doors are down there,” said Grak.

I looked around and realized that he was right. I’d been so focused on threat detection that I’d missed it. Above the waterline, there was just a wall made of masonry, with no way to exit. Even the way we’d come from had silently sealed off.

“So,” I said. “We go down?”

“I should do my scan first,” said Grak, looking down.

“Think you can ward against this goop?” I asked.

He shook his head. “I’ve been checking as we go. Warding has been spotty as far as anomalies are concerned. Velocity wards, but nothing else.” He didn’t say it, but I could tell that he was worried about what he’d be left with when velocity was gone.

“Okay,” I said. That was unfortunate, but not unexpected. Warding had mapped out ‘dark areas’ of potential magic, places on the spectrum that didn’t correspond to any known material or magic, and I’d been hoping that there was a block set aside for the Long Stairs.

“Entad at the bottom,” said Grak, after about ten minutes or so. “Either exactly one, or it’s cloaking others.”

“Can you check?” I asked.

Grak frowned. “To check I would need to ward against the one. If it’s cloaking others, it might be the amulet of nondetection, but it might also be something important.”

“And?” I asked, not quite picking up on what he was saying.

“If Uther is down there, he might be depending on whatever the entad is,” said Amaryllis. “Wardproof armor, or something like that.”

“Ah,” I replied. I looked down at the fluid, which I was increasingly thinking of as goop. “Okay, so … we pull him up.”

“Rope test,” said Amaryllis. She produced a length of rope from Sable and slowly lowered it into the goop. Again, when it was an inch from the surface, a pseudopod formed and reached up to touch the rope. When it did, it latched on and began to climb, moving quickly and getting thicker as it went up. Amaryllis released the rope rather than allow the goop to touch her hand, and frowned down at where the rope had disappeared.

“Do we think he’s actually down there?” asked Raven.

“What defense would he have had against this?” I asked.

“Not going in?” she asked. “He could have just avoided it.” She was looking at the goop with her brow furrowed. “But with still magic gone, with this not being something warding works against, I don’t know. I can’t see a sword being effective. Transport entads wouldn’t work. If he got caught, then there’s a chance he could get pulled down, but … this has to be escapable, doesn’t it?”

“No,” I said. “It really doesn’t. Especially not for a single person.”

“He should have been able to get out,” insisted Raven. “This is a stupid trap to have gotten him.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I’ll give you that. Uther trapped in a goop pit isn’t how anyone would think he’d have gone out.”

“We’ll get him out,” said Amaryllis. She looked at Grak. “What do you think are the odds nullifying the one entad you can sense down there will kill him?”

Grak frowned. “Low,” he said. “It’s likely the amulet of nondetection.” He frowned at her.

“Bethel?” I asked. “Anything?”

“A sphere,” she replied.

“Fuck,” I said. “It’s a bobbler.”

“A what?” asked Raven.

“Bobbler,” I said. “It projects a sphere around you, so for you, no time passes, but for everyone else, that sphere of spacetime stays there, not doing much. It lasts for, uh, some indeterminate amount of time. It’s from a book, not original, but I used it in-game. I’d thought maybe that was how Everett had made it five hundred years, but — if Uther’s been sitting there, bobbled, then maybe for him it’s been no time at all.”

“It would be protecting him?” asked Grak.

“I don’t know,” I said. “Maybe.”

“It would block other signatures,” said Grak, frowning.

I tapped my foot for a moment.

“I might be able to bring it up,” said Bethel. “I still have the hydrophobic coating.”

“Let me test wards first,” said Grak, staring down at the goop with a frown on his face.

To my surprise, he was able to make some headway on the problem using a fairly plain velocity ward. As he explained it, any fluid had some minute movement of the particles within it, and a one-way ward, which was somewhat difficult, would mean that particles would only go in one direction, to the outside of the ward itself. I mentioned Maxwell’s demon, and he said that was entirely correct, so I just shut up and watched as the tube he’d made slowly drained. It took an hour before we were able to see the top of the bobble, and more time than that to fully uncover it. The goop couldn’t stick to the ward, nor to the bobble, and eventually Bethel was able to lift it up to the floating platform we were standing on. It had a perfect mirror surface, reflecting us.

“And this thing will open up on its own?” asked Fenn.

“Should,” I replied. “Unless it’s not what I think it is.” I pressed my hand against it, and felt that it was warm, not by itself, but because it perfectly reflected the heat of my fingers. “But for it to open up might take years, so I don’t think we want to wait for it.” I turned to Grak. “Just the one entad there, right?”

“Hmm,” he replied, glaring at his reflection in the bobble. “If he still has the amulet, we’ll lose track of him once this is popped.”

“He’ll be able to see us,” said Raven. “He’ll understand this is a rescue attempt.”

“Do it,” I said. A part of me wanted to say that we should get into battle positions, but we weren’t planning to fight Uther, and I couldn’t fathom why he’d want to fight us, not without talking to us first. My eyes flitted to Bethel, but she’d had a long time with Valencia, and Valencia had cleared her for the mission.

Grak created the ward first, then flicked it on, and standing in front of us was … nothing, just empty space. I knew that was just the amulet of nondetection, but it was eerie how completely it worked.

“Uther?” I asked, after a moment had passed.

He appeared in front of us, removing the amulet from around his neck. He was as I’d seen him in the mirror he’d left for me at Speculation and Scrutiny, older, but still the same. He had dark, curly hair and a full beard shot through with a touch of grey. He looked like a king, and not just because he had a platinum crown bespeckled with precious gems. He was completely decked out in entads, including lots of rings on his fingers and two swords of different lengths hanging from his belt. The most striking thing was his armor though, which looked like pearls of black caviar coating him, and my guess, based on how impractical it looked, was that it was really good.

He looked at each of us in turn, but his eyes laid on Raven the longest.

“Face Protocol, Lotus Protocol, Puppet Protocol,” he finally said. “And I’ll need introductions.”

“It’s me,” I said. “Juniper.”

He looked at me for a moment, taking in my armor and the sheathed swords at my hip. “So it would seem,” he replied. “What was the name of your pet hamster?”

“Mildew,” I said, though it took me a moment.

“The name of the restaurant we used to go to?” he asked.

“Uh,” I said. “The Great Wall.”

“The other one,” he said.

“Ruttles,” I said. I was watching him, still not really believing it was him. I wracked my brain, trying to think of something I could ask him, something that I hadn’t already told the others, or that they couldn’t have found out from Earth. “It’s been forty years for you,” I said. “Or more, since we don’t know how long you’ve been in this place, and all the other stuff they say in the legends. I don’t want to ask you questions you’ll have forgotten the answers to.”

“Ask anyway,” he replied. “If I don’t know, then I don’t know.” He looked over at Raven and Amaryllis. “I assume you taught him the protocols?”

“They did,” I said. “And — I remembered some of them from our games.”

He regarded me for a moment, then turned to Raven. “You know everything, then,” he said. “I’m sorry I didn’t tell you sooner.”

“It’s okay,” breathed Raven, losing the edge of tension she’d been showing. “I understand.”

Uther turned back to me. “The questions?” he asked. “It will help confirm for you as well as me.”

“Tom,” I said. My tongue felt thick in my mouth. “Do you remember his character’s name, in the Knights of the Square Table campaign?”

“Elhart Cloakshield,” said Uther, after a momentary pause. He was watching me more carefully now. I hadn’t picked that campaign by accident. It was the one where the character of Uther Penndraig had originated.

“What movie did we go see, opening night, right before,” I paused, because I didn’t know if he knew he was dead on Earth. “Early in May, 2016.”

“May 6th,” he said. “Captain America: Civil War. It was when you came up with Mome Rath.” He was watching me, judging to see whether I would react to that name.

I nodded. “Good enough for me, I guess.”

Arthur — Uther — turned to Raven and Amaryllis. “Confirmation should be easier here,” he said, nodding at them. “Raven, you journeyed to the Outer Reaches with me, so all that’s needed from you is some confirmation that the information isn’t simply leaving your mind as soon as it enters.”

“I’ve been there too,” said Amaryllis.

“How much time has passed, my daughter?” Uther asked her. He looked Raven over, perhaps trying to make some judgement. The visible aging would have been a major clue, since she didn’t look twelve.

“I’m not your daughter,” replied Amaryllis. “Not Dahlia. I only look like her. I'm your granddaughter, ten generations removed. It’s been five hundred years since you left, almost exactly to the day.”

I frowned at that. I hadn’t done the math. We’d always said ‘five hundred years’, but it had really been a bit less than that. ‘Almost exactly to the day’ sounded fishy, or magical, in a way that I didn’t like. I wondered whether Amaryllis had planned it that way.

“Not Dahlia,” said Uther, staring at Amaryllis.

“No,” said Amaryllis, squaring herself up. “But it’s a pleasure to finally meet you.”

Uther gave her a nod. “And the rest of the introductions to your motley crew?”

“Fenn Greenglass,” said Fenn, stepping forward. “Reformed thief and archer extraordinaire.” She did a little curtsy, then pointed a thumb at me. “Juniper’s ex.”

“Grakhuil Leadbraids,” said Grak. “Warder.”

“Is that your ward?” asked Uther, looking down at the hole in the green ooze. “It’s quality work.”

Grak nodded. It was hard to read his expression.

I looked at Bethel, where her form was standing. I was waiting for her to speak, and not particularly looking forward to it. From everything they said about Uther, he could defend himself, but I’d seen the kind of damage that Bethel was capable of delivering. She had been waiting for her turn, and that made me worried. I had no idea what mix of emotions was going on in her head.

“I go by Bethel now,” said Bethel. “Once upon a time, I was a house called Kuum Doona.”

Uther regarded her for a moment, then stepped forward to get a closer look at her. At any moment there might be an explosion of violence, or failing that, accusations against him, ones that I didn’t think he had any way out of, except to say that she wasn’t a person. And then what was there? Learning to get along? If that was possible, these weren’t the right conditions for it.

“The entad,” said Uther, straightening up. He looked down at the platform we were standing on, then at Bethel. “Still bound to me, I see.”

I looked at Bethel. She said nothing for a moment, then opened her mouth to say something.

“Don’t speak,” said Uther.

Bethel shut her mouth.

“In fact, I think I’ll take direct control,” he said. He held out his hand toward her, and her form disappeared entirely. I looked at his finger, and another ring was there.

“You can’t do that,” I said.

“How did you do that?” asked Amaryllis.

“Connection,” replied Uther. “It was Vervain’s greatest gift, and indeed, one of the most powerful on Aerb.”

“No,” I said. “His greatest gift was that he was the Dungeon Master.”

Uther looked at me. “You’ve gotten that far along, have you, Juniper?”

I nodded at him. My eyes kept going to the ring on his finger, where Bethel’s physical form was.

“Have you spoken with him?” asked Uther.

“I have,” I said. “Three times now.”

“I only had one conversation,” he replied. “With Vervain.”

“Before you killed him,” I said.

Uther sighed. “Old history.” He looked down at the goop. “We should be on our way. We have a lot of ground to cover.” Without another word, he jumped down off the tunnel that Grak had made in the goop, landing softly on the ground. He began on his own ward down there, and I saw that he was consulting the ward Grak had made from time to time.

“Did he just … steal Bethel?” asked Fenn.

“Seems like it,” said Amaryllis. She looked at me. “This is a problem.”

I could feel from the way the air was moving that she was muting herself. The very platform we were standing on had been created by Bethel, and was being maintained by her, even if Uther had taken control. It was a serious problem though, given that he’d taken the largest chunk of our offensive might.

“But how?” asked Fenn.

“It’s his entad,” said Raven. Her eyes had not left Uther. “He is bound to it, has been bound to it all this time.”

“She’s a thinking being,” I said. “He can’t just — I mean —”

“Done,” said Uther, from down the well of green goop. He had extended his own ward sideways until it touched the wall, and was using various magic of his own to hasten the inevitable movement of the goop to the sides. “I suppose warding has advanced in the years I’ve been gone.” He opened the door and stepped through, then called back to us, “If you’re coming, now is the time to come,” then strode off without another word.

“Fuck,” I said. I leapt down and followed after him, and I could hear the others doing the same.

The room we found ourselves in was one of the largest ones I’d seen, and Uther was striding along the flagstones with purpose, as though he hadn’t just been freed, as though he hadn’t just met us, as though he hadn’t gotten the news that it had been five hundred years. The room itself had skeletons hanging from the vaulted ceilings. I was worried that they were going to come to life or drop down on us, because that seemed like the typical thing to have happened. By the time I caught up with Uther, they had started singing, a low and ghostly chorus.

“Wait,” I said. “Can you hold on a minute? It took me a long time to find you, and more effort than you’re probably aware of, —”

“A quest of some kind?” asked Uther. He shook his head. “There’s always a quest. But no, I’m not having it. I’m done with Aerb, no matter who or what tries to pull me back in. There was a time I’d thought I might find you on Aerb. It’s all your design, after all.”

“Stop!” I shouted. Uther stopped where he was and turned back to me. I’d instinctively let my hand go to my sword, but I moved it away when he looked at me. “Do you even have any idea where you’re going?”

He regarded me for a moment. “Back to Earth.”

“Aerb needs you,” I said. “There are a crazy number of exclusions, the Void Beast is coming, there’s unification in the hells —”

“Juniper,” said Uther. “Joon. Is that really you in there, in that body that’s no longer your own?” He was looking at my height, my obvious muscles, and perhaps thinking about how plain and average I’d been.

The others were catching up to us. “Yeah,” I said. “It’s me. We need to —”

“Joon, none of it is real, don’t you get that?” he asked. There was pleading in his eyes.

“Of course it’s real,” I replied.

He leaned forward. “Every inch of Aerb is something you made up, every species, every landmark, every magic, it was all from your head.” He had a finger positioned right at my forehead. “If you’re really Juniper, then you have to recognize that, don’t you? It’s a game, it’s not real, and I’m done with it now, so yes, I’m going home.”

“Aerb is your home,” said Raven as she caught up. “You haven’t been on Earth since you were sixteen.”

“And is Aerb still that same home?” asked Uther. “Are there others, besides yourself, who yet live?”

Raven stared at him. “No,” she said softly. “I’m the last I know of.”

“You have family,” said Amaryllis. “Anglecynn still stands. The empire you built, the First Empire, has a successor. You are revered as a true hero, the founder of the modern era, the greatest poet and sage of all time, an incomparable legend —”

“And I’m done with it,” said Uther. “I have declared myself finished with Aerb, and no words will shake the firmness of my conviction.” He gestured at us. “Show me new plot threads, new characters, it does not matter, I am done.”

“And what then?” I asked. “You come out on Earth in the middle of a military installation that’s part of a vast coverup, as the greatest swordsman in the world? What’s the fucking plan here?”

“I’ll figure it out when I get there,” he replied. He looked around at us, waiting for a challenge, then set off to the nearest door.

“What are we doing about this?” I asked.

“Following him,” said Raven. She set off after him, down the large room, hurrying to keep up.

“Seems kind of bad that he stole Bethel,” said Fenn. She was eyeing Uther’s back. “Like, real bad. We’ve got a ‘don’t kidnap party members’ rule, don’t we? I thought I remembered a clause like that. Want me to shoot him?”

I almost said that there was no chance that would do anything, but I stayed quiet, because I’d seen how much power she could put into an arrow. In theory, he would be able to perfectly parry it, but I wasn’t entirely confident in that.

“No,” I said. “No, we came here to talk.”

“We came here so you could go with him,” said Amaryllis. Her face was set. “We were never going to bring him back. It was always going to be the two of you together, returning to Earth.”

“I’m not going back to Earth,” I said. “It’s not even Earth, for fuck’s sake.”

“Then we’ll figure something else out,” said Amaryllis. “Come on, we need to go.”

I looked at Grak, but he only nodded.

“That can’t be the plan, can it?” asked Fenn, but even as she asked, she was moving to follow. “We’re going to Earth? I’m pretty sure when I put my signature on the LSP, there was nothing in there about going to a place where we’re going to get vivisected.”

“Because I don’t know what was in the FSP, I can’t be sure, but it does seem like the LSP was underdeveloped by comparison,” said Amaryllis. “There were just too many unknowns.”

“No one blames you,” I said.

“I should sure as fuck hope not,” said Amaryllis. “Because I didn’t see anyone else going to the trouble.”

“Can we take him in a fight?” asked Fenn. I stopped her words dead before they could reach Uther. “Seems like we can’t, right?”

“Arthur, wait!” I called again.

He turned back to me, but didn’t stop moving. “Do you understand your role in all this?” he asked.

“I — no,” I said. “I mean, I don’t think I have a role, unless it’s just to talk to you, to — to reconcile. On Earth you were dead. You’d been dead nine months before I came here.”

“Your role is to stop me,” said Uther, ignoring what I’d said. “You are a temptation to return to Aerb, a temptation to give in to the demands of the narrative. You all are, in your ways. It’s the eleventh hour, and you represent another call I must refuse.”

“No,” I said. He was about to reach the door. “Hey, I had my own adventures, my own companions, maybe you were the chosen one, but I’m the chosen one too. Look at me, do I look like I did when we were in high school?”

He finally did stop, then looked at me. “No,” he said. “You don’t.” He stayed there, looking at me. “How long have you been on Aerb?”

“Months,” I said. “I’ve spent a lot of it in a time chamber.”

His eyes were watching mine. “Has the narrative found you?” he asked.

“It was there right from the start,” I said. This, I knew, he would care about. “I had — an overlay. Messages relayed to me on a HUD, like a videogame.”

He nodded. “Well, it’s immaterial.” He kept walking and touched the door handle.

“We have a map,” I said. I wasn’t sure if that was the right thing to say, because if he followed the map we’d have less time until he got to his destination, but I didn’t want to walk through door after door like this, not when there was a chance we’d run into something horrible. Above us, the skeletons had continued their ghostly singing.

“Let’s have it then,” he said, holding out a hand. “I’ve taken a few, but they were compromised.”

I reluctantly handed over the book. It felt like he was perfectly prepared to leave me behind if I didn’t keep up. All I wanted to do was sit and talk, and all he wanted to do was move. Once he had the book, he started reading intently, flipping through the pages almost so fast it was a blur.

“You need to stop,” I said. “You need to talk.”

“No,” he said, not looking up at me. “What I need is a return to normalcy, and the only place I’m liable to find that is Earth.”

“Aerb needs you,” said Raven, but we both knew that argument wasn’t going to sway him. She hadn’t left his side, and the way she was standing close to him was like a child trying to get the attention of their parents. “Why did you do this, why did you abandon us?”

He looked down at her. “Aerb lasted five hundred years without me,” he said. “And I suppose that there were epic battles in that time, calamities avoided only by the skin of your collective teeth, great sacrifices, exclusions, all of it. And the world still stood. Even if I cared about it — but gods, I don’t care about it.”

“How can you say that?” asked Raven. “How can you say that the place you’ve spent your entire adult life meant nothing to you? The place where you met your wife, where you had children, where you made an empire, where you’re the Poet King?”

“None of it is real,” said Uther. “None of it.”

“Solipsism,” I said. “It’s not a tenable philosophy.”

“I’m not claiming that nothing is real,” replied Uther. “I’m only claiming that Aerb isn’t real, or if it’s real, that it’s so managed and planned that it might as well not exist. I have seen evidence of the unreality of Aerb, and spoken to its self-professed god. I was a part of the very creative wellspring of everything which exists on Aerb. If it is real, it is meaningless. Therefore, I am going home.”

“No,” I said. “No, you’re not going home, don’t you get that if it’s possible to get there from Aerb, it can’t be Earth? Earth didn’t have massive dimensional tunnels!”

“And you have a better solution?” asked Uther, moving closer to me, as though I was meant to answer the challenge of his words with physical might. “You have some way of waking up from the nightmare? A way to exit the simulation?”

“I clearly didn’t get the same experience as you,” I said. “Look, can we sit down for a bit and just talk, I’m not going to try to convince you to come back with me, but before you go on this insane trip back to what’s clearly not the Earth we came from, maybe I can lay some facts on you, and then you can fuck off to wherever it is you think you’re going to go. Okay? One hour, tops.”

He stood there, as if he was going to tell me that he couldn’t even stomach that, but finally, he nodded and sat down on the stone. “Very well. Tell your tales.”

Old Sins Cast Long Shadows

I thankfully still had multithreading. As I spoke to Uther, half of my mind was focused on the ring on his finger.

I didn’t know what, if anything, to do about Bethel. The entire reason we’d brought her was because of her immense power, and if it had been possible for us to bring that power along and leave Bethel behind, we’d have done that in a heartbeat. In fact, I had tried to figure out some way of doing that and came up short. I could empathize with Bethel, but I didn’t like her or want to be around her. It felt too possible that she would find some reason to hurt me, that her reform would be revealed as a facade, or that she would just ‘slip’, like an addict who has to start over from day one.

With all that said, being reduced to a tool, being silenced like that, wasn’t what she deserved, especially from the same person responsible for so much pain and suffering in her early life. What she deserved was to be healthy and happy, the same as anyone else, even the worst of them. If Uther was going to do that to her, lock the person away, or make her go dormant, or whatever he’d actually done, I had some moral duty to stop him. I had a sick feeling in the pit of my stomach, the kind I got from seeing something bad happen and allowing it to be someone else’s problem.

The more I thought about it, the more I was upset by it, shock and confusion giving way to anger and frustration, even as I kept explaining what had happened to me to Uther.

I had to skip a lot of stuff, especially because I wasn’t just giving an overview of what I’d been up to on Aerb, but also what had happened on Earth, and beyond that, the last five hundred years of Aerb’s history. All that, in about an hour, was a big ask, even eliding important details. Above where we sat, there were still the floating skeletons, and they hadn’t stopped singing, though they changed their tune every once in a while.

“So then I get an error message,” I said. “I can give you the exact line, but I never had any other context, and it was a different presentation from all the other messages that I’d gotten. It happened again months later, when I was exposed to a meme that should have been lethal.”

“I have never had such a thing,” said Uther. “Never in all my time on Aerb. There was never one whiff of anything like that.” He sat back slightly. Amaryllis had pulled out chairs partway through, to keep us from having to stand. “It’s not real.”

“The … error message?” I asked. “I mean, I did think about that, but why?” Again, I looked down at the ring on his finger. I was going to have to bring it up, to take Bethel back and make him undo what he’d done, but there was no way I could do it by force.

“I haven’t the faintest idea,” he replied. “Though of course I have many guesses.” He looked at me and leaned forward, resting his hands on his knees. “Proceed. You have twenty-six minutes left.”

“Oh come on,” said Fenn, rolling her eyes.

“Do you have a problem?” he asked.

“Twenty-six minutes,” she said. “Like you’re in charge of jack shit. Like you’re magically timing this down to the second. Come off it man, it’s just,” she made a jerking off motion.

I’d kind of expected him to laugh, but he only stared her down.

“He’s still king of all Anglecynn,” said Raven. “Show some respect.”

Fenn gave her a skeptical look. “If he wanted my respect, maybe he shouldn’t have stolen Bethel. And maybe he shouldn’t have gotten stuck in a bunch of slime.”

“He wasn’t stuck, it was on purpose,” Raven said softly. She looked to Arthur, and he gave her a gentle nod.

“Wait,” I said. “What? Why?”

Uther stayed silent, which left Raven to explain. “He was deliberately severing himself from the world,” she said. “He wasn’t down there because he couldn’t escape, he was down there because he was waiting for everyone to die.”

“You’re not the first to find me,” said Uther. “You’re not the first to try bringing me back.”

“Who else?” asked Raven. “You wore the amulet of non-detection, it should have been impossible for them to follow you. I wasn’t able to get any sense of where you were until years later, when passage to the Long Stairs had been rendered impossible.”

“Is this counting against our time?” asked Fenn. “I mean, are we still pretending that it makes any sense whatsoever to have this conversation be timed?”

I gave her a frown, and that was all the attention anyone paid to her. She didn’t like Uther, for a variety of reasons, and she was letting it show a bit too much. I had my own uncomfortable feelings, for different reasons, but I didn’t think we’d get anywhere by antagonizing him or calling him a dick, even if he was being a dick. That wasn’t including taking Bethel, which went a bit beyond being a dick.

“It was my sons, one after another,” said Uther. “Zona had known where I was going.”

“You tried to take her with you,” I said. “This wasn’t your first time in the Long Stairs.” The pile of octopuses had said as much.

“No,” he replied. His eyes went to me. “I found this place shortly after I first became king. It was just a door, standing in the middle of a field, completely unassuming. There was a small village near it, and it had become the stuff of local legends, alternately a holy site or something haunted. There was no utility in it, of course, so it was simply a curiosity, a door to nowhere, connected to nothing, and utterly indestructible.” He let out a slow breath, and I caught myself becoming enraptured by both the storytelling and the flow of fresh information. “The oddest thing about it, from my perspective now, was that there was no particular quest attached to it. No one was fighting over the door, there was nothing coming from it, there was no urgency or promise attached to it, it was just … there. It was a mystery, to be sure, but there was nothing that compelled exploration of it, aside from the fact of its existence.”

He sighed. “There were three parts to the lock. I was an accomplished enough warder to manipulate a piece of it, and I brought Forty-Two with me to handle the mechanical aspects, which I hadn’t then had cause to learn, but it was the final password that eluded me. I had begun to see bits and pieces of campaigns by that time, most obviously in the form of characters, but occasionally little details I remembered of Juniper’s worldbuilding. I wondered whether that last component of the door might be something from them. But no, while it was something that acted as a gate that would open only for me, the secret was one that I believe anyone who’d come of age with abundant computers might have guessed.” He looked at us. “It was also the first hint that there might be something terrestrial behind those doors.”

“To be clear,” said Amaryllis. “The password was, for you, ‘Password1’?”

He nodded. “The relief on the face of the door was, of course, another clue, but I didn’t make the connection that it was the Long Stairs until I was already in it. I hadn’t been properly prepared, and I ended up running at full tilt for quite some time, leaving a trail of monsters behind me. I was violating protocols left and right, not that I could remember them, or trust my memories. Eventually I found myself in a large room where I could hole up and make a defense, and there ensued a vigorous battle of the kind that I was known for. I survived, lucky, in the way that I often am. I was lost, utterly lost, in one of the most dangerous places I had ever been.”

I was keeping an eye on Fenn from time to time, and she kept giving me knowing looks which read, at least to my eyes, as ‘boy does this guy like to talk’. When she caught me looking, she made a yapping motion with her fingers, subtle enough that I was the only one who saw it.

She had a bit of a point though. He’d been the one trying to drag us along, to get where he was going, and now he was sitting there telling us a story. I’d given him the short version of things, a bucket of bullet points that he might want to know, and he was giving me a narrative. I wondered if that was just how he was now, but really, it wasn’t all that much different from how he’d been when I’d known him in high school.

“I tried to be more methodical after that battle,” said Uther. “I checked rooms carefully, backing away if they seemed like they contained something I’d have trouble handling. You’re not supposed to do that, I’m sure Juniper has told you, but I was hoping that I would escape a penalty. Thankfully, I made it to the first Landing, but unfortunately, I ran afoul of one of the creatures there and lost a considerable portion of my faculties, including the ability to speak. I was eventually able to get the parasite off, but I was addled, and I knew that if I tried to recuperate in the Landing, I would have more than just one of them to contend with. I soldiered on, not quite recovered, and only three rooms later, I came across the Americans.”

“It was a revelation,” said Uther. “I had known that I was in the Long Stairs, but the idea that it would connect to Earth hadn’t even crossed my mind. Why would it? I’d seen nothing of Earth aside from the campaigns, not for a decade. But there they were, with flags on their shoulders, speaking a language that I could place, but which was, unfortunately, unintelligible to me. There were only three of them, and one was in a bad way. Looking back, I think it was a medic, a wizard, and their artillery. From what I now know of their tactics, they should have been attempting a return home, and perhaps they were, but unfortunately, we ran across each other. It took them three minutes to open fire on me. I hadn’t known how my blade would fare against burst fire from a rifle in close quarters, but the ease with which I deflected the bullets was shocking. The wizard though …” he looked at me. “Juniper had always described them as terrifying creatures of incredible power, the last resort of raw power for the team, treated with the same awe and respect that you might treat a weapon of mass destruction.”

“I did tell them about nukes,” I said. “Plus, uh, Aerb has nukes. Or, had. They got excluded while you were here.”

He nodded, not seeming to care that nuclear weapons had come and gone. “The comparison you always made was to aircraft carriers.”

“Which you always thought was nonsense,” I said.

“You said they could make eight delves before being irrevocably compromised and unable to continue,” replied Uther. “The bulk of them were pulled from PhD programs. In no way would they be able to match the logistical and economic importance of an aircraft carrier.” He’d made the same point back on Earth, and it was a bit shocking to have it regurgitated here, almost perfectly. It had been about forty years for him. “But I knew something of their capabilities and limitations, and I knew that if I allowed that wizard to cast anything, I would regret it immensely. As soon as the barest syllable began to leave his lips, I lunged forward and sliced through him, my blade passing through his kevlar vest as easily as if it were a single layer of silk. I killed each of them in turn, in fact, though the medic succumbed to prior injuries without the others to support her.”

He was silent for a moment. “I searched their bodies and found nothing. Perhaps their lack of a mapping was what had caused them to get as lost as I was.” He let out a sigh, then looked up at me. “I had grown accustomed to killing by that point in my career, but I have to say, those deaths affected me. Those people were the first link I’d seen to my home, my true home, and I had been forced to kill them. For years afterward I felt like they would have had some kind of answers for me, but instead, I was left with only questions. I took what I could from them, anything with writing on it, but it was meaningless to me until much later on. Once I’d fought through the damage that the octopus had done to me, I was only able to confirm the date in the outside world.”

“Which was?” I asked.

“Hard to say,” he replied. “The medic’s bag had the most printed material, mostly in the form of expiration dates, but my best guess from what I could find was approximately mid-June of 2016.” He looked at the others. “How completely did you read them in?”

“Completely,” I said. “We got an entad, via the Dungeon Master, which allows certain things to be pulled from Earth. Amaryllis and Fenn might possibly have watched more movies and television from Earth than I did.”

“And do you still have it now? The entad?” asked Uther. His eyes had gone wide.

“No,” I replied. “Because it was a part of the entad that you’re currently wearing as a ring.” I swallowed. “Which we’re going to take back now.” I tried not to sound accusatory. I tried to think about what I would want that request to sound like, if I were him, and settled on calm and understanding, as though it were a mistake, an accidental violation of protocol. I was pretty sure I just sounded as nervous and uncomfortable as I felt.

Uther looked down at the ring on his finger, where it was one of many. He closed his eyes for a moment, then turned his hand palm up. Without a word from him, a small candy appeared in his hand, a peach ring, and he smelled it for a moment, then ate it.

“Hmm,” he said. “I tried to have the chefs at Caledwich Castle make those. They never could get it quite right though, perhaps because they lacked the industrialized sugars and artificial flavors. None of the ethyls, the lactones, the aldehydes.” He looked at me. “You’ve been having different adventures than the ones I had. You’ve been here less than a year, and already there’s a relief from the clawing homesickness.” He held out his hand again and pulled a can of Mountain Dew from thin air, then set it down and pulled a Snickers, and kept going for a bit, testing what it could do. Bethel must have been aware of all this. Above us, the skeletons were still continuing their ghostly singing.

“Stop,” I said. “Bethel is an ally. A companion.” It was hard for me to say that. Bethel was not a friend, and a part of me thought she deserved whatever had happened to her. Only a part though, and feelings of revenge and retribution were ones I held off on the most.

Uther paused, then tried one more time, curling his fingers slightly. “No electronics? That’s a shame.”

“Did you hear me?” I asked. “Give Bethel back, now, and release whatever weird hold you have over her.” Again I tried to put firmness in my voice, but I knew who I was talking to. He had been the closest thing Aerb had ever had to a full blown emperor. When it came to combat, I thought a fight between us would last a single round, and definitely not in my favor.

“Hold?” asked Uther, raising an eyebrow. “I bonded with her, not long after she was created. She’s my entad.” He looked at Amaryllis. “As is that glove, for that matter, and the sword at your hip.”

“Arthur,” I said. “I don’t want to have some fucking conversation about whether or not something that quacks like a duck should have all the rights and privileges of a duck. Release Bethel to me, now. Let me talk to her.” I was feeling heated. In a fight, I was certain I would lose, even if he didn’t use Bethel to cleave me in half. I knew that, but I had to press anyway.

He slipped the ring from his finger and looked at it. “I remember those conversations,” he said. “About whether a sentient sword deserves to live a life of its own, or a golem created by a wizard deserves a right to vote. Did you know some of your slave species made it to Aerb?”

“I know,” I said. My eyes were on the ring. I’d been serious about not wanting to have the conversation, but I felt like we were going to have it anyway.

“I suppose, if you think of it as your companion, it might have spoken of me,” said Uther. The pronoun use there definitely felt deliberate. “I was at a difficult point in my life when I went to Kuum Doona the second time, to claim it. This was long after my first trip into the Long Stairs, which I’d made a difficult and miraculous escape from, against the odds, as those things are usually done.” He gave us all a grin, and I nearly smiled back, just on instinct. “I was looking for a way out, in those days. Not a way out of Aerb, but a way that I might escape the narrative forces that had such a stranglehold on my life. I had thought that the Boundless Pit might be the answer, not because there was any direct evidence pointing toward it, but because it represented, in my eyes, the underworld through which I might need to pass before the cycles of narrative would finally be done with me. Do you know what I found down there?”

“No,” I said. He was talking a lot, and I was worried that if I let him keep talking, he would brush off the whole issue of having forcibly taken Bethel and stripped her of all agency and power. I did want to know what was down there though, and if it explained things at all, I needed to hear it. Still, I didn’t want to get trapped in his orbit, as I felt I had been since he came out of the bobble.

“I found infinity,” said Uther. “I found a world without end. It widened as I went down, so I followed the slope, angling my fall, looking at the walls as I went down mile after mile. They’d called it the Boundless Pit, or some translation thereof, but I hadn’t thought that was literal. I had supposed that it was a hundred miles, or a thousand, or ten thousand, and at the bottom, I would find some kind of answer. No. There were only endless changes in the biomes that stuck to the walls, endless different civilizations, different species, on and on. Sometimes there were patches of light, artificial suns or bioluminescent birds, and in other places people lived in the dark. I had come looking for an end to the adventures. I had been meditating on what would eventually become a book, Degenerate Cycles, and there was something unutterably profound in falling so far and seeing no end in sight. I did stop, every so often, to see what there was to see, to gaze upon whatever new sights were there. It just … kept going.” He took a breath. “I cried as I fell, for I could see that there would always be more worlds to conquer.”

I stared at him. Something about how he’d phrased it tickled a memory. “‘And when Alexander saw the breadth of his domain, he wept, for there were no more worlds to conquer.’”

“Benefits of a classical education,” Uther nodded. There was no trace of humor in his voice. He was looking at the ring he was holding in his fingers, the mute form he’d contorted Bethel into. I wondered if he realized how much he looked like a villain. He’d caught us in his monologue. “I gave up. I fought a few enormous monsters down there, more to take out my anger and frustration than because there was any point to it. The anger gave way, eventually. I had never been particularly good at sustaining anger. I returned to Kuum Doona and slept for a week. And when I awoke, there, standing in front of me like a vision from god, was my high school crush, Tiffany Archer.”

I looked at Fenn, thinking that she was going to call him on his shit, but she was just sitting there looking uncomfortable. It occurred to me that I didn’t just think she would call him on his shit, I thought that she should, or that someone should, and if it wasn’t going to be anyone else, it had to be me. “And once you figured out that it was the entad you’d bonded to, you decided to groom and then rape her,” I said.

Uther closed his fist around the ring, where he’d been focusing his attention, and turned his eyes to me. He didn’t seem hurt or perturbed by what I’d said. There was a steely calm to him that made me feel like he was using some kind of social still magic on me. I was pretty sure that was just him though. “Do you remember the abortion debates?” he asked.

“A matter of axioms,” I replied. “That was always what you said. But you’re forgetting that I know you, and I can see exactly where you’re going with this, and you’re also forgetting that about five minutes ago I said I didn’t want any kind of fucking debate about personhood with you. So hand over the fucking ring.” It was hard, trying to force my anger through. There was something about his calmness that was making me feel like I was unjustified.

He stared at me for a moment. “This is emotional for you. I’m sorry. I didn’t realize.” He tossed the ring, and I snatched it out of the air.

I held Bethel in the palm of my hand for a moment, but she didn’t move. “What did you do?” I asked, looking up at him.

“Nothing,” he said. He raised an eyebrow. “If the entad is remaining inert, that’s by choice.”

I stared at the ring for a moment, then slipped it onto my finger. If he was telling the truth, and I had no idea whether he was, then Bethel was remaining in the form of a ring for a reason. I tried to think of it from her perspective, but I had no idea what it was like to have to follow someone’s command whether you wanted to or not. I imagined it as horrifying, like being puppeted, but it was possible that it was something else. The more I thought about it, the more I wished that I’d pushed harder, sooner, that I hadn’t sat there so long talking to him, hoping that the situation would resolve itself.

“I won’t give an argument, if you don’t want it,” said Uther. “But Kuum Doona, as it was then, was no person. From what I can tell, more entads have been added, some of them with intelligence of their own, but — Juniper, you know the arguments as well as I do, the levels of intelligence that an entity can contain — you said you didn’t want an argument, but surely I have a right to defend myself against whatever it is you think I’ve done.”

“You were ashamed,” I said. “You instructed her to take on a different form, to tell no one, then abandoned her completely, in spite of her obvious material value to you.” I wanted to say that he’d threatened her, that he’d stuffed entads inside her against her will, but if he didn’t believe she had a will, I didn’t think he’d find it important.

“Of course I was ashamed,” replied Uther. “I am ashamed. Do you think I want to be airing this now? Talking about it in front of Raven?” He gestured to her, and she withered. I glanced at the faces of the others, and to a one, they all looked unhappy, though in different ways. “I was embarrassed, yes, ashamed, yes, and as soon as it was done, I wanted to put that particular bit of my life behind me. It was an unseemly attempt to fill a void in my psyche, to indulge in nostalgia.”

“Nostalgia?” I asked. He was framing it in his own way, I could see that, and it was so hard to fight framing. “It was Tiff, she wasn’t — you had no right to her body.”

Uther stared at me. “I know that, Juniper,” he said. “You don’t want an argument, which means that we can’t litigate this. You want to air your emotional responses. You can finish tossing whatever accusations you’d like at me, but it will have to be while I do my best to return to Earth. Story time has gone on long enough. Do you remember, earlier, when I asked you if you knew your role?”

“It’s just us,” I said. “There is no role.” But if there was, he would be playing the villain. He seemed blind to it. I wondered whether there was any possible frame in which he would have seemed like a hero.

“It’s transparently obvious once you see it,” said Uther. “You’re here to rope me back into a life of adventuring on Aerb. Just look at you.” He pointed at me. “Juniper, my old friend from high school, and the architect of everything on Aerb, himself a capable adventurer and probable equal, begging me to come back.” He pointed at Grak. “A warder here to show me advancements in the state of the art and reveal a new, higher tier of magic.” He moved on to Amaryllis. “A strong and capable descendant who, by some unknown and intriguing magic, looks exactly like my beloved daughter, ready and willing to take on the role of Dahlia but without any of the baggage.” He stood before Raven. “A last companion, a connection to the old life, a font of knowledge, now an adult.” He finally faltered when he got to Fenn.

“Lovable scamp?” she asked. “Comic relief?” She hesitated. “Love interest?” I was hoping that she’d hesitated because she wasn’t sure whether she should make the joke, but it was extremely hard for me to tell.

“You, I’m still figuring out,” said Uther. He looked away from her, as if her existence was unimportant. “At any rate, it’s all so lazy, so hackneyed. And the time skip! Do you know why hack writers do time skips?”

“No?” I asked.

“It’s because time skips offer something interesting and new when the plot can’t organically accommodate it,” he said. “It’s a cheap way of getting a feeling of newness from a setting that’s been milked half to death.”

He stalked off again, apparently having needed to get all that off his chest.

“But it is compelling,” I said, following after him as he went through the door. “Every single thing you listed off, everything you saw, it did affect you, it did grab at you. You’re just being bull-headed about it.”

Maybe he would have said something back, but the room he’d walked into was filled with slate grey rock creatures that were slowly rising from the ground.

In the descriptions of how Uther fought, he was often compared to water, with an economy of motion that made it seem like he was following the path of least resistance between his enemies. They’d said it was like he’d choreographed every fight ahead of time. It was like watching high art, a performance of violence beyond compare. Here though, in the Long Stairs, he was taking a different approach, or maybe just dispensing with pomp and circumstance. If I had to compare him to anything, it would have been to a pinball, moving between targets with a flash, his motions visible mostly by the wake of bodies he’d cleaved through.

There was a reason for the legends.

<Are you okay?> I sent to Bethel.

It took her some time to reply. <No,> she finally answered.

<It’s okay if you want to withdraw,> I sent. <If you need someone to talk to, I can pass you to one of the others. Or you can talk to me.> Her talking to me was an afterthought. I had always felt more empathy for her than the others, at least in my estimation, but maybe that was because I was a dumbass who hadn’t seen all the warning signs. Even after things had gone south, I had spent a lot of time trying to see things from her perspective, maybe to my own detriment. Now, with three years gone by, I probably knew her least of anyone aside from Fenn, but I still wanted to figure her out.

<I thought that the connection was finished,> said Bethel. <I thought I’d surpassed the bond, mastered it. I was a fool to think a man who could sever his connections to hundreds of entads couldn’t rekindle one. Now I’ve lost my chance to kill him.>

<Would you have?> I asked.

<No,> she replied. <Maybe, if I had known he would have such absolute control of me. But me hurting any of you now is an impossibility, beyond the realm of choices.>

<He did something to your mind?> I asked.

<No,> said Bethel. <But the bond has rekindled. Attack is impossible.>

<We could get him to undo the bond,> I said.

<It wouldn’t matter,> said Bethel. <Unless you need me to kill him, but he would see it coming a mile away.>

<I don’t think we’re planning on that,> I sent. <Let me know what you need.>

She was silent in response. I hoped she understood that I meant it, even with things as they’d been between us.

I followed Uther as he passed through the rooms, and I tried to think.

I thought I would probably lose any debate I started with him. He’d been better at talking his way around things when we were in high school, and now he had forty years on me plus a whole hell of a lot of experience. Maybe it was like debating abortion, where a lot of it came down to immovable axioms. Or maybe we’d uncover some murky gray areas that we could never fully explore without knowing what had been going on with Bethel internally. I was willing to give some credence to the idea that she wasn’t fully formed at that point in her life, and unlike a child, who had a fullness of life ahead of it, that wasn’t the same with Bethel. The whole thing gave me the heebie jeebies either way, but Uther clearly thought what he’d done was defensible, even if it was shameful.

If I was looking at it from his perspective, maybe it was simply embarrassing, like someone looking at your internet search history or a list of all the videos you’d watched. Not that you’d done something wrong, necessarily, but also not the kind of thing you’d want to make public for everyone to see. If he really didn’t see Bethel as a person, or at least that iteration of Bethel, who was possibly less sentient than a pig … well, granted, you weren’t supposed to fuck pigs.

It would all have been easier to swallow if he’d said he was sorry, or offered some apology, but he was plowing on ahead through the Long Stairs, going through door after door, not wanting to talk about any of it.

“I think it’s not all about you,” I said, as we entered a room carpeted with mosses and ferns. “I think it’s about me.”

“Oh, I would agree with that,” replied Uther. “It was obvious enough.”

“It was?” I asked.

“Everything has the stink of Juniper on it,” said Uthur. “It’s about me, but it’s also about you, all this fakeness. There was a time I thought that you were the one pulling the strings behind it all, somehow, a dungeon master gone mad.”

“I think it is,” I said. “Not me personally, but someone with a vested interest in both of us. Someone with my perspective.”

“You were always the one most interested in your worlds,” Uther replied.

“I slept with Maddie,” I said.

He stopped where he was, feet sunk into the moss, and turned to me, narrowing his eyes. “What? When? Why?”

“You died in a car crash,” I said. It was the first time telling him that, but it got no reaction. Maybe he had some memory of it. “I didn’t handle it well. Looking back, I’m sure a lot of it was depression, but there was also some self-hatred and destructive tendencies, and — she was always so eager for friendship, and she liked me for whatever reason. We dated for like … a week.”

He was still staring at me, judging me, but finally, his face relaxed. “Ah,” he said. “I see why you mention it.” He turned and kept walking, barely slowing when a section of the moss lurched up from the ground and attacked him. He augmented his blade with magic when a dozen slashes did little, and with a blast, it was blown apart along the cuts he’d made. “You’re drawing parallels. You think, in fact, that these parallels are intended, designed.”

“I don’t really care,” I said. “Designed or not, intended or not, there are parallels. You were desperate, in despair, wanting a comfort that I’m pretty sure you didn’t actually get, because there was no way to get it. Plus some pretty clear unresolved feelings for Tiff.”

“Humiliating,” he muttered as he opened another door. This one led into a long room with writing on every wall, and I closed my eyes, same as him, relying on other senses to guide me. It was possible the writing was harmless, but it seemed like a bad place to take chances.

“The difference,” I said, with my eyes screwed shut, “The difference is that I had the good sense to feel like shit about it. I made my apologies, eventually, to the extent I was able.” I gave myself a C-, which was still a passing grade. “What you’re doing is just — just ignoring this, pretending that it didn’t happen, making excuses for yourself, justifying it.”

“You can make excuses and justifications and still think that you did wrong,” replied Uther as we walked on. I used my senses to look back at the others, making sure that they were following behind us, and that they wouldn’t have trouble going blind. I wished that they weren’t privy to this conversation, especially Raven, but there was no way to avoid that without using vibration magic to block them completely, which I didn’t want to do either.

“You can, yeah,” I said. “Did you just get through forty years on Aerb and never learn how to give a proper apology?”

He sighed. “Apologize to your entad?” he asked.

“Yes,” I said. “But — she doesn’t really care about the weird sex stuff, she cares about being abandoned and having entads forced to become a part of her against her will. Also, and I know you know this, you’re just being a dick about it, she’s not my entad. On Earth, we call the concept of owning another person slavery.”

“Things are difficult and complicated on Aerb,” said Uther. We still couldn’t see each other, and my sense of the room wasn’t good enough to know what expression was on his face. “I don’t know how much you were exposed to, in your time so far, but there were debates that raged over things as simple as whether other species should count as being people. I wasn’t able to resolve it all, and there was always something new and different, a new species, a thorny new problem, some aspect of personhood that didn’t fit well into the models I’d made, your stupid slave species, inherent prejudices — and I know I’m not giving the apology you want, but if you keep casting aspersions, I’m going to deal with them as they come. Don’t brand me a slaver and then expect me to prostrate myself before you, whimpering like a scolded puppy.”

He must have been able to see my face far better than I was able to see his.

“I am sorry,” he finally said. “In a long life as a warrior, adventurer, and king, I’ve accumulated many regrets. That is one of them. I worried about it, because unlike the others, there was no defense, no weighing of costs or risks, just myself as a base and imperfect man. I am sorry, and I apologize.”

He reached the next door, still with his eyes closed, and stopped there for a moment with his hand on the doorknob. “Ready?” he asked.

“Yes,” I said.

He opened the door, and the next room was so blindingly bright that I was glad I had my eyes closed. Even then, I could see the light through my eyelids. Uther drew his sword, but the problem was solved with an arrow that sailed over my head and through the doorway. It shattered a bulb in the next room, and the light went away almost immediately.

“How could you even see that?” I called back to Fenn.

“Seeing your target is for chumps!” she yelled back to me.

I opened my eyes once we were in the formerly lit room. Uther was looking at the shattered lightbulb, which was as wide across as my shoulders.

“What’s the technology level of the Long Stairs?” he asked me.

“Uh,” I said. “Pre-industrial, or maybe not quite. Early modern, I guess.”

“1713?” he asked.

“No,” I replied. “Or, not quite.”

“And what the fuck is the significance of that date?” asked Fenn as she approached. It was the first thing she’d said in quite a bit, though I’d heard whispered conversations between the other members of the party as we’d gone along.

“It’s the date of Magus Europa,” said Amaryllis. “Juniper’s campaign setting about a magical version of early modern Europe.”

“Well, no,” I said. “I mean, that is the canonical date of the campaign, but it was picked because it marks the end of the War of Spanish Succession with the Treaties of Utrecht, along with the start of one of the Golden Ages of Piracy. But when I was thinking about the Long Stairs, my only firm thought was that it was pre-electricity and pre-electronics.”

“And yet,” replied Uther. “Here we see what was clearly a light bulb before an arrow smashed through it.”

“Sure,” I said. “It’s odd. Not that odd though, Long Stairs wasn’t meant to be one specific time or place. I could see myself throwing in a bank of weird 1960s era computers, just to make things more interesting.” I glanced at the toad on my shoulder. “Sometimes you make some rules, then you think up exceptions to those rules to keep them from feeling stale or overdone. I like rules with addendums. Maybe, I don’t know, the Long Stairs eventually adjust to all of the people coming in and dying. It sees all of the materials and equipment they have on them and starts adapting, or borrowing, or whatever it is, however it works. Makes it less compelling if the overarching processes are known though.” I was being distracted from the issue of Bethel. I was allowing myself to be distracted.

<What do you need from him?> I asked her, using multithreading. <I’m trying to argue on your behalf, but it’s difficult to know what you want.>

<I didn’t come here to face him down,> she replied. <I came here for you and the others, to make sure you don’t die. I came because I made a promise to Amaryllis. I didn’t need him to say that he was sorry or ashamed. If what we know about the Long Stairs is true, I will slowly die as I’m brought up. All I need is for you to bring me back down again.>

I frowned at the ring on my finger. <Where did your anger go?> I asked. It wasn’t just an idle question, I was seriously concerned that she might have had her mind screwed with.

<The anger is there,> she replied. <The instinct to kill is there. I have experience with controlling those emotions, understanding where they come from, and why acting on them would be bad.>

<Okay,> I said. <You can talk to me, if you need anything, if there’s something you want.>

“The death rate wasn’t that bad,” replied Uther, back on the other thread. “Though from what I’ve seen, these Long Stairs are considerably harder to handle. Because we started at the bottom, I wonder?”

“There was a second run of the campaign,” I said. “I ran it after you died.”

“Three times then,” said Uther. “We played a one-shot for Halloween.”

“Yeah, I guess,” I said. “There was nothing substantial about it though.”

“It had a heavier focus on memetics and antimemetics,” said Amaryllis. “At least, that was what you told me.”

Uther looked at her. “And you’re not Dahlia?”

“No,” she replied. “I only look like her. I’ve been to Cidium to visit the places she used to be, hoping that it would unlock something or jog a buried memory, but there was nothing.” This was news to me. “If there’s some secret to it, I don’t know it. Perhaps it’s just the Dungeon Master having a bit of fun. I’ve always wanted to see you in the flesh. You’re still the King of Anglecynn, if that means anything to you.”

“I thought that might be the case,” replied Uther. “And no, it means nothing. There is no argument, no form of persuasion, which could bring me back.”

“They came here,” said Raven. She’d come forward to stand beside Uther. “Your sons. You put yourself in stasis where you thought no one would be able to find you or get to you, and it was because they’d managed to track you down.”

He nodded.

“There was so much you never told me,” said Raven. “There was so much that went unspoken, so much that you kept to yourself. I was one of your Knights. I was — it was supposed to be a meaningful connection, but how could it have been when you stayed silent about everything that truly mattered?”

“You were twelve,” Uther replied, barely sparing a glance at her.

I waited. We waited. After all the words he’d spilled, it felt like a slap in the face to her that this was all he was willing to spare on the subject of why he hadn’t told her anything.

“You were twelve,” he said again, turning to her. “During my time on Aerb, I told exactly four people the truth of my origins. One of them was a girl I stayed with when I first got here. She died not long after I’d made the grand revelation to her, and wound up in the hells, which were not common knowledge at the time. Perhaps some infernal got the story out of her, but she knew me under my true name, Arthur Blum, rather than any of the pseudonyms I’d used. I was less careful, in those days, and for a long time counted myself lucky that I hadn’t suffered too greatly for it. When I had my first meeting with Vervain, I told him everything, and he took it in stride, then instructed me to keep it to myself while we figured things out. I told Forty-Two as well. He was the third, but only after we’d been together for quite some time. He’s —” he faltered for a moment. “He was a doppelganger, and quite adept at secrets. The fourth was, of course, my wife, from whom I kept no secrets.” He was silent for a moment. If Raven was right, and he’d deliberately flung himself forward in time through use of the bobbler, maybe the enormity of it was finally hitting him. “There were, perhaps, things I didn’t tell you which you might have been old enough, or at least mature enough, to handle. There were others that I entrusted to vanishingly few, simply as a matter of opsec.”

“You lied about the core of who you were,” said Raven. Her hands were balled up into fists. The explanation was clearly not sufficient for her. I hadn’t expected so much anger from her though.

“No,” he said, regarding her. “I lied about where I came from, but where I came from wasn’t core to who I was. My knowledge, my values, those I always did my best not to lie about, even when it might have served me well. I dragged Aerb, kicking and screaming, into something approaching the ideals of America as I’d known it. Democracy, freedom, equality, accountability, all were severely lacking when I arrived, and I did more than any one person should rightfully have been able to.”

“You lied ,” repeated Raven. “All the books you wrote, the songs, the inventions, all of it was from Earth. There’s hardly an original thought in there. It was a cloak.”

“And that’s what bothers you?” asked Uther, cocking his head to the side. “How many adaptations have you written without having access to the source material? It’s no easy feat. It’s not a matter of transcribing the words from one book to another, and even when I had enhanced my ability to remember things properly, even with entad support, nothing could survive the shift from one culture to another. Yes, each of them was from Earth, but they took my energy, they showed my imprint, my sensibilities and understanding of the world.” He looked at the rest of us. “How much more do I need to answer for my supposed crimes?”

“She’s not upset about the books,” I said, sighing. “I mean, she is, but she’s more upset that you, a friend and mentor, were lying to her for the entire time you knew her.”

Uther stared at me. “And do you know Raven as well as you knew Maddie?”

“No,” I said. I could feel my voice grow cold. He hadn’t said it like a dig, or an accusation, but it was really hard not to read into it. I could feel Raven shrinking under the implication. “It’s difficult to have someone you care about, someone you look up to, turn out to be less than you’d imagined them to be. You weren’t an endless font of creativity, so what? But that image of you that Raven, and I’m sure many others, had built up in their heads, just can’t stand up to reality. That’s a painful thing. Surely you can empathize with that?”

He gave me a slow nod. “You’ve changed.”

“Gods, I hope so,” I replied.

What worried me was that he hadn’t. I was meeting him at a strange time in his life, and we were dredging up all kinds of ancient history, but he was displaying the same tendency to argue things into the ground that he’d had on Earth. It was one of the things that had made him shitty at apologies, and he was apparently still not great at them. I supposed he hadn’t really had much cause for giving apologies, given how well everything usually turned out for him and how righteous his causes normally were.

Uther stalked off, and as before, we followed.

The Long Haul

You might be asking what I expected when we met Uther. Honestly, I’m not sure. Maybe I thought that it would all just end, and the Dungeon Master would pop out from behind a curtain and say, ‘Hey dude, congrats on saving your friend, it’s all over, you can do what you want with Aerb’. Maybe I thought the credits would roll. Maybe I thought there would be some reaction from Uther, a tearful reunion, something. I hadn’t expected what I got, which was a man who saw us as nothing, or as a tactic to bring him back, if we were real at all.

“Hey,” I said to Raven, keeping my voice low. We were walking through another large room, which was usually a bit of a chance for a break. This one had lots of books, but we were being careful not to look at them. “Are you okay?”

“No,” she replied. “I imagined this going differently.” She was about as morose as I’d seen her.

“He’s going to Earth,” I said. “The only way to stop him is going to be to physically stop him, and I’m not sure we would be able to do that.”

“Then we’ll go with him,” said Raven.

I watched her for a moment. “Not to put too fine a point on it, but everyone but me, Amaryllis, and Uther is at risk of death from a lack of magic. You in particular.”

“Wait,” said Fenn. “Why would an elf be at risk?” We were close enough for her to hear, but I’d been hoping that she would do the courtesy of ignoring the conversation.

“Because I don’t know how you’re built,” I said. “Your muscles aren’t like human muscles. You’re stronger than you should be. There’s no particular elf magic that someone could ward against, but it might be that you’d suffer a sickness if you were on Earth due to some physics incompatibility.”

“What,” she said. “Seriously? I’ve been prepping to go to Earth for ages and you’re springing this on me now?” When she said ‘prepping’, she really meant watching anime, I was pretty sure. Not that she hadn’t had it in her head that she would go there someday, or that she hadn’t learnt a lot about Earth with that in mind, but … this was the kind of mindset I’d always had toward Fenn, which had been a problem in our relationship.

“Juniper stole the concept from Vernor Vinge,” said Uther.

“No,” I said. “I mean, I was inspired by him, but I didn’t steal anything.”

“Yes, you did,” Uther replied. “The Long Stairs are a variant on Vinge’s Zones of Thought. The closer to Earth we get, the less permissive the physics are.”

I wanted to quibble on the word ‘closer’, but kept my mouth shut, because there was a coherent concept that was almost like ‘closer’. “Having a landscape of variable magic isn’t something that Vinge came up with, there’s loads of prior art. If anything, his application of that variability to science fiction was what was novel.”

“But we’re saying that I might get sick and die?” asked Fenn. “Because I’m not really keen on dying again.”

“You and Grak, yeah,” I said. “There was a world I built, which we never ended up playing, and I never ended up getting more than half-baked, where the far reaches could only be inhabited by humans. All the magic was toward Oros Olympos in the center of the world, and the further you got away from it, the less magic was sustained, until eventually you got far enough away that life itself was impossible. If the diminishing of magic in the Long Stairs is like that, then you’d end up suffering from something like radiation poisoning or malnutrition or … I don’t know, lots of things.” I glanced at the toad on my shoulder. “Even things that aren’t ‘magic’ might be affected.”

“You quoted ten percent,” said Uther. “Most artifacts can be taken just beyond Hellmouth, to the staging area, but only ten percent can be used on Earth proper. The least powerful ten percent, most likely. That’s what you said, in high school.” He had some kind of magical augmentation to his memory, because it was the kind of thing I didn’t remember saying.

“Which, again, means that it’s not Earth,” I said. “You and I grew up on an Earth where there were no magical items being brought up by a secret government organization in the Pacific Northwest.”

“This again?” asked Uther. “It’s a way back to Earth, the only way back to Earth that I’ve ever seen even a hint of.”

“I don’t want to keep saying it,” I said. “But I need to understand why you think it’s a good idea to even try, why Earth was worth abandoning Aerb for.”

“The second time,” said Uther as we walked through the stacks of books. “The second time I tried to leave Aerb for Earth, I was going to take my wife and children with me. I had an entad to keep the children safe, at least for as long as it kept working, but my wife insisted on being by my side. The lower half of her body had been replaced by an entad of my own creation, with legs like a spider, replacing not just her hips and limbs, but nearly her entire digestive system as well, everything below her rib cage. Without it, she wouldn’t have been able to breathe.”

“And what?” I asked as we approached the door. “You were just hoping that it would keep working?”

“I was,” he replied. “I was desperate to escape the cycles of adventure. I’d thought that the establishment of the First Empire would have been enough, once the fires had been put out, but it all kept going and showed no signs of stopping. The world was larger than just the kingdom I’d started in, larger than the surrounding continents, enormous in the context of Earth, but even after that, there were the various planes and realms, new spaces to explore and deal with, a whole other side to Aerb with a hostile and resilient empire of its own, always more and more and more. So yes, I was hoping that my wife would be able to make the trip with me, or that we would find some kind of solution to her illness. Instead, we made it to the third Landing before her entad gave out, and from there I was in a rush to return to Aerb, giving up the dream of Earth so that my children wouldn’t be deprived of their mother.”

“But you did leave them in the end,” said Amaryllis. “You left them, and all of Aerb.”

“Once they were all grown,” replied Uther. “My sons had grandchildren, who I was often too busy to see, and they had their own concerns, separate from mine. My daughter was an adventurer in her own right, and it was fairly clear that she was going down a different path than I’d gone down.” He cast a glance at Amaryllis, but swallowed whatever comparison he was going to make. “My wife gave her blessing for me to leave, and my obligation to her was the only one I felt truly bound by.”

He came to the door and stopped. “And that brings us to now. My time on Aerb has run its course. I’m being offered a new Aerb, one that’s five hundred years advanced, with all new adventures and problems, a successor empire to wrangle into submission, an Anglecynn court filled with descendants, new technologies, and shades of Earth. I refuse that offer. This is my last adventure.” He punctuated that declaration by opening the door.

Beyond lay the next Landing.

“You went hard on these Landings, huh?” asked Reimer.

“What does ‘going hard’ mean in this case?” asked Craig.

“Meaning, his worldbuilding muscle was fully erect,” replied Reimer with a laugh.

“You know that the penis isn’t a muscle, right?” asked Arthur. “It’s important to me that you know that.”

“What I meant was that Joon is really playing up the Landings,” said Reimer. “I mean, when the Long Stairs was pitched to us, it was a series of disconnected rooms, right? And strangely, no stairs at all?”

“They’re metaphorical stairs,” I said.

“Sure, but like … the Landings are these little cities, disconnected from the rooms,” said Reimer. “I was thinking they would be more cohesive, fit in a bit better? Like, if there was some kind of anchor you could produce with enough effort that would be able to lock a bunch of rooms together, and the Landings would be like, I don’t know, cities or something that were built around the anchors.”

That was actually a brilliant idea, and I saved it away for later. “Sorry to disappoint, I guess.”

“Nah, it’s fine,” said Reimer. “They’re like … really big, important rooms with more to explore and do. I wasn’t complaining, just, not what I’d expected. I like that you went hard on them. It’s like stopping in on a different world entirely, like we’re astronauts.” He looked at Arthur. “What’s Latin for ‘stairs’?”

“I’ve got no fucking idea,” replied Arthur. “Why do you think I speak Latin?”

“You’re interested in law stuff, right?” asked Craig.

“Sure, but that’s like twenty or so words,” said Arthur. I could see him mentally working through what the actual number was.

“Looks like it would be ‘scalar’,” said Reimer, looking up from his phone. “So we’d be scalarnauts.”

“The -naut suffix comes from Greek, not Latin,” said Arthur.

“Fine,” replied Reimer, looking down at his phone again. “Wait, it’s just ‘skales’ then. So scalarnaut is right.”

Arthur shrugged. “I don’t speak Greek either, for the record. Not sure that conjugation is right though. Might be more like ‘scalanaut’ or ‘scalnaut’ or something, if you had to make up a word.”

“The term is canonically ‘delver’,” I said. “I mean, there are two kinds of ways that people talk about things, the official documentation stuff where everything is given a number and designation, and the way the fireteams talk about things, which is usually a bit catchier.”

“And delver is which one?” asked Arthur.

“The latter,” I said. “The official designation for someone who routinely makes trips into the Long Stairs is LST, Long Stairs Traveler. Important mostly because the Long Stairs warps people, sometimes so much that they need cosmetic surgery to rejoin society, other times so much that there’s just no way that’s ever going to be possible.”

“And this Landing,” said Reimer. “The crystal skull place. That’s going to warp us too? Because it says in your RDP that everyone needs to acquire a crystal and put it into their own head before they leave.”

“Sure,” I said. “And you do.”

“But we would know what that means, right?” asked Reimer. “I mean, if it’s RDP, other teams have come down here and done that, so they know the procedures?”

“The acquisition process has been different every time,” I said. “And there have only been three teams that made it back from this Landing. As far as installation and what that means though, you’ll have a hole drilled in your head by one of these people, then have the crystal inserted, after which the hole will be sealed by affixing a gold coin in place and having your medic do healing on it.”

“And this is safe?” asked Arthur. “We’re not going to suffer from, oh, all the stuff you’d think you’d suffer from if primitive people were trepanning you with a crystal?”

“With healing magic, nothing major,” I said. “No psychological types or anything like that.”

“I’m all about crystals in the head,” said Reimer. “Also, how much of this was taken from the Matrix?”

“Five percent,” I replied with a smile. “But with more brutalist, imperfect transhumanism.”

The wet market Landing had been large, a big multi-level building that was maybe the size of a typical American shopping mall, but the crystal Landing was the size of a small city, with buildings like stalactites and stalagmites, giving the whole thing a feeling like you were walking through the maw of a creature with too many teeth. The style was adobe with more curves, and there were a paucity of right angles, which probably contrasted with the facets of the crystals. There was no greenery, nothing living aside from the people, no food, and barely any water.

The people of the crystal Landing had skin the same dun color of their adobe houses, and a skeletal look from their lack of muscles. Their heads were where they were most different from humans though. The tops of their skulls were open, and the multi-hued crystals, each of them shards, were sticking out of the top, packed in. They would reach up and rearrange them sometimes, or take one out to clean or inspect it. Their clothes were simple, woven out of a drab brown that was roughly the same color as their hair. They had hardly any nose at all, but wide mouths, which they breathed out of. Their eyes bulged from their heads, probably to give more room for the crystals.

“Everyone is clear?” asked Amaryllis. “We do our best to negotiate for a good crystal, have them implant it, then get out of here.”

“We have the offensive capacity to fight them,” said Uther, looking over the crystal people. “More than any fireteam.”

“Personally,” said Fenn. “I would rather not have brain surgery, especially if it’s from these guys.” She looked at me. “What kind of horrible thing happens if we try to leave without crystals in our heads?”

“They send out a tracking team that can follow you,” I said. I liked RDP as a concept, but the problem with it was that there needed to be concrete consequences if the players fucked up, and ‘oh, it just TPKs you’ wasn’t very fun. “If you kill one tracking team, they’ll send another, and another, and the only way you’ll be able to avoid them is if you get to Hellmouth.”

“We want that tracking ability, if possible,” said Amaryllis.

“It’s granted to them by the crystals?” asked Uther, looking at me, not her.

“It is,” I nodded. “It’s not complete knowledge of the Long Stairs, but it’s basically, ah, kind of a navigation package? It takes two crystals though, one to know where someone is, the other to path to a thing. They work in concert with each other.”

“All we would need to do is pick someone we know is on Earth,” said Uther. “Then we would have a straight path, without needing to follow any of these asinine rules.”

“In theory,” I said. “But we’d need to find one or more of these tracking teams, then get the crystals installed, then hope that Earth is close enough that we can name a person.” This was all in the Long Stairs Plan, at least in skeletal form.

“There are people named in the mapping book,” said Amaryllis.

“Fair point,” I said. “I guess that’s what we’re going for then.”

“I’ve already been altered by these people once,” said Uther, looking out over the city. “That’s how I became an omniglot.”

Raven turned to him. “You never said.” It wasn’t quite an accusation.

“I said only that it was something that needed to be kept secret,” replied Uther, not looking at her. “And I believed that to be true. The Long Stairs, and the connection to Earth, were something I took great pains to not reveal to anyone. So far as I know, I was the first person to go through the door, and I built a disguised vault around it after I came back out.” Whatever the big climactic battle had been, I was pretty sure there’d been nothing of the sort, though that wasn’t very surprising. “Still, if you are here, it’s likely that others will follow. All the more reason to hurry along.”

“Others?” asked Raven.

“My sons both followed me down, wanting my blessing for their rule, wanting advice,” he said. “I sent them away. It was those long conversations that made me think I might escape into the future to continue my journey, though the rule of three had been invoked and found wanting.” He clapped his hands together. “So, shall we go shopping for crystals?”

“Lead the way, I guess,” I said.

When Uther had said he was an omniglot, he had apparently meant it without qualifiers. The speech of the crystal people was like nothing I had ever heard before. When I tried, my mouth couldn’t even make the right noises. Uther was doing it through vibration magic, but he was far, far more skilled than I was, and I’d run down my supply of breath by pulsing on magic vision every now and then. Maybe if I’d had time to play around with it I’d have been able to figure out efficiently generating the chords that made up their language, but that still would have left me unable to speak it.

We followed after him, mostly, and sat around while he conversed with the crystal people. This kind of thing was Uther’s bread and butter, and once upon a time, in the campaigns I’d run, it had been Arthur’s bread and butter too. He loved to talk to people, to make deals, to figure out what they wanted or how they operated. Of course, I was the one coming up with all the people, the same actor with a thousand different faces and personalities, and for the most part, I was amenable to diplomatic solutions, even if it was better if there was some combat sprinkled in there somewhere.

I wondered whether following behind him, unable to understand, was how his Knights felt, and decided that it probably was. Then I wondered whether that was how the other players had felt at the table, and … well, mostly they had been fucking off, or getting in their jokes, so I thought probably not. I made a mental note to speak with Reimer and Tiff about it, if I ever saw them again.

“There’s a problem,” said Uther, after an extended conversation with one of the crystal people. “The tracking crystals are held by only a select few and regulated by their government, such as it is. If we kill one and steal their crystals, we’ll need to do it quietly so as not to alert the guard, because otherwise we won’t be able to make it through installation.”

“And we’re all doing this?” asked Fenn. “We’re all getting black market crystals through the brain? Because that seems insane, even for us.”

“I’ve already done it,” replied Uther, tapping his head. “And I’m as sane as they come.” He gave Fenn a grin, and maybe it was my imagination, but there was a faint flirtatiousness that I didn’t like. “Our other option is to deal with the kill teams as they come, or kill our way through enough of these people that they won’t send a kill team. Either would do, I think, but getting the tracking crystals for ourselves seems like it gives us the shortest path back to Earth.”

“We can’t kill these people,” said Raven. “They’ve done nothing wrong.”

“They would track us and attempt to kill us if we left without adding modifications to our brains,” said Uther. “I would hardly call that ‘nothing wrong’. You’d have us instead enter into protracted peaceable negotiations with these people? They consider me little more than a mongrel, and the rest of you are protected from slavery only by virtue of our obvious physical might. There are humans here, from Earth, living in thrall to the crystalids.”

Raven gave him a sour look, but had no rebuttal. I assumed that Uther had been telling the truth, because it was the kind of thing that I would have included in this place, if it had gotten enough playtime to be fleshed out. Three teams had returned from the Landing, which meant that some unknown number had gotten there and then been killed, captured, or worse. It wouldn’t have been a particular surprise that there was a fireteam somewhere in the city, stripped of their gear and working as menial slaves.

“If there are human prisoners, we should go free them,” said Amaryllis.

Uther gave a beleaguered sigh. “A quest,” he said.

“We have the one book,” said Amaryllis. “They might have another, which would let us compare and find areas of information rot. They might have expertise in the ways and means of the Long Stairs, codes that they might be able to give us.”

“I’m not saying the premise is thin,” said Uther. “But it’s clear you’re stalling for time, hoping that I’ll change my mind about Aerb.”

“Then you misunderstand me,” said Amaryllis. “You misunderstand me quite a bit, if you think that it’s ‘clear’. Aerb is dead and gone. There is only the Long Stairs, and Earth.”

Uther stared at her for a moment. “Do you think it was a dark curse that made you so much like her?” he asked. “A cloning program? Some magic to pull her from the weave of space and time?” He shook his head. “Another quest. Always another quest.” He seemed to be considering it, as though he wanted to get to the bottom of a mystery. “No, the two we need are there,” he pointed to one of the larger stalactite houses. “I’ll go there, kill them, take their crystals, and we’ll have them installed.”

“They’ll have telepathy,” I said.

“They will?” he asked.

“Maybe,” I said. “I mean, I would have included it. Maybe not high-powered instant information transfer, but if they’re going to be sending kill teams after the party, then yeah, they should have some way of knowing whether it was working or not. So maybe not strict telepathy, I guess, but they’d need the equivalent of radio, which doesn’t work in the Long Stairs, and if they have the crystals anyway … then sure, I would expect them to have telepathy crystals of some kind.”

“So we’ll need to kill them quickly,” nodded Uther. He pulled the amulet of non-detection from nowhere in particular and paused for a moment. “I’ll be back quickly.”

And then the amulet was on him, and there was no sign that he had been there at all.

“He used to feel bad about killing guards and soldiers,” said Raven. “He was slow to get to this point. As time went on, he had less patience for those who had put their life on the line for a cause or a coin. The problem of what to do with guards … you’ve run across it yourself, Juniper. Uther wrote about it in Degenerate Cycles, how the same problem gets revisited from different angles multiple times to show different facets and aspects, until eventually there’s nothing left to learn from it, nothing to show, everything drawn from it.”

“And this is what he settled on?” I asked.

“It’s the most expedient,” replied Amaryllis. “Killing goes quickly. He probably wouldn’t put it in those terms, but he already doesn’t think that any of it is real. The need to be morally upstanding goes away when you think that you’re the center of a world which keeps setting up challenges for you.”

“But we agree that’s what the world is, don't we?” asked Raven. She turned to me. “The Dungeon Master said as much to you.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I mean, kind of, in a sense. The uh, … the reality or irreality of everything is the kind of thing that I don’t think we want to spend too much time dwelling on, and which I think Uther has spent a lot of time dwelling on. The Dungeon Master’s own actions make more sense if the reality he’s created isn’t real, I guess. It would mean he’s only a little monster, not a big monster, if we’re thinking intent matters.”

“And you think there’s a chance that’s true?” asked Raven. “That this, all of this, is fake?”

“Well,” I said. “Fake is a strong word. ‘Virtual’ seems like it would be more likely, even if there would be a lot of problems there, and it would need tech so astronomical that it would basically be magic. But a virtual world wouldn’t be ‘fake’, really. I mean, at least as I’ve always seen it, the mind runs on the hardware of the brain. Change the hardware — and that’s probably harder than it probably sounds — but you’d still get something like the mind. The only reasons you couldn’t replicate a world in silicon are technical, economic, and moral.”

“You’re ceding too much ground to him,” said Raven.

“Well, I’m not trying to convince him that the world is real,” I said. “I’m not even trying to convince him that his actions have consequences. I just want to … to talk to him, I guess. To get him to sit down and to explain things to him, and have him explain back.”

“And that’s what you think we’re here for?” asked Raven, folding her arms. “The world is dying.”

“I’m here for that too,” I said. “But bringing Uther back to continue his adventures, so he can play Atlas with the world on his shoulders for another few decades … I can see how he’d think that was what we showed up for, but I can’t imagine that the point of all this was for us to do that to him. Or, I can imagine that it was the point, but I don’t feel like it’s something I’m therefore obligated to do.”

Bethel appeared beside us, frowning slightly. “Then you’ll take him to Earth?” she asked.

“Are you okay?” asked Fenn.

“I’ll be fine so long as no one inquires after me,” said Bethel, shooting Fenn a frosty look. There was some of the old Bethel there, the Bethel who couldn’t stand the thought of being seen as weak. It was no surprise that it had resurfaced, given what had happened. I still thought that Uther deserved a punch in the face for it, or some more severe comeuppance.

“I’ll follow him to Earth,” I said. “Or I’ll convince him to come back to Aerb. But if I do that, it won’t be because I’m trying to convince him that the degenerate cycles are good, it’s because I’ll have found some way to stop them altogether.”

“And does such a way exist?” asked Uther, who appeared next to us as he took off the amulet. As he did, Bethel vanished.

“Not yet, no,” I said. “I’ll think of something.”

“We need to discuss how much further we’re going in the Long Stairs,” said Grak.

“To Earth,” replied Uther, looking at Grak as though he’d forgotten Grak existed.

“You are,” replied Grak. “I do not want to risk going past where warding works. Do you know where that is?”

“Somewhere between here and the next Landing,” replied Uther.

“Hrm,” replied Grak. He looked at me. “There are two options. Either I will go with you until warding fails, then return here, or I will stay here while you go ahead.”

“Ah,” I said. “Second option seems a lot safer for you, so I guess I’m going with that. But … are you sure? I mean, to come all this way and then turn back?”

“Warding is my skill,” said Grak. “It is my contribution to the team and my ultimate defense against harm. Without it, the risk that I would die rises dramatically. I’ve sparred with Amaryllis. I’m not the warrior she is, and she pales in comparison to the rest of you.”

Amaryllis nodded.

“Okay,” I said. “If you’re sure. I mean, the whole trip is voluntary, always was.”

I had seen the looks that passed between Amaryllis and Grak, and wished that I had been a snoop and listened in on their conversations. My hunch was that he wasn’t just leaving because he thought he was going to be useless, he was leaving because Amaryllis had convinced him that was where the narrative was going. Grak wasn’t useless without his warding, I was pretty sure he knew that, but he was right that he would be taking a larger hit to power than anyone else.

“I hope you don’t take this as abandonment,” said Grak. “I will wait a month for you. Then I will head back on my own and assume you are dead.”

“I attacked and killed four men in there,” said Uther, gesturing at one of the buildings that hung from the ceiling. “That might create a problem for you.” He looked down at the amulet in his hands, then passed the amulet of nondetection to Grak.

“This is too generous a gift,” said Grak, not taking it.

“It’s served its function,” said Uther. “I always make sure not to use any particular trick too many times. Besides, I don’t expect it to have much life in it once we go further into the Long Stairs.”

Grak slowly took the amulet from him, looking it over with what I assumed was warder’s sight. “Thank you,” he said with a low bow.

“Anyone else want to hole up with Grak?” I asked, looking at the others. <Anyone?> I didn’t let my eyes go to the ring on my finger, but I was definitely thinking about Bethel. She was shutting down by degrees, that much was clear, I could see that, and if she wanted to escape from Uther, given she couldn’t properly confront him any more than we already had, I wasn’t about to blame her. I looked at Raven. “You’re not going to be able to make it all the way,” I said. “And the next Landing … I guess you could drop off there too, if you need to.”

“I’m going all the way,” said Raven. “To Earth, if that’s what it takes to bring Uther home.”

“It might kill you,” I said. “I mean, you could go from living to dead in an instant.” I tried not to think too much about what that would look like.

“Then I’ll die,” Raven replied. Her eyes burned into my own. Uther, for his part, was looking away, giving the whole conversation some distance, as though it didn’t concern him.

“Fenn?” I asked.

“Do you really think so little of me that you think I wouldn’t speak up if I didn’t want to come?” she asked. “I’m going to Earth too, unless the going gets tough.”

“Then let’s go,” said Uther. He held up a handful of crystals. “We still need to get these installed.”

I was, strangely, not very frightened of the whole process. I should have been, and briefly considered that there might be some effect preventing my natural reaction, but I guess I was kind of treating it like a visit to the doctor’s office, or the dentist. It wasn’t going to be pleasant, but I was putting my faith in the process, the same way I did when the doctor told me to go take some pills. Just like then, it wasn’t like I could do my own independent verification, so why worry?

A lot of that faith went out the window when I saw the thing that was going to do the surgery. It wasn’t a doctor at all, but a bulky arm sprouting up from the center of a round room. Back on Earth, there were surgical robots, and it seemed like maybe it was inspired by one of those. It got narrower along the ten or so joints, until it terminated in ‘fingers’ that themselves had forks, like a hand with each finger having its own hand. There was a chair right in front of it, and a table of implements that the grotesque hand could reach for. I looked down, at the point where the thing came up from the floor, and it was clear that there was something down there, some larger organism of indeterminate size that was sticking this complicated hand-thing through a hole. I couldn’t see any eyes, so how it was going to sense me while it was doing the operation was in question.

“Uh,” I said. I’d been led into the room by one of the crystal people, with my two crystals in hand.

“Place the crystals on the table and sit down,” said a voice from a hole in the wall. It was in perfect English, most likely thanks to the same omniglot crystal that Uther already had in him. So far as I could tell, most of the crystal people seemed to see us as poor unfortunates.

I placed the two crystals down and sat in the chair, though my nerves were definitely getting to me. We had never actually gotten to this part of things when I’d run the campaign, and they’d only been to the Landing once, which was enough to play out all the things I found interesting. The room with the crazy surgery claw seemed familiar, but it was from the first iteration of the campaign, ages ago, and it had never been used. I couldn’t remember if I had come up with mechanics for it, but if I had … you wouldn’t want to outright kill a player, you wanted to give them a complication of some kind. At its most basic, that would be reduced health, but there were lots of complications you could throw at someone. Or maybe, if the crystals had been hard-won, it would be fine to present them as a kind of boon.

I accepted my fate though. There was a chance that we should have just risked the kill-teams, especially with Uther having killed a fair number of the crystal people already, but they would become more of a problem the further up the Long Stairs we got, and handling them when we were, presumably, just baseline humans might have been a real problem. Besides, this way we’d have a way to make a beeline toward the top, or as much as you could do that in the Long Stairs.

The hand went for the table and hesitated, its fingers moving in mid-air as it seemed to decide what it was going to do. That wasn’t particularly encouraging. Even less encouraging was when the hand went down to the table and began feeling for the tools, touching various handles, which I noticed had little notches on them to differentiate them.

The conclusion that the hand was blind was reinforced when it used one of its fingers to feel around in the air until it touched my head, then carefully, gingerly, held my head in place. Another part of the hand picked up a variety of tools from the table, blades and chisels, touching the tips of them briefly to check for sharpness.

“Anesthetic?” I asked.

There was no response from whoever was monitoring the procedure. Uther hadn’t mentioned any pain, but it was possible it had slipped his mind. I held as still as I possibly could, trying to avoid anything that would cause this device or creature to fuck things up.

There was no pain. The sensation was, instead, like someone applying an ice cube to my forehead, cold but not overly so, and then there was some shifting of the skin there, tugging one way and then the other. I was fully conscious for all of it, and saw a piece of my skull, flesh still attached to it, removed and set in place on the work table. The part of the hand that wasn’t holding my head picked up one of the crystals, again blindly feeling for it like it had done with the instruments, then inserted it into my head at full speed, like a windmill slam. I felt nothing, but suddenly had the awareness of where Fenn was, though it didn’t extend much beyond a general directionality and distance. There was some other ability attached to it, allowing me to switch who my target was, but before I could experiment, the second crystal was slammed in next to the first. It didn’t seem like there would have been enough room in my head for one of them, let alone two, but there were some kind of space shenanigans going on. The second crystal gave me the path to Fenn, detailed down to specific instructions on how to open the door, and it took me a moment to figure out how to shut the blaring information out.

The arm replaced the piece of my skull, then worked at the spot on my forehead with its tools. I waited, idly testing my new abilities, and eventually, the voice from the wall told me to be on my way.

“That was surprisingly pleasant,” I said, touching the spot on my forehead. There was no sign that anything had happened there. The skin had been repaired and the bone had been healed. It wasn’t the kind of messy transhumanism that I usually favored, it was just … done, without any apparent complication.

Amaryllis was the next to go in, and I turned my new ability to her as the door closed behind her, which gave me a sudden sharp headache. “Ow,” I said.

“Problem?” asked Fenn.

“Crystal’s not equipped to handle someone in several places at once,” I said. “They were trying to guide me to her and all of her clones back on Aerb.”

“Meaning you saw a path?” asked Fenn.

“No,” I replied. “Just a painful confusion. Fuck.” I’d switched back to tracking Fenn almost immediately. “It’s a two crystal system,” I said. “Pretty sure the problem is with the first crystal, trying to say where she is, because she’s in thirty fucking places at once.”

“Clones?” asked Uther. “Powerful magic. While we wait, would you mind telling me how it’s done?” He took out his wand from extradimensional space and began putting up wards, which I thought was more out of habit than for any real practical reason. I waited until he was done.

“Part of the game system,” I said. “She can concentrate for a bit to make one, then concentrate to merge in their experiences.”

“But in terms of what’s happening at the lower level?” asked Uther.

“We don’t know,” I said. “Probably nothing. It’s like an entad that you can’t take away from her.”

Uther narrowed his eyes. “So you’re saying she’s a witch.”

“Uh,” I said. “Is that a joke?”

He cocked his head to the side and looked at me. “Don’t you remember that one? We used to do it all the time in the Magus Europa campaign.”

“Ah,” I said. “Guess I forgot.”

Fenn was the next to go in, after giving Amaryllis a very careful inspection to make sure that she was lucid and not profusely bleeding.

Once Amaryllis was out, she did almost the exact same thing that I had done, which was to grip her head in pain before recovering.

“Yeah,” I said. “I can’t track you, I think it’s because of the copies. Sorry, I should have warned you.”

“Then why doesn’t it work when I try it on you?” asked Amaryllis.

I frowned, then tried using the power on myself, and got the same instant splitting headache. “Ow,” I said. “Once Fenn gets out we’ll find out whether you can use the power on yourself, just to clear up whether that’s the issue. Seems like something QA could miss.”

“That still wouldn’t explain why I can’t use it on you,” said Amaryllis.

“Naively, we should expect a second Juniper,” said Uther. He pointed up, which was, by agreement, the direction we were pretending Earth was.

“Huh,” I said. Then, “No. Or, I guess … I can disambiguate the two Reimers, the Earth one and the Aerb one. Same with Tiff. They’re not copies, so maybe it’s different, but if there’s a Juniper up on Earth, then … he shouldn’t be the same as me.”

“Another mystery,” sighed Uther. “Another intriguing complication designed to pull us from the path toward Earth.” He gave me a faint smile. “Can you see how desperate it is?”

“If it were true,” I said.

“You don’t deny that the world is fake,” said Uther. “You’ve spoken to its architect, as I have. What more is there to question?”

I kept my thoughts to myself. There was loads more to question, different aspects that could be tugged at, but he didn’t want to hear any of it. I didn’t think that our team was specifically designed to pull him back, but I could see how it might look like that to him. And he had been through hundreds of quests and experienced this kind of thing before, or if not the specific aspect of fleeing to Earth, then probably some others that seemed similar. Trying to debate it with him, at this stage, seemed like it would be foolish.

We went through, one by one, all but Grak, who had said his goodbyes and found lodging in a different part of the Landing. Further testing confirmed that Amaryllis and I were the only ones that the tracking didn’t work on, and while the fact that she had clones who were functionally ‘her’ seemed like the obvious reason it didn’t work on her, it was still a mystery why it didn’t work on me. Another Juniper, somewhere, was the best theory we had, but who, where, and why were all open questions. It was entirely possible there was a Juniper up on Earth, one close enough to me that he counted as being the same, which was a weird thought.

When we were done, and everyone was modded, we left the Landing. There was a chance that they would send kill teams after us anyway, but most of them were dead, and Uther had done his part to make the killings untraceable. The amulet of non-detection, now in Grak’s care, erased forensic evidence, not that the crystal people had that in spades. Still, it was a disquieting insight into how Uther dealt with things, and didn’t bode well for what might come next.

A Long Row to Hoe

The third Landing was a maze, one of such great size that traveling through it, even on the correct path, was going to take a while. The walls were a hundred feet tall and twenty feet apart, featureless dark grey, capped with regular lighting that gave a hostile, institutional vibe. It was all laid out in a circle, but it was big enough that the curvature wasn’t the most obvious thing about it. The maze was, by design, incredibly boring, except that people lived there, and had pretty much taken the whole place over.

We had the crystals in our skull, which I hoped wasn’t an Indiana Jones reference, so the maze portion of things wasn’t all that relevant to us, it was simply a matter of following the steps as laid out for us.

“How confident are we in this alien pathfinding?” asked Amaryllis.

“Not very,” I said.

“But how long could the maze really take to walk if you were just brute forcing it?” asked Fenn. “Weeks? Months?”

“There are people here who believe that the maze is the entirety of their universe,” said Uther. “Toward the center, there are tribes for whom any expedition that might have any remote hope of reaching the outside walls would be the equivalent of sending a galleon across the Atlantic in the 1400s. Perhaps not impossible, but so costly and dangerous that no one would ever do it.”

“That seems a bit extreme,” frowned Fenn.

“To walk the entirety of the maze would take decades,” I said. “The place was supposed to be so massive that it could serve as a brick wall unless you had help.”

“Any particular reason that people haven’t just marked up the place?” asked Fenn, who had definitely not read up on the Long Stairs as much as she was supposed to.

“If you follow markings, you’re liable to run into traps or trouble,” I said. “Or just end up at Wall Drug.”

“When we get to Earth, I’m going to Wall Drug,” said Fenn. “First stop.”

“You understand Wall Drug sucks, right?” I asked. “I’ve been there like three or four times. It’s a successful advertising campaign, that’s all it is. It’s a place you go only so you can say that you went there, and because there’s fuck all to do when driving across South Dakota.”

“Still,” said Fenn. “You want me to be a normie and go visit the Statue of Liberty?” She paused for a second. “Wait, I just realized I’m not American.”

“Just now?” asked Amaryllis.

“There are going to be military guys at the Earth end of this trip, right?” asked Fenn. “Surely they have some kind of immigration and naturalization policy for people who come up from the depths of the spooky dungeon.”

“They probably have vivisection policies,” I said. “Or maybe it’s in an era where they don’t do that anymore, I guess. MRI, definitely, sedated to get a clear image, since that’s a method for detecting some of the anomalous mental disorders.” I looked at Uther. “You really think that they would just let you go? Or are you planning to fight your way through without any magic? I mean … you’re dead, up on Earth.”

“I don’t know,” he said. “I’m hoping that they let me through. I’m hoping for a return. An end to it all.”

The words echoed in my head. “Not sure that’s going to work,” I said weakly.

“You understand it doesn’t matter?” asked Uther. “Whatever happens when I get back up there, it’s part of the contract of narrative that I be put back into my old life, even if that makes no sense. Perhaps it will be a matter of RDP that they give the people found in the Long Stairs a good, normal Earth life. I don’t care how it’s done, but it will be done. The narrative’s not complete without it. And if the Dungeon Master continues his reach to Earth and uses me as his plaything, then I will have done everything in my power under the structures presented to me to stop it.”

We took a left without even discussing it. Oddly, it had been all lefts from the moment we’d come through, which did seem a little suspect. The first time we got directed down a dead end and were instructed to double back, we would know that something was up, but I really hoped that “just always turn left” wasn’t the kind of algorithmic complexity we were dealing with. If it was, we were going to have some problems getting through the maze. I wondered how the crystal people did it, but it was way too late to ask them.

“Problem up ahead,” said Uther. He put his hand to the wall. “There’s a fight.” He sighed. It was, I supposed, the kind of thing that he’d been through a hundred times before. We’d even been through it twice in the Long Stairs already, looking in on big fights between two sides where we didn’t have any actual stake in the matter. There, we’d left them alone, but there was a chance that wouldn’t be possible in the maze, not if they were part of some organized society. Or maybe we would just resist taking a side and cut our way through, killing all witnesses. Uther hadn’t done that yet, but the incident with the crystal people had raised my war crime senses.

The scene we came on would have been utterly confusing, if I hadn’t been the one to design it. There was a thick layer of soil on the ground, and fir trees growing up toward the lights that were high overhead. There were dozens of people among the trees, fighting with each other using mostly crude wooden tools — tools, not weapons, things that were used for some other work but picked up for combat because needs must. One side was men and women with red skin, all of them lanky and missing their lower jaws, with bulbous noses. The other side were a more eclectic mix of the Long Stairs species, including two of the crystal people and one of the elf replacements.

It was a resource war. Trees took a very long time to grow, and timber was the only real building material available in the maze. Anyone who built a tree farm was extremely forward thinking, though it was entirely possible that something like this could occur naturally if the corridor was left alone for long enough. The fact that all the trees I could see were still standing was a good sign that this particular war was recent, since one side or the other presumably wanted to cut them down.

“Who are we siding with?” asked Uther. “They both seem equally poorly armed.”

“We might be able to bypass this,” I said, frowning at the fight. They were killing each other, and the opportunity for intervention was closing. Looking at it logically, we should help the people who weren’t ethnically homogenous, because they were the ones most likely to accept humans into their midst. I looked to Uther. “How well do you think you could disarm them and make the fighting stop?”

Uther frowned at the battle, then sprang forward, fast as the wind. When he descended on someone, it was like they’d been struck by lightning, and they were invariably left dazed on the ground, largely uninjured. Sometimes he used his sword to cut apart their implements, but other times he would slap them across their face with the flat of his blade, somehow avoiding cutting them in the process. I rushed over to join him, not that I could match his feats, and as I was on my way over, dozens of arrows went over my head and into the melee, pinning people to trees and knocking weapons from hands, mostly just so Fenn could demonstrate her prowess.

By the time I got there, the fighting had died down and the yelling had picked up. Amaryllis almost immediately began administering marzipan fairies to the wounded, pantomiming that they should eat them. Once the first of them began healing, the rest noticed and began following suit, often with a rush of words I couldn’t understand from the others.

Uther held forth. I couldn’t understand a word he said. We hadn’t gotten any of the new polyglot crystals, which was an immeasurable disappointment, because I wanted that far more than the tracking ones. He was switching between languages, holding a conversation with both sides at once, and from what I could gather, both mediating a ceasefire and serving as translator. Of course, a ceasefire was a lot easier to organize when you’d just single-handedly demonstrated that you could personally kill all forty-some people in the general vicinity before any of them could escape.

“Alright,” he finally said. “It’s handled. This corridor has valuable trees, and they’ve been fighting over them. Today was the day that the reds were going to harvest all of them, which is why the blues came in to stop them, not because they wanted the wood, but because they’re a natural wonder of the maze and, in a roundabout way, they understand that trees provide air.” He sighed. “It’s so boring, do you understand that Juniper? Did you read Degenerate Cycles at all?”

“I did,” I said. “Eventually you run out of things to say, and if you keep pushing the cycles beyond that, it will be flat and emotionless repeats, even if the context is different. Each new cycle must either shed light on some new thing or give different illumination to something in the past, and eventually even the new things start to look like the old things. It seemed kind of like an argument against immortality. You used to hate those.”

“Well,” he replied. “I still do. But life as a whole is not about conflicts and their resolutions. Life doesn’t need to be about what’s new. When I talked about living forever, I wasn’t thinking about having to solve new and interesting conflicts. I was thinking of pleasant but ultimately unimportant days. But that, of course, would be the obliteration of narrative. The stakes would be nonexistent, and that would be fine. I just never believed that anhedonia would be a real problem, which is what people always went back toward. And on Aerb, that wasn’t the problem. The problem was the stakes, the risk, the conflict, the danger.” He gestured in the direction of the fight he’d stopped, with the people gathered in their own two groups among the trees. “This wasn’t interesting or a challenge, so it has no role in the narrative. It wasn’t pleasant to solve their disputes, but it’s the kind of thing I could handle. Unfortunately, for there to be a real conflict, there need to be stakes, and those stakes are inclined to increase over time. And even then I might have endured, save for the falseness of it all, the way that everything was planned and choreographed.”

“Okay,” I said. “Sure. But you don’t think it’s all at an end here? I mean, you could return to Aerb, and the narrative would be over.”

“You said things were bad there,” said Uther. “I’ve heard claims that there are problems that require my intervention. It’s a call to adventure, levied against someone who has responded to thousands of them.”

“So what was your solution?” asked Raven, looking at the trees. “One group wanted the trees for lumber, the other for oxygen, how did you split the difference?”

“By the terms I negotiated, they’ll hold off on gathering the lumber until there are enough saplings to replace them,” said Uther. “Who knows whether that agreement will hold, but raw might was enough to get them to agree to it. I didn’t suggest that I would personally murder everyone here if they didn’t come to an agreement, but they could imagine it, I’m sure.”

“And now?” I asked. “Do we have some lead if the crystals are foiled by having complex pathfinding?”

“None at all,” replied Uther. “The Conguine are likely to be more friendly to us. They have a city not too far from here that we could visit, if we find ourselves taking too long of a path. Neither side so much as acknowledged that there was an exit. When I mentioned it, it seemed to be a bit of a faux pas. It’s very possible that the crystals will guide us through there anyhow. The Conguine control much of this area, particularly the surrounding choke points.”

“And which are the Conguine?” I asked. “The motley crew or the red skins? Okay, now that I say it, red skins is probably not appropriate.”

“It’s what their name translates to,” shrugged Uther. “And their skin is quite literally red. But no, the Conguine are the other ones. From what I can tell, they’re hippies.”

“Conguine as opposed to sanguine?” I asked. “Meaning, uh, with blood?”

“It’s my own translation,” replied Uther. “And it would be ‘con’ as in ‘together’. One Blood might have been better, though less literal.”

“And they’re concerned primarily with keeping the maze as a living ecosystem?” I asked.

“From what they say, yes,” replied Uther. “I don’t care one way or another. The Long Stairs are even less real than Aerb is. There’s some permanence with regards to the Landings, but not all that much. Whether this place lives or dies is immaterial.”

“Let’s keep going then,” I replied. I didn’t like that kind of talk, not just because of what he was saying about Aerb, but because I cared whether the ecosystem inside the maze continued. How could you not be fascinated by whole civilizations living inside a maze, with no building wider than twenty feet, with farms built in strips, and all kinds of other things?

<How are you doing?> I asked Bethel as we walked.

<I’ve been thinking,> she replied.

I wasn’t sure how to respond to that, whether it was an invitation for me to ask for more information or not. I stayed quiet, allowing her time to think. I really should have handed her off to someone else, because there was no reason she should have been my responsibility, but some perverse part of me really did think of her as needing protection from Uther. None of us could possibly beat him in a fight, but I came the closest, and I thought maybe he would listen to me more than the others.

<I want to come with you,> she said. <The others are going to be left behind as we ascend. I will lose function. I can tell already that my mind is shutting down, piece by piece. While I’m still able to make plans, I want to let you know that I want to go all the way. When I’m only an entad, use me to help you stay alive and to see Uther to his destination.>

<Okay,> I replied.

I waited for more, but there was nothing.

I took the toad down from his perch on my shoulder and looked at him, first making sure that all his flowers and leaves and moss and things were still there, and then into his eyes. “How about you?” I asked. “Are you coming to the top, if that’s where we’re going? Can you?”

The toad blinked at me, then hopped back up onto my shoulder, seeming annoyed that he’d been moved. I was pretty sure that he was capable of turning into a human if he wanted to, just like the other locus, but he felt no particular need to. I was less sure that he was capable of speech, or even understanding speech, but there was no way to get a real answer.

When that was finished, Amaryllis came to stand beside me. “I have a confession,” she said as we walked. There was a lot of walking in this Landing. The corridors were pretty bare, because these were places that no one had taken over for their own. The tree farm, it seemed, had been placed where it was in order to be out of the way. “I don’t really understand the appeal of this place.”

“I wouldn’t want to live here,” I said. “But I’d guess you’re talking about some other kind of appeal?”

“You created it because you found it compelling,” said Amaryllis. “What’s compelling about it? What is there for people to like about it?”

“I can field this one,” said Fenn.

“Can you?” I asked.

“Oh, sure,” replied Fenn. “You see, back in 2016, there was a factory game called Factorio, and in Factorio, there were a variety of world settings, and one of these settings was for world height, and you could set it very low if you wanted. If you set it low enough, that was called a ribbon world, and it was Juniper’s favorite thing ever, at least for a few days. It was the constraint of it, the absurdity of it that he loved, a basic concept taken to its very extreme, or at least to the extreme that still allowed things to get interesting. He saw these ribbon worlds and a whole region of his little teenage brain lit up, like someone had set off the flashbulb in there, and he started drawing up plans while he should have been paying attention to school, plans for how thin a strip of land people could live in, if they had barely any technology at all. He started thinking about these walls,” she gestured to the walls on either side. “And he thought to himself, ‘how close could those walls be, if you could never be in a place that had any wider’, and apparently the number he pulled from a hat was twenty feet, enough that you could make an easy barricade, enough so that you’d have a hard time not noticing someone if they passed by you, enough so that, I don’t know, you could conceivably not die if you had soil and seeds and water and light.” She turned to me. “That was my best Juniper impression, by the way.”

“It was very manic,” I said.

“The timeline wouldn’t have worked,” said Arthur. “Juniper’s brief obsession with ribbon worlds came later. This was here from much earlier on.”

“Fenn is right though,” I said. “The second time we did Long Stairs, the enormous maze was influenced by ribbon world stuff.” When I’d made the connection, I had a brief hour of happiness, the kind I would desperately try and inevitably fail to recapture from the midst of a haze of depression and hatred. “The original was much more focused on ant farms and terrariums, but for people, and as a maze rather than a straight line. But it always was about putting as many possible constraints in as I could while keeping it interesting, pushing things until the point where they would almost break, then pushing them just beyond that so I could see the break happen.”

Uther stopped in his tracks. “That was it,” he said. “That was the part that I was missing.”

“Uh, okay?” I asked.

He turned to me. “I had always thought that it was you, somehow,” said Uther. “They were your worlds, after all, mashed together, refined, and remixed. I thought that it was you, pulling the strings, for whatever reason. But if that was the case, the thing I couldn’t understand was why you would have kept on going, especially after the confrontation with Vervain. Why make a narrative that never ends? Why allow it to go on to the point of absurdity, straining the very boundaries of convention? It was your particular imp of the perverse, that’s why. I don’t know how I never saw it, because when I think of it, it’s the answer to so many questions I had when I looked at the world. Why? The answer, most of the time, must have been because you wanted to push things into uncomfortable places, just to see what would happen.”

I looked at him. He looked like he was about five seconds away from cutting my head off. There was a full, boiling, barely contained rage in him, all directed against me. “It’s not me,” I said, feeling helpless. “I mean, it’s not — I would never do that, not for real. All the game stuff, it was just a game, it wasn’t real, and I’m just as horrified as you at all of it.”

“No,” said Uther. His voice was quiet. “No, you don’t feel the same depth of horror. There’s a part of you that delights in all this, seeing your creations come to life, a world that matches your aesthetic completely.”

“Fine,” I said, feeling defeated. “That’s true. Maybe for me that takes the edge off the horror of being here, of seeing fucked up things come to life. Maybe it takes my mind off a trillion people being tortured forever, or the horribly unjust societies, or the forms of torture, devastation, and cruelty that aren’t even possible on Earth. Fuck, I’m going to take comfort and joy where I can, even if it’s this.”

“It’s narcissism,” said Uther.

I gave a helpless shrug. “I don’t know what you want me to say. Maybe I would feel the same way about Aerb after being there for a few decades, but yeah, the whole world was more or less made with my sensibilities, and I like it. Aerb appeals to me.”

“And the idea of a man endlessly trapped in a narrative, unable to escape?” he asked. “Does that appeal to you too?”

I wanted to say no, but I didn’t want to lie. “It does,” I said. “It’s compelling. I’d never do it to someone, but it’s a story I’d read, a movie I’d watch, something like that. Sure.”

For a second I thought he was going to go for his sword. I’d have understood if he did. His life hadn’t been a living hell, and I didn’t think he’d have said it was, but he was tired of it all, stressed out and broken, and he wanted to go home, or at least to have it all end. To know that some small part of me took some interest in taking absurd things to their logical conclusions … it might have pissed me off too. He didn’t go for his sword though. Instead, he just turned and walked.

We followed him, as we’d been doing.

“He’s not going back,” said Raven. “He’s not returning to Aerb.”

“We don’t need him to,” said Amaryllis. “We only need the narrative to guide us to whatever will allow Juniper to ascend to godhood. We need to get to the end of things.”

“You still believe in all that shit?” asked Fenn. “Even after seeing the man himself?”

Amaryllis nodded.

“I think I might be the next one out,” said Fenn. “I feel like I need to stay though. Uther looked like he was ready to kill someone, and I’m the only one of us strong enough to beat him.”

“You wouldn’t be able to beat him,” said Raven.

I stayed quiet. My eyes were on the back of Uther’s head, and I was thinking about what he’d said, and what the Dungeon Master had said. ‘Kindred spirits’. I’d have never done any of this to Arthur, but if I were playing with paper dolls, or writing some bit of worldbuilding, or something like that, I definitely might have come up with it. Not for real, no, but if my conception of what I was doing was that it didn’t actually matter … maybe. And if that was true for me, then maybe it was true for the Dungeon Master. I didn’t know if that meant anything. It certainly didn’t shake my confidence in the nature of reality, not that I was particularly attached to any given theory about How The World Really Is.

“Let’s just go,” I said. “See this thing through.” I looked at Raven. “You’re not going to be able to make it to the top.”

“I have to try,” said Raven. “Even if there’s no convincing him to stay, I have to try to follow.”

“I can take Bethel with me if I stay here,” said Fenn. “Also the toad, if you want.”

“Bethel wants to go to the top,” I said. “There’s some risk in that, but the thing that allows her to be this size is the Anyblade, and I’m pretty sure that one can make it all the way to Earth if need be.” Bethel had always claimed to be able to go no smaller than a large staff with a house as part of it, but I had always been skeptical about that. That she was the size of a ring, one with a tiny house on it, seemed like proof she’d lied, early on in her relationship with us. That wasn’t a huge shock.

“How could you know that the Anyblade can make it up?” asked Fenn.

“Because the Anyblade was from the Long Stairs campaign,” I said.

“Ah,” said Fenn. She looked ahead. “Landings are the safest place to be, right? This is probably a good one to camp out at, if I’m out?” It was the second time she’d asked.

“The next one is more hostile, or at least less friendly,” I said.

“It’s a bummer, because I really wanted to see Earth, but I also don’t want to die,” said Fenn. She held up two hands, like she was weighing options. “Well, after you’re god, you can recreate Earth for me, or give me a magical ticket or something, right?” she asked.

“I guess,” I replied. “With the backpack, you’ve already gotten a good sampling of what Earth has to offer. And I wouldn’t recreate people from Earth, so you’d have a bunch of actors.”

“Earth enthusiasts acting out a little mundane play for me?” asked Fenn.

“Eh,” I said. “Non-sentient processes.” I looked ahead to Uther. He was walking some distance ahead of us. “I get the sense he’s not going to be a part of any new world, not even if it’s clear that there won’t be any narrative.” It was sinking in that there might not be anything to do with Arthur, that he’d been too deeply scarred by the world of Aerb and its endless narratives to ever return. There was a chance that our entire trip through the Long Stairs was nothing more than an opportunity for me to say goodbye. It was painful to contemplate. I wanted my friend back, and to the extent he was still there somewhere, we might be only a few days away from him disappearing entirely, beyond my ability to talk to him yet again. He was being an asshole, but I understood it, and beneath it, there was an old friend.

Our crystals led us to a checkpoint, and Uther spoke to the guards there, presumably telling them something about the fight at the tree farm. These people were pretty clearly Conguine, and they let us pass into their territory. The checkpoint was made primarily of wood, and was halfway down a long, straight hallway. Aside from the door and walls, there was a simple framework that went some fifteen feet into the air, where archers were sitting. Fenn gave them a skeptical look, but didn’t boast. I was sure she was thinking of how easy it would have been to snip their bowstrings with a few well-placed arrows, or something equally ridiculous. It wasn’t necessary, because they let us through.

Conguine territory was different from the other parts of the maze we’d seen. It had more plant life, for one thing, though there was a distinct lack of dirt, and most of the plants seemed to be hydroponic, grown in what looked like wooden bowls. Some of it was decorative, but we didn’t need to get too far until we were pretty firmly in agricultural territory, where the vegetation was fairly densely packed. Doing agriculture in twenty foot strips wasn’t quite as crazy as it first sounded, since medieval farmers had used sixty-six foot strips called selions, and crops were planted in rows, but I wouldn’t have wanted to be a yeoman in this kind of environment. There were all kinds of interesting challenges that anyone living in the maze would have to overcome, but very little of the solutions could be seen from a quick glance at the crops. Most of what they were growing seemed to be some kind of lettuce, but there were herbs mixed in too, a few tomato plants, and in one case, bamboo, which I hadn’t even known would grow properly in hydroponics.

We slept, as we had a few times now. Uther seemed to see our sleeping as an imposition, and every time I woke up, the first thing I did was to see whether he was still with us. If he’d wanted to, his best bet would have been to put the amulet of non-detection back on, but he hadn’t done that when he had it. My guess was that while he didn’t particularly want to travel with us, he could see the shape of the narrative, and thought that if he left us behind, he would see us again somehow anyway. Perhaps he would get stuck in a trap, a real one this time.

The first time, back in the rooms, I was pretty sure Raven had taken the opportunity for an extended conversation with him, but I hadn’t been privy to what they said, only to Raven’s eyes, which were red from crying.

This time when I woke up, Fenn was sitting next to Uther, both of them against a wall, speaking to him in hushed tones. Raven was with Amaryllis some ways away, deep in private conversation. We weren’t sleeping very long, and I felt like it had been less than six hours. When I got to my feet, Fenn stood up and came over to me.

“Hey,” she said.

“How’s Uther?” I asked.

“Do you mind if I fuck him?” she asked.

I stared at her. She had a faint smile on her face, like it was a joke, but she often had that look, and often used jokes to cover up her true feelings. “Fenn, you’re your own person. We broke up. It’s none of my business.”

“You’re not even a little jealous?” she asked.

“I’m weirded out,” I said. “But I’ve really been trying to reorient how I think about sex, and — if there were any jealousy, I would be over it in a heartbeat.” I hoped that was true. It felt true.

Fenn turned away, frowning. “I kind of wanted you to be jealous.”

“That would be pretty toxic of me,” I replied, frowning.

“Yeah, well,” she said. She turned back. “I was never going to.”

“No?” I asked.

“I mean, I get why Raven swoons over him,” said Fenn. “But nah, he would be one of those bad decisions that I try not to make anymore.”

“So you asked if I would mind because you were hoping for drama?” I asked. “Because we’ve got a lot on our plate, and I’m kind of trusting you to pull your weight.” I tried to say that as nicely as I could.

“Alright,” said Fenn. “Can I be upfront?”

“Sure,” I said.

“I’m getting real frickin’ nervous about this whole thing,” she said. “I want to see Earth, I do, but I also don’t want to die horribly, especially not if it’s just because I’m in the way of the narrative.”

“Okay,” I said slowly.

“Val’s gone, Grak’s gone, Bethel’s fading away,” said Fenn. She looked down at the toad, which was chasing a bug near my feet. “The locus is … I don’t even know.” She looked back up at me. “That’s half the cast, so to speak. And seeing Uther, hearing him, I’m convinced that I’m not in this for the long haul, whether I like that or not.”

“I’m not sure what this has to do with you fucking him, to be honest,” I said.

“I was never going to do that,” said Fenn. “I mean, part of me wants to see whether he’s worth the fuss, but another part of me — this is pathetic, I have to warn you.”

“Consider me duly warned,” I said, nodding.

“I wanted you to put yourself between us and shout, ‘No, that’s my Fenn, and I still care about her’,” said Fenn. She gave me a nervous look.

I hesitated. “Ah.”

“Shit, that’s a heart-breaking response to that,” said Fenn. “I mean, I know you’re married and everything, but I wanted something, some, I don’t know, emotion to still be there.”

“I mean,” I said. “There is. But it’s so grossly, indecently immature for me to treat you like you’re my property.” It was immature of her to want it too, but I kept that thought to myself.

“It’s just what I wanted,” said Fenn, giving a helpless shrug.

“Well, look,” I said, squaring my shoulders. “I care about you deeply. I’m incredibly happy to have you back. But if you sleep with Uther, I’ll kill him, then you, then myself.” I kept my expression as serious as I could.

“Way too far,” said Fenn. She gave me a smile. “But I appreciate the effort.”

“What were the two of you talking about?” I asked.

“Flesh.txt,” said Fenn with a grin. “Sorry.”

When we got on our way, I thought about what Uther had said the day before.

He was right, of course, I did love Aerb, even if you included the Long Stairs. That was part of why I never wanted to return to Earth. I wanted to ask how you could fail to love a place like this maze, with its cramped quarters, strip farming, and built up ‘city’ blocks where everything was vertical by necessity. The inspirations were obvious to me, since there really were buildings that were as thin as twenty feet, though usually spite houses rather than fully practical homes. Here, that was every building. In some of the places that we passed through or by, we were reduced to a little more than three feet of corridor, with the rest of the space of the hallway given over to buildings of one kind or another, some of them with proper doors. The materials limitations meant that the walls were pretty thin, sometimes nothing more than paper, and my guess was that the better living arrangements were up high, accessed by periodic steep staircases or ladders. Better to live where people didn’t need to walk right by your doorway to get to where they needed to go. The best places to live were, naturally, deadends in the maze, but the best place to put a city was at a central junction, so there were some tradeoffs.

I wouldn’t have wanted to live in the maze, not at all, and I wouldn’t have put people in that kind of place, but I loved that I could walk through and see it. My mind immediately dealt with it in the abstract, like it was a math problem to be solved, the equations of society and civilization put into this warped, cramped area, where you only ever got a long sightline when you found a corridor that went for some distance without stopping. The lights never shut off, which was fine for the plants, but not so great for people, and in the places there were structures, there were light shafts that could either deliver light inside or be closed off if someone wanted darkness. There were also some problems with food, which ultimately seemed like they stemmed from a lack of dirt, which in turn came from the fact that when the maze had first begun, it had been barren and sterile. Then people had come, and people had died, and their bodies had decomposed and shriveled up, releasing their bodily materials and moisture into the maze, which eventually accumulated enough that people could start living in the long term.

As we moved through Conguine territory, we got to see some of the processes they used. They had a tool that was something like a squeegee, twenty feet long and pushed by a team of two, who went down an empty corridor. They were gathering up trace stuff that had fallen on the floor, which would then be put into a compost pile and turned into soil. I was fascinated by the whole thing, and wished that I were the omniglot, not that I would have had a chance to stop and ask them questions.

At the same time, I was introspecting on my love for these things, and how it fit in with my role within Aerb, and my relationship with both Arthur and Uther, those two people separated by decades of adventure. I’d never really known why I loved worldbuilding, and had never really thought about it too much. The naive answer was that I liked to distance myself from the world and put things into their ordered, proper place, but I didn’t think that was right, because I really liked messy, complicated worldbuilding that was explicitly not about putting things into order. I liked shades of grey and awkward corner cases. The other naive answer was that it was the same reason other people liked speculative fiction: it was a way of illuminating certain things about the real world that you didn’t normally get to see. I wasn’t really sure though. All I knew was that Aerb hadn’t dampened my enthusiasm at all. If anything, it had heightened it.

In the context of Uther, I could see how that would rankle him, but I wondered if it hadn’t annoyed Arthur too, back when we’d played together. The stuff he’d said about me living in my own little world … it seemed like the kind of thing that might have been at the back of his mind when we were friends. But it wasn’t like the worldbuilding stuff that I loved so much was special and unique in some way. As a hobby, it didn’t seem much different from, say, a love of sudoku puzzles, or a book series no one else is interested in, or some kind of sport. Worldbuilding seemed, to me, inoffensive and a little bit boring as a hobby, at least from an outside perspective. Most of what I did was just reading up on whatever had caught my fancy at the moment.

We’d gone almost a mile before Uther spoke again.

“I think we’re heading toward the capital,” he said. “That’s a problem. Movement will be restricted.”

If you mapped out most mazes, you could divide the area into ‘lobes’, places that could be reached only through specific choke points, which largely branched off from the main path that led from the exit to the entrance. Classical mazes had lots of natural choke points in them, and there were huge benefits to controlling them. If you could control who had access to a whole area of the maze, you could very easily mount a defense, or alternately, tax whoever wanted to go through. I tried to imagine how it would be on Earth, if getting from France to Germany was only possible by moving through a twenty-foot wide doorway. One side would naturally end up controlling it, or at least with majority control, and they would place a heavy tax on everything coming through. The maze had that, replicated hundreds or maybe thousands of times.

We came to this choke point pretty quickly, guided through the twists and turns by our crystals. I was a little surprised that no one questioned or stopped us, but within the walls of this civilization, my guess was that they weren’t too worried about intruders, even armed ones. Once we’d gotten past the perimeter defenses, we were more or less free to roam, at least until we got to the next internal choke point.

The lines formed by the walls weren’t all entirely straight within the Landing, but they were all regular and geometric, with the odd curved wall being a mathematically perfect curve, at least to my untrained eye. Most of the junctions were T-junctions, but there were a few angled turns as well. The internal choke point, which seemed to be near the center of the city, was a rare five-way junction. All we could see of it was a large building and a fortified entrance. Curiously, it was the first structure we’d seen that was made of stone. It seemed to be the same material that the maze walls were made of, except that there shouldn’t have been a way to damage the walls. It was anyone’s guess where the material had come from though, if not the walls. It wasn’t like you could have a quarry in the maze.

“Two options,” said Uther. “The first is that we go through at speed, killing anyone who stands in our way.”

“They’re innocent, Uther,” said Raven. “They’re a foreign government, but they’ve done nothing wrong unless you count controlling their own borders.”

“Can any of you fly?” asked Uther, looking between us, ignoring Raven.

“Can you?” I asked.

By way of answer, he briefly hovered off the ground. “What’s the least complicated and awkward way for me to take you past all this?” he asked.

“Sable,” said Amaryllis, holding up her glove. “It still works, thankfully. We have oxygen tanks and masks that will allow us to spend some amount of time in the void.”

“Fucking seriously?” asked Fenn. “All this time, all this power, and we’re going back in the fucking glove again? I hate going in the glove. I’ve sworn off going in the glove.”

Amaryllis had already begun popping out tanks of air and breathing equipment for us, and when she handed one to Fenn, she took it with a grumble.

“Thank you,” I said. “For taking us.”

He raised an eyebrow. “Why wouldn’t I?”

“I don’t know,” I said. “We’re an imposition on your ability to move quickly. We keep bothering you. You think that I’m the guy who imprisoned you here, or maybe an avatar of him, or something.”

He nodded. “I’ve considered it. But I can see that the narrative is in full effect, and having you all with me is a part of what will allow my escape, to make this a narrative of my removal from Aerb. If I shook you off, you would find me again, as improbable as it might be. You’ll be with me until you’ve served your narrative purpose, whatever that might be, and then you will drop off. The dwarf was there to tempt me with new systems to explore and fields to master, but I proved that I wouldn’t be swayed, and now he’s gone, never to be seen again.”

It kind of made sense, in a twisted sort of way, but I didn’t think it was really true. I glanced at Amaryllis, who seemed about as convinced of narrative control over everything as he did, but she was thin-lipped, and beyond that, putting on her tank and mask.

“You remember how the glove works?” she asked, holding out Sable to him.

He nodded, taking it from her. “It was a trifle, when I had it. It’s no doubt grown enormously in power. Another temptation, fruit borne of the tree of time.”

“Grown?” I asked.

“The extradimensional space is finite,” said Amaryllis. “But it grows if the glove isn’t used. The gain is exponential over time. If left alone for hundreds of years, which it was, the total available space would be enough to hold a city, if done in small pieces.” She’d gotten the information from Grak, I was pretty sure, and I’d never been told about it, because it was a curiosity, nothing more.

“Gain over time is a rare effect,” said Uther, nodding. “Exponential gain over time even more so. I was unfortunately never able to find anything to speed it along. As it turns out, it was simply waiting to be tucked away somewhere for a few hundred years, setting up exactly this scenario.”

The scary thing was, there was a good chance he was right, and if he wasn’t, then it had been placed there for me instead. It was just barely possible that this was a happy coincidence from the Dungeon Master’s perspective, but more likely it was just a matter of planning things out with absolute foresight.

We went into the glove, for what I was hoping was the last time. It had been a hot minute, and I’d forgotten how much I disliked it, especially the feeling of helplessness and ignorance of what was going on in the outside world. There were other physical sensations that I didn’t enjoy, but it was mostly the psychological stuff that got to me. That it was Uther on the other end, with our lives in his hand, made the whole thing more nerve-wracking. I didn’t think he was insane, per se, but he was operating under a model of the world that could give wild results to inputs.

Either way, we popped back out of the glove after another five minutes. We were in another part of the maze, far beyond the castle, but apparently still in Conguine territory, because there were people in the corridor both ahead of and behind us. Some of them were giving us looks, perhaps because of the raw magic on display, whether that was Uther flying through the air or us suddenly materializing.

“They didn’t appreciate that,” said Uther. “But I think I made it clear that there was nothing to be gained from following me, and that they were clearly outclassed when it came to combat.” Once he’d looked to see that we were all fine, he resumed walking.

“How much more of this to go?” asked Fenn. “I’m not taking a liking to this maze.”

“Could be as much as a week,” I said.

“Two or three more civilizations,” guessed Amaryllis.

“Less than that,” said Uther. “Someone has been digging tunnels through the walls.”

We found the source of the bricks not long afterward. There was, in fact, a tunnel going through one of the walls, one that had been carved out by someone who had clearly had some difficulty, or perhaps just enjoyed making tunnels that were cramped. Uther and I were tall enough that we had to stoop, but even for the others, it had to have been a bit claustrophobic.

“It undermines the entire idea of the maze,” I said. “If you can just make a path from point A to point B, why even have a maze?”

“A disruption to your precious setting?” asked Uther.

“No,” I said, “I just don’t understand why it was allowed. There are all kinds of things prohibited in one way or another on Aerb, most notably through exclusion, but also a few other ways. Why include something that would subvert the central conceit?”

“You’d have allowed it,” said Uther. “So long as it was a player who did it.”

That gave me pause. “I mean,” I said, trying to think that through.

“You always did,” said Uther. “You loved breaking the rules almost as much as Reimer did, just in a different way. You liked to set up your wooden blocks and then watch as they got knocked into disarray. ‘Blowing up the world’, you called it. I very specifically remember that conversation.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I think I do too.” I frowned. “That still doesn’t explain this,” I continued, gesturing to the holes running through the walls. “I mean, it’s fine if the players blow up the world, but if the players come to a world that’s already been blown up, that feels like a missed opportunity in a way that I’m not sure I’ve seen much of on Aerb. Or, I guess you blew up the world, or some local portions of it, and I’ve been spending the last half a year wandering through the proverbial wreckage.”

“And it appeals to you, to do that,” said Uther. He nodded at another of the holes in the wall, which was our destination. “The entire world appeals to your interest.”

“I guess,” I said. “You have to know that I wouldn’t have done this to you.”

“Perhaps,” he said. He ducked down to go through the tunnel. No one had stopped us from using the tunnels yet, and we hadn’t met anyone going the other way. Because of the variable space between corridors, some of the walls were hundreds of feet thick and others were only a handbreadth. I wondered how they’d decided where to put the tunnels, but my guess was that they’d mapped things out and made strategic decisions.

“These cuts,” said Amaryllis, touching the wall as we passed through. “They used void tools.”

My frown deepened. “How do you know?”

“Cut depth is low,” said Amaryllis, pulling her fingers back from the wall. “It’s also one of the only things that would get you through something inviolable.”

The closer I looked at the marks on the wall, the more I thought she was right, though it was never much of a surprise when Amaryllis was right.

“How?” I asked. “And why?”

“That was my doing,” said Uther, not looking back at us. “The second time I came through, I brought an immense amount of void crystals, along with the equipment to make them work.”

“They need an electrical charge,” I said.

“Leyden jars,” replied Uther. “I had been hoping that if I ever returned, they would have punched a few holes for me. It seems that was a case of good planning.”

“When did you learn about void crystals?” asked Raven. “Their discovery post-dates you leaving Aerb. I suppose it’s no surprise that you would be keeping secrets though.”

“It was not long after the Wandering Blight,” said Uther, ignoring the bitterness in her voice. “There was a rogue group who had harnessed my early experiments with electricity to excite the crystals, though of course it would also have been possible for a vitric, or other means. You were asleep for it, if I recall, and we didn’t want the power spreading any, given the difficulty in defending against it, and its utility as a surprise weapon.”

“It’s causing problems on Aerb,” replied Raven. “Introducing it here, where it’s been used for five hundred years, likely exacerbated that problem immensely.”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “You’re not doing the math properly. Anything going on here is dwarfed in comparison to true industrial uses. In the heyday of void tool usage, whole tonnes of material were being removed every day. A civilization here using hand-powered void tools would be a drop in the bucket.”

“But we should stop them, right?” asked Fenn. “I mean, void stuff is mostly shut down on Aerb.”

“None of it matters,” said Amaryllis. “This will all be over before any of that would be relevant.”

With this section of the maze having a significant number of shortcuts, we were making much faster progress, with no need to double back. No one was trying to stop us, either because we were in places where they assumed we were supposed to be, or because we were clearly heavily armed. It was still another day’s worth of travel to get to the exit, but that was a far better time than we’d expected to make.

There was, naturally, a part of me that felt like we’d given the maze short shrift. There was so much we hadn’t seen, and I was sure that we had missed out on a civilization or two that had their own take on organizing society within the confines of the maze. There was so much more to look at, like what was causing a slight breeze through the maze, something I hadn’t designed in, or how they dealt with water, which should have been pretty hard given there were no rivers or lakes. Obviously figuring that stuff wasn’t high on the list of priorities, and arguably, wasn’t on the list of priorities at all, but leaving it all behind left me with a bad taste in my mouth.

I wondered what that said about me, and whether Uther was right.

Long Memory

We were back in the rooms, taking them one at a time, and following through the RDP as much as we were able to. During the time we’d been in the Landing, both books had gone through unrecoverable rot, and consisted of the same word, over and over. The copies had likewise rotted, and I counted myself lucky that the same wasn’t true for our heads. Almost every book we had in Sable was unusable, which meant that it had got its hooks in pretty deep, and Amaryllis spent nearly twenty minutes rapidly dumping an immense quantity of books into a room that had a horse-sized duck in a cage in the middle of it. (We stood well clear of the duck, and hoped that it would enjoy literally thousands of books which mostly contained the same word repeated over and over.) Raven’s book entad was toast as well, and she took quite a while to clear it, hoping that would fix the issue and allow new books to be added.

“Time and resources wasted,” said Amaryllis once it was all done. She sighed.

“Better to have it and not need it,” I said.

“Yes?” she asked, raising an eyebrow. “And?”

I looked at her. “Uh,” I said. Uther chuckled. “The full expression is ‘better to have it and not need it than to need it and not have it.’ It was a favorite of my dad’s. Sorry.”

“You should have claimed it,” said Uther. “That’s what I always did, as I’m sure you’ve figured out. I can only be thankful that before I came to Aerb, I studied the greats and learned more than my fair share of quotes. There were times I wondered whether I was meant to come to Aerb, or a place like it. I credit our games for a lot of things I had learned.”

The earlier animosity seemed to have left him, but that was putting me on edge, because we hadn’t actually resolved anything, and from where I was sitting, probably couldn’t ever resolve it. Growing up, there had been a lot of fights like that between my mom and dad, arguments that couldn’t ever be ‘finished’, so the only resolution they’d get is the catharsis of yelling at each other, which obviously sucked and wasn’t a long-term solution.

Raven got sick not too long after. I’d worried that she was just going to die, or possibly explode, but instead she passed through another door of the Long Stairs and doubled over in pain, clutching her chest and stomach.

“Well, that’s it for you,” said Fenn with a sigh. “Come on, I’ll guide you back to the maze Landing and we’ll wait it out.” The way she said it, it was like she’d been waiting for some excuse to fuck off and not be with us anymore. After everything she’d said, I was surprised that she’d kept going after we were done with the labyrinth Landing.

“No,” said Raven. “Give me a second, I’ll be fine.” She was panting hard. The Ell had massive internal extradimensional space as one way of allowing for their ridiculous conceit, and I had no idea what was physically happening to her, only that it couldn’t have been good.

Uther knelt down next to her. “It’s your time to go,” he said. “I’ve appreciated seeing you one last time, but if you go further, you will die. There were always parts of my adventures you couldn’t go on, places you couldn’t travel, things you couldn’t be allowed to see. We must all accept our lot in life.” I don’t know if he’d intended it to be cruel, but that was how it came out to me.

“Please,” she said. “Just give me a minute, I’ll be okay, I’ll come with you.”

“Come on,” said Fenn, lifting her up like she weighed next to nothing. “I’ll take you back to the Landing, we’ll chill out with the maze people, and we can grab a pint while we wait for this whole thing to blow over.”

“I’ll be fine,” said Raven through gritted teeth.

“It’ll be good for us to have some time together,” Fenn insisted. “Hey, you haven’t heard any of my best jokes or most delightful anecdotes yet, so that’s something. And I should also point out that I’m giving up going to Earth for you, which I don’t think you should turn your nose up at.”

“Please,” said Raven, looking at Uther. “I went through so much trying to find you, and then trying to continue your work. It can’t all be for nothing. You can’t just abandon Aerb. You can’t just abandon me, please Uther, I know somewhere in there is —” she winced. “I know you care about me.”

“I do,” said Uther. “But all the same, I’m continuing on.” His voice was steady and calm. “You’ll have to make peace with that. It’s something that I can’t help you with. I hope you understand.”

He set off, and I fought my instinct to follow him, instead turning to Raven, even as Uther went through the next door.

“Fenn will take care of you,” I said to Raven. I looked up at Fenn. “Thank you.”

“No problem, hoss,” replied Fenn. “I’m just hoping that any of this is worth it, plus I'm a little scared that I might be reduced down to normal any day now.” She shrugged. “Earth probably sucked anyway. I’ll take care of the little Ell, you go.” She looked at the ring on my finger. “You need me to take Bethel too, or?”

“She wanted to go all the way to the top,” I said.

Fenn looked at the toad that was sitting on my shoulder.

“He’s staying with me too,” I said. I had no idea whether that was the right call.

“Fine, fine,” Fenn replied. “Welp, smell you later.” She turned to leave, carrying Raven, before pausing. “Wait, I never got a chance to use it, but ‘more like schlong stairs’ was waiting for the right opportunity.”

“I’m glad we got you back,” I said to her. “Even if it was only for a bit.”

“Sure, sure,” Fenn replied. “I love you too, but I’m leaving, don’t make me white fang you.”

I wanted to ask what she meant, but she left, carrying Raven, and when the door shut, for just a moment, I was all alone. I had the crystals though, and they honed in on Uther just fine, so it was only a matter of following the steps the crystal told me to take.

When I caught back up to Uther and Amaryllis, they were in the middle of an argument, one carried on as they walked.

“Because it doesn’t map,” said Amaryllis. She sounded frustrated, but only in the way that she sometimes let a note of frustration creep into her voice as a conversational tactic. “If you’re attempting to apply a framework to reality and find that some parts fit but others don’t, it’s a sign that something is fundamentally wrong with the framework. Fenn doesn’t fit. I don’t fit.”

“Hey,” I said. They both ignored me.

“You’re accusing me of trying to fit round pegs into square holes?” asked Uther.

“I am,” replied Amaryllis. “I fundamentally agree with you about the narrative, but I think there are too many things missing from your model. You’re inventing epicycles to explain how and why your model works. In my view, the narrative hypothesis works in several naive cases, but you never tempered it with the understanding of the narrator and what he wants. Now, you’re stuck in the trap of hammering everything into a theory that only almost works, which has unfortunately reinforced itself through your actions.”

“In which way?” he asked, seeming more bored than curious.

“Oh come on now,” she said. “I’ve read through what transcripts we have, I know you’re better at argumentation than this. Invest something in the conversation.”

“I don’t see the point of it, dear daughter,” said Uther. He glanced at her. “Or whomever you’re supposed to be.”

“You can think of me as Dahlia, if you’d like,” said Amaryllis. “It doesn’t bother me in the slightest, so long as you actually engage with the conversation I’m trying to have.”

“Very well,” replied Uther. “Your argument is that we have more free will than it would first seem, and aberrations within the narrative are both possible and expected given some willful deviance on the part of the protagonist. Is it that you think I don’t have an enormous amount of experience, or that you have some new evidence to bring to the table? Are there avenues for non-compliance that you think I haven’t tried?”

“Let’s back up slightly, if you’ve decided to take this conversation seriously,” said Amaryllis. “Juniper argues in favor of narrative, but the type of narrative he argues in favor of is collaborative, that of a Dungeon Master and his players. This means that the Dungeon Master is, yes, in charge of the narrative, has full knowledge of almost everything that the players do, is able to retroactively insert people, places, and ideas into reality, and to adapt to the choices of the players. There are fundamental differences from traditional narratives though.”

“Hang on,” I said. “I actually preach something very different, which is that it doesn’t actually matter what’s going on at a higher level, since we have very little ability to change or challenge it.”

“Either way,” said Amaryllis. “If you walk the straight and narrow, doing what you think needs to be done, playing everything as a narrative, the result is going to be that you don’t see the seams in the narrative, or the places where there are dropped threads, pieces that are quietly written away. You spent too much of your time following the narrative path in front of you without blowing things to hell.”

“And you think your presence here is because of something like that?” asked Uther. “You think that there were some significant deviations from what the Dungeon Master, if we’re using that moniker, had planned?”

“I think that it was planned that we would be here, absolutely,” said Amaryllis. “I think that the specifics were largely left to us. It was all within the Dungeon Master’s control, ultimately, but I see a preference for not interfering, and your hypothesis that we’re all here with specific hooks to dig into you to get you to come back seems far too specific given our actual goals and personalities. I don’t give a bubbling shit if you go to Earth. Personally, I don’t want you to come back, nor am I equipped to tug at your heartstrings as I might be if I were Dahlia, even if I have done a fair amount of research into her. Fenn’s role within our group was largely as comic relief and as a love interest —”

“She was more than that,” I said.

“I’m talking about narrative purpose,” said Amaryllis. She seemed slightly exasperated by my interjection, and I didn’t think that was a conversational tactic. “Her role was also to die and provide grief for Juniper to work through. She allowed him to grapple with loss in a similar way to how he grappled with the loss of you. Fenn being here fundamentally wasn’t about you, it was about Juniper, which is why she doesn’t fit. And still, you’re trying to hammer her into your narrative.”

“But you’re admitting that you think the others do fit,” said Uther. “Raven, Grakhuil? Even Bethel?” He didn’t mention the toad, which I was a little put out by. It seemed like bad manners.

“I don’t know,” said Amaryllis. “It’s incredibly difficult to say, because we don’t know where the camera, so to speak, is pointing.”

“Camera?” asked Uther. “Such a strange term to hear. The hardest thing about Juniper suddenly appearing is hearing all of these ideas and terminology from Earth.”

“It’s a term from Aerb as well,” said Amaryllis. “We have movies and television, though more the latter than the former. I run the television network and star in a few of them.”

“Ah, well,” said Uther. He seemed like he wanted to ask more, and I wondered whether Amaryllis had been trying to bait him. “And in the end, you think that it will just be me and Juniper?”

“Yes,” said Amaryllis. “But all the same, I’ll hang on for as long as I can, and either I’ll die or be blown into the winds.”

“I don’t think I can stop myself from thinking of you as Dahlia,” said Uther. “Even if I have no intention of following that thread, it’s good to see her face. You share much of her same fierceness.”

“You left your kids,” I said.

“They were all adults,” Uther replied. “No, the only note of regret is that my grandchildren are all long dead.” He looked at me. “How many good years did my wife have left?”

“Four,” said Amaryllis, which I was thankful for, because I hadn’t paid as much attention to the exact dates.

“More than we expected,” said Uther with a nod. For a moment, I saw real regret from him. “But of course, I knew when I went forward in time that I would be leaving them behind, just as I would be if I made it down the Long Stairs.” He paused in the middle of the room we were in. “We need to eat some of this?”

I looked at the food on the table. Everything there was completely desiccated, and the room was incredibly dry. Laying on the ground was another member of some lost fireteam, and he was dried out too, a complete husk of a person.

“It’s RDP,” I said. “So yes, we need to eat a little bit. It’s never actually poisonous, or wasn’t in the games I ran. Except one time, I guess, when it killed the party. Also, Bethel identified some poison in an earlier buffet room.” I glanced at Uther. “The ‘kill everyone’ stuff was after your time.”

“What happened here?” asked Amaryllis, looking down at the body on the floor. She stooped to get a better look at it. “The room should have been frozen in time when he died, so that we would come across a fresh corpse, right?”

“It doesn’t matter,” said Uther, picking up a leathery piece of pear and eating it.

“It might,” said Amaryllis, standing up. “You’re running out of magic. We’ll need to be more careful going forward.”

“He might still be alive,” I said, looking at the corpse. “Or he was able to live long enough for this place to dry out.” I looked around. “It’s not really clear to me where the moisture would have gone through.”

“Lived long enough?” asked Amaryllis.

“Monkey’s paw immortality,” I said. “It’s one of the things on offer in the Long Stairs, if you’re willing to search for it. Immortality without health, basically. The high end stuff is pretty high end.”

“Ah,” said Amaryllis, looking at the corpse. “So you think that maybe he made it to this room, then lay face down and just continually died until the magic gave out?”

“He might still be alive, actually,” I said. “Or alive in some technical sense, capable of thinking but not movement, speech, or sensation. Just trapped in his own head for five hundred years.”

Uther stepped forward and stomped on the skull with enough force to send bits of bone flying. “Well, hopefully that will kill him,” he said. There was a solemnity to his voice that was incongruent with the sounds of crunched bone that still seemed to echo in the room. He looked over at me. “Always thinking up some new torture, aren’t you?”

“Yes,” I said. “But that’s not a particularly new one. I’m more wondering why everything is so dry here. There should have been a lot of water in both the food and the guy.”

“Magic of some kind,” said Uther. “We should be going, if we’ve done our due diligence.”

I picked up what looked like a dried plum and ate it without comment. The requirement to partake of food, even just a little bit, probably did get people killed every once in a while. Amaryllis took something unidentifiable that seemed crunchy, which was probably a better idea. The plum was too leathery. I fed the toad a tiny bit of apricot.

The Long Stairs were full of mysteries, even for me. When I’d been designing the place, I’d wanted it to have a feeling like there was always another thing to look out for, another RDP or LSP or another of the acronyms that we mostly stopped using after the first few sessions. Since I hadn’t actually prepared a full list, the real Long Stairs had a lot of things that I had no clue about, and even the books we’d found, not that I’d had the time to read all of them, didn’t give full, clear descriptions of things.

We went through a room with reversed gravity and had to crawl our way along the ceiling. We went through a room filled with nitrogen gas rather than normal air, and nearly died before we noticed. We fought a pile of clothes that tried to smother us, then right after that, a bear the size of a van that was immune to blades. We came across a dance troupe, whose performance we had to sit through as part of RDP, then passed by a man selling wares which were piled high on his back. We went through a jungle that only lasted twenty feet, and a desert that turned out to be made entirely of sand golems.

We talked in fits and starts, when we weren’t discussing the matters at hand.

“What do you miss most about Earth?” I asked Uther.

“The internet,” he replied. “Or perhaps the subset of the internet that allowed us to instantly access information. It took me a good decade to unlearn my understanding of knowledge as something that’s constantly at my fingertips. Even if much of what was on the internet was wrong or biased, the wealth of information meant that it was easy to interrogate sources.”

“You could have built the internet on Aerb,” said Amaryllis. “I have plans to, actually, if this doesn’t pan out. Making computers will be a good first step.”

“And perhaps in another few decades, you’ll have something like Earth has,” said Uther. “That’s not a roaring endorsement of Aerb.”

“You could skip your way through those years with the bobbler, if you really wanted to,” said Amaryllis. “Like I said, I have no strong feelings about your return to Aerb one way or another. I want Juniper to get from this what he needs to. I want the Dungeon Master to complete his narrative, and I can see clearly that this is where it comes to a finish. Whether that sees you on Earth or Aerb at the end of it, or even alive or dead, doesn’t matter to me.”

“From what you’ve said, I’m your world-renowned ancestor,” he said. “I had, perhaps, hoped that if people thought of me five hundred years down the line, it would be with a bit more respect.”

“People do,” said Amaryllis. “I don’t. With all the enormous advantages in your favor, most people would have done worse, but that doesn’t absolve you of your failures. I’m sure you would see my giving a history lesson as an enticement of the Dungeon Master’s, and I don’t think it would accomplish anything anyway, but some very bad things were the result of your reign in ways that I think, as a scholar of Earth, you could have anticipated.”

“A scholar of Earth?” asked Uther. “I was a teenager when I was put here. I was smarter than average, with more interest in history, society, law, and governance than almost anyone my age, or at least in my high school, but I was still a teenager. I hadn’t even finished high school, let alone undergrad. It’s that life I was robbed of to play these extended games on Aerb.”

I didn’t pipe up to say that actually, he had died. From his perspective, that wasn’t true, and all it might have done was to clarify where I was coming from, at least emotionally. Arthur dying was, I thought, probably close to the truth, even if it might not have been literally true. Aerb was a resurrection, but he was right, it was a resurrection that he had never asked for, and one that came with strings attached. If he wanted to escape it, I didn’t blame him.

There was a fair amount of silence as we made our way through the rooms, and I had a chance to get my thoughts in order. Eventually, when we were taking a rest and eating fairies to recover from some fresh wounds inflicted by opposite-wolves (like wolves, but the opposite), I went over to Uther.

“When you died, I mourned you,” I said. “You were such a constant presence in my life, my best friend, and it was like someone had yanked you out of reality and pulled a bunch of wires out of my head in the process. I felt numb to the world, like this was the betrayal that I had always seen coming, and nothing much worse could happen. I was a shit to everyone, above and beyond all the ways I was a shit to everyone even before it had happened. I was lashing out. It wasn’t very healthy. I pushed people away, which made everything worse. I dated Maddie for like, a week, and then I hit rock bottom and tried to kill myself. Not too long afterward, I was on Aerb.”

Uther stared at me for a moment. “I’m sorry you went through that,” he finally said.

“Maybe I kept to myself too much when we were friends,” I said. “Look, if your grand ambition is to return to Earth, to return to the summer after your junior year, then maybe there’s a chance you get what you want. If I’m there, I’m hoping that knowing more about me helps you in some way, if you’re allowed to remember any of this.”

He was silent for a moment, then nodded. “Going back to high school with no memories of Aerb is one of the worst possibilities,” he said. “But it’s one that I am prepared to accept. If the government organization up top is the same as what you designed, they’ll have powerful amnestics. And of course, aging backward is something that I’m prepared for as well.”

“Prepared for how?” I asked, watching him.

“This,” he said, holding out a hand to allow a vial to appear from nowhere and land in his outstretched fingers. “I should have taken it out before, but I’ve been worried about how much power I’ll lose in the process.” He looked up at me. “I may need your protection during the ascent.”

“You’ll have it,” I said. I wondered if that was why he’d allowed me to come this far with him, but there were probably multiple reasons.

“Then I suppose, if the vial still works, there’s no use in waiting.” He popped the cork from the top, and it fizzed up like a can of soda. Before I could say anything more, he downed it, all in one go.

“What, uh, what was that?” I asked.

“Age reversing serum,” he said. “It won’t be exact, but it will be close enough. I couldn’t bring myself to do a full course of testing, so it’s only approximate, but it should bring me back to how I looked at sixteen, if it works at all. And if it doesn’t, so be it.”

“You’ll still die young,” I said, watching him. “I mean, relatively young. If this all works and you go back to Earth, and they somehow put you back into high school, with all the problems that would have to be solved to make that happen — if that all happens, it seems like your fate is going to be to die of early-onset dementia.”

Uther was looking at his hands, and not particularly paying attention to me. “There are three varieties of death by old age, speaking broadly,” he said. “Physical health, mental health, and the health of the soul. They’re related to one another, but I solved all three. If those solutions hold, I’ll be fine, and if not,” he shrugged. “It’s not what I’m most worried about, obviously.”

“Seems like a dick move not to share that with anyone,” I said.

“There were many problems,” said Uther. He was still looking at his hand, which hadn’t changed. “The biggest was that I was the only one with the expertise, and it would take me perhaps two months with unfettered access to someone’s soul. I could have started up a new athenaeum, and perhaps with a team of thirty, it could be done for — well, currency is bound to have changed in five hundred years, but it would suffice to say that it would be a treatment only for the extremely wealthy.”

“But you could have,” I said.

“I was never terribly comfortable as king,” said Uther. “And kings that would live forever would — ah, there it goes.”

The changes were more extensive than I’d been expecting. He was shrinking, both in terms of his height and muscle. His face was getting softer too, especially in the cheeks and eyes. His face hadn’t been very deeply lined, but what wrinkles were there had faded away. I was wondering how and why this was working, especially given that you didn’t just get as tall as Uther because you naturally grew that way, not if you started from where Arthur was at sixteen.

“This is going to make sword-fighting more difficult,” he said. He called forward his sword and got into a fighting stance, making a few tentative swings. He’d used several different swords as we swept through the rooms. This one left a trail of lightning twisting fractal thorns into the air. He looked at me. “Care to spar? Just to see how much skill I’ve retained.”

It was bizarre. He didn’t look like he had in high school, because he wasn’t as pudgy as he’d been then, but it was close. It was like Arthur playing dress up.

“That bad?” he asked.

“Different,” I said.

“Bad,” said Amaryllis, who had been sitting out the conversation. “You look like … limp.”

“Harsh words, but probably fair,” said Arthur. “Still, I wouldn’t mind a test of my abilities.”

I hesitated for a moment, then drew my regular sword, leaving the vorpal blade in its sheath. “Okay,” I said. “What are the rules?”

“I try to hit you, you try to parry,” he replied. “Or you try to hit me, and I try to parry. If the blade goes in, we have healing to spare.”

“Alright,” I said.

For a moment he just stood there, and I wondered whether he’d lost his edge completely, but then he moved, and the tip of his blade was like a viper moving straight to my throat. The only reason he didn’t get me was that he stopped short. He’d bypassed my sword completely, and my reflexes, which were like molasses compared to his, led me to try parrying it away long after I would have been dead. The clink of my sword against his sounded pathetic.

“Is that really the best you can do?” asked Arthur. He was the same person he’d been a few minutes ago, only changed physically, but my brain refused to believe that it wasn’t my high school friend, that he hadn’t somehow undone forty years of change. Body modification wasn’t new to me, but the image of Arthur as a teenager was too powerfully etched in my mind.

“Uh, yeah,” I said. “I got good with a sword, but I was only ever the best swordsman in the world for a single afternoon, and I can’t do that again, because Essentialism is excluded now.”

Arthur sighed. “Well, I’m diminished, but not as much as I might have feared.” He sheathed his sword. “But I may need more help than I’ve needed up to this point.”

“Good, then let’s get going,” said Amaryllis.

We soldiered on through the rooms, none of them particularly noteworthy. We fought monsters, faced down dilemmas, and followed RDP as best we could. We got a few repeat rooms from time to time, or at least rooms that looked like repeats, but that didn’t necessarily mean anything, and I didn’t think the crystals were steering us wrong. The repeated rooms were part of the creepiness of the Long Stairs, especially if you got them when you were going in what you thought was the right ‘direction’.

We were going through a room filled with statues when Arthur decided to speak up again. I didn’t particularly think it was the time for it. The statues seemed like they were guaranteed to come to life, and there were thousands of them, each its own unique work of art, all lined up on plinths. Normally if you had a bunch of statues like this, they’d be copies, churned out by either a factory or journeymen or molds or something, but I couldn’t see any repeats among them. Each looked like it had been done by a master at the height of his abilities. The room was huge, one of the aircraft-hangar ones.

Statues coming to life was one of those tropes that could bend back around on itself. It was cliche, incredibly so, but because it was so cliche, it added an extra sense of foreboding and creepiness to proceedings. You weren’t worried that they would come to life, you were worried about when, and that sense of inevitability turned something cliche into something still worth doing.

“I understand that it took time and effort to get to me,” said Arthur as we walked. “Yet the actual pressures you face aren’t so great. Aerb is not within its final minutes. So why now?”

“We were in cycles of stories,” I said. “They were inflicting harm on people and getting bigger in scope as time went on. Every single time, it felt like we were coming through by the skin of our teeth. The time pressure was low, but we thought we needed to get a move on. And now that rune magic is excluded, there are no spikes, which means that everyone is funneling into the hells.”

“I see,” replied Arthur. “You’re thinking that I will help draw this to a close somehow. You think that if you accomplish your mission, there won’t be one more thing to worry about.” He shook his head.

“That’s the hope,” I said. “That’s … kind of what the Dungeon Master said.”

“Did you revel in it?” he asked. “Playing the hero?”

“I don’t know,” I said. “I guess. Nothing I did was really … I mean, there was a huge kaiju, I guess, but other than that, nothing really heroic.”

“In all that time?” he asked. “I might have understood it better if you had been hiding from the world, like I was, but you came to me with a full complement of companions, and it sounded like you were very busy. But you weren’t busy being a hero?”

“He saved my life on several occasions,” said Amaryllis.

“Mmm,” said Arthur. “One thing I’ll say for my daughter, she was never a damsel in distress.” The voice and tone didn’t match him all that well, given that he looked like he was a teenager on his way to some esoteric Renaissance Festival. “Oh, I don’t put that on you, of course, it’s all the narrative. I rescued plenty of strong women in my time.”

“Gross,” I said.

“Which part?” he asked. “Did you think it better to rescue weak women?”

But I didn’t get a chance to reply, because the stupid statues we’d been walking through had chosen that moment to come to life, and we had a pitched battle with them. They were weirdly slow, moving half the speed of a person, or maybe even less, but they made up for that by being quite heavy and difficult to break. I didn’t spend too much time fighting them, instead opting to slip between them, push off against a leg that was trying to kick me, and get up over their heads. My plan had been to jump across their heads and hope that they weren’t fast enough to grab me, but the plan had a problem, which was that Arthur was in front of me, and he was killing so many of them my choice was between getting back down and taking the long way around.

I looked back toward where Amaryllis had been, and couldn’t see her. I went to where she’d been standing, jumping on heads to do it, and drawing the vorpal blade as I made my way over. I dropped down among the statues, slashing at them, and realizing only after the first few swings that the vorpal blade was cutting through them like they were made out of paper.

I spotted the black glove beneath a broken arm, and picked it up with my free hand while the other was fending off any statue that got too close to me. Once I had the glove, I cut my way through more of the statues, moving back toward Arthur.

“This will take some stamina!” he shouted to me, the only way he could be heard over the sound of marble falling to the ground.

He was right, but this was the first time his stamina was in question. We had gone fairly far into the field of statues, but there was still a long way to go, and they were all around us, closing fast. They didn’t take all that much to kill, but there were thousands of them, and there wasn’t really a way to be leisurely about it, even with their slow movements, because we were entirely surrounded.

Arthur was still a master with a sword, even having been diminished to a teenaged version of himself, but after not too long, it was clear that he wasn’t up for fighting off a thousand of these things. By the time Amaryllis popped back out, gasping for breath, Arthur had slowed down, and our forward progress was almost entirely down to me slicing through marble with the vorpal blade. I was becoming more and more grateful for the weapon. At a certain point, I took the lead and Arthur covered the rear and sides. His swings were getting wilder with every passing minute, and I could tell he was gassed.

It took twenty minutes to get to the door, and by the time we did, I was half-dragging Arthur while Amaryllis did her best to cover our retreat. The vorpal blade continued to slice as cleanly and sharply as when we started, though I hadn’t really expected it to dull. Without it, I was fairly certain that we would have died.

I pushed through the door as quickly as I could and pulled Arthur through, then slammed it shut as soon as Amaryllis had slipped in. Monsters could follow through doors, and if the statues did that, I wasn’t sure what we would do about it. You could eventually outrun things, and they were pretty slow, but that meant barrelling through a lot of rooms without the caution and diligence that the Long Stairs normally required. I waited by the closed door to see whether they would come through, but there was nothing, not even any banging against the door. Out of sight, out of mind, I supposed.

The new room had a fountain in the center, lit from above. Inside the fountain was a small world of moss, leaves, and flowers, with a few fish swimming around in the clear water. The toad hopped off my shoulder and onto the ground, then hopped his way over and splashed into the fountain. He was unscathed by the battle with the statues, and had held on through the whole thing like he was glued in place.

Arthur lowered his helm, causing the black beads of his armor to melt down into the cuirass of the armor. He was breathing heavily, red in the face, and dripping with sweat, which matted down his hair.

“Fuck,” he said. “It’s been a long, long time since anyone has needed to save me.” He lifted up his hand, which was trembling. “This body is worse than I’d thought it would be.”

“Having second thoughts?” I asked.

“No,” he replied. He looked down at my hand. “You didn’t use the ring.”

I looked down at my hand. I hadn’t used Bethel, because I didn’t really think of Bethel as something to be used. She should have acted on her own, but it was worrying that she hadn’t.

<Bethel?> I asked.

<Yes, Juniper?> she replied. There was something flat about her voice.

<Are you okay?> I asked.

<Yes,> she replied.

<I could have used some help back there,> I said.

<I understand,> she replied.

<Are you still capable of acting of your own volition?> I asked.

<I don’t understand the question,> she replied.

“Shit,” I said. “She’s lost a lot. Capable of speech, but cognition is iffy. I’ll figure out what her abilities are, but I’m not sure she’s so much of a person anymore.” I didn’t know how I was going to figure out her abilities, given that most of them had probably failed.

Arthur rested his head against the wall and sat there allowing his breathing to go back to normal. “What were we talking about?” he asked.

“Rescuing women,” I said.

“No,” replied Amaryllis. “Playing the hero.”

“And you were saying you weren’t a hero,” said Arthur, nodding weakly.

“I didn’t get to play the hero all that much,” I said. “The narrative stuff that was put in front of us, there wasn’t very much saving people from imminent and unambiguous threats. Some of it was people wanting to kill us, but a lot of it was harder to say one way or another. I could see where the enemy was coming from. I mean, there was an element of empathy, most of the time, if not at the moment, then afterward.” I paused. “There was this guy I killed in a trial by combat, and it felt good, but then afterward, his niece came to me with tears in her eyes, and … from what Raven said, that wasn’t normally the kind of fallout and forced introspection you needed to deal with.”

“She was right,” said Arthur, nodding briefly before resting his head back on the wall again. “Oh, there would be weeping spouses, certainly, sometimes sons and daughters, but they were always antagonists themselves, completely irredeemable and able to be killed without much moral consideration.”

“Yeah,” I said. I wondered how much that was true, and how much Arthur was telling himself stories. “We … didn’t really have that so much. Oh man, there was this guy who made zombies, and —”

“Don’t say the z-word,” said Arthur. I looked at him for a moment, but he just gave me a weak smile. “The trope?”

“Yeah, except they really don’t like you saying the z-word on Aerb,” I said. “Wait, did you never call them zombies? Or never run into any undead?” Blue-in-the-Bottle postdated Uther, but there were loads of things you could call necromancy on Aerb.

“Oh, we came across perhaps two dozen varieties,” said Arthur. “Some of them on the disjoint planes. I called them ‘walkers’, or ‘shamblers’, or ‘the infected’, until eventually I was running out of distinct names.” He let out a breath, then placed his palms on the floor. “Alright, I think I have my breath back. Gather up your toad and let’s go.”

He didn’t look like he’d gotten his breath back. “Before that, do you mind if I talk to Amaryllis in private for a bit?”

“No, not at all,” he replied. He pulled a drink from extradimensional space and began chugging it, then got out two marzipan fairies he’d stored in his pocket.

I took Amaryllis to the side and spoke to her in a low voice. “How much longer do you think we can carry on?”

“We almost died there,” said Amaryllis. “I went into the glove because one of them was squeezing hard enough I thought he would break my ankle. But this is the end game. There’s a good chance that I’ll die if I don’t bow out. And we can’t rule out that this ends with all of us dying.”

“But you don’t think it will?” I asked. “Because narrative?”

“Because I think you’re strong enough, Juniper,” she replied. “From a narrative perspective, I think your death would work. If you died, it would be a tragedy, a man unable to let go after the loss of his best friend. But I think you’ll make it through.”

“Ah,” I said. I wasn’t sure I liked that reading. I still kind of thought the narrative was useless. “We still have one Landing left, and it’s going to get harder. I’m hoping we come across some army dudes that haven’t been looted, because I don’t know how much longer any of the good stuff is going to last. We’re already hobbled. I want to push on, but I don’t have any faith in narrative, and after that room … it’s looking dicey.”

“Everything is being stripped away,” said Amaryllis. “That’s the nature of going up the Long Stairs, for us.”

I nodded. I didn’t think that talk had actually helped me much, but I was glad we’d had it.

“Ready?” asked Arthur.

“Sure,” I said. The next door we needed to go through had a giant red X on it, which seemed a bit ominous, but wasn’t a part of RDP. The rooms weren’t uniformly getting harder, but we were losing our advantages, and all it took was a difficult room for us to be splattered against the ground like so much bird shit.

“Were you leaving the toad here?” asked Arthur.

I looked back at the fountain. “Oh,” I said. “Right.” I went back to the fountain and picked up the toad. He seemed like he wanted to stay, and struggled in my hands for a bit, but once I went back over to the door, he stayed still in my hands, and reluctantly took his position on the shoulder.

We headed off down the Long Stairs, heading to the next Landing.

Long Pig

Before we reached the last Landing, Arthur’s armor promptly fell apart. The thousands of black beads fell off him and hit the floor all at once, clattering to the ground and rolling everywhere. He wasn’t quite naked beneath them, but he was just in briefs again. They had to have been magical, because they’d changed size when he’d reversed his age.

He sighed. “I’d wondered when that was going to happen.” He looked at Amaryllis. “Is Sable still working, and do you have a spare suit of armor?”

“It is, and I do,” said Amaryllis. “Though perhaps if we’re losing storage, we should switch to full packs.”

Arthur grimaced. “My stamina and strength are both lacking at the moment. Thankfully, there’s not that much we’ll need.”

“Food and water,” said Amaryllis, popping them out of Sable and setting them on the ground. “A first aid kit, if the fairies fail. Guns, lots of guns.” I was mildly surprised to see proper handguns coming out of the glove, followed quickly by an AR-15 and a few magazines of ammo.

“The backpack never made weapons,” I said, frowning at them.

“I had three years,” replied Amaryllis. “They’re knock-offs, obviously, made on Aerb, but hopefully interoperable with weapons we find on fireteam remnants, if it comes to that. Though I do have to point out that they’re a significant amount of weight, and wouldn’t have done a damned thing against most of the threats we’ve faced so far.”

“Firearms,” said Arthur, shaking his head. “I’d never wanted them to show up on Aerb.”

“So how does that fit in with them being here?” asked Amaryllis. “You said yourself that I was here to convince you to come back. Why would I have a thing you didn’t like, or other uncomfortable news?”

“I can’t rightly say,” sighed Arthur. He was looking at the guns. “You know, I only ever shot one once.”

“That time we took you to the range?” I asked. “Well, hopefully your Knack is intact, because we might have to use these as our primary weapons.”

He picked up a handgun, hefting it and inadvertently muzzle sweeping me in the process.

“Fucking gun safety man,” I said, taking it from him. “Maybe it’s better if you keep using the sword.”

“Do you really think we’ll need guns?” he asked. He looked so young, and it was hard to get over it.

He was clearly uncomfortable with the guns, despite being the master of however many magics, one of the greatest warriors in known history, et cetera. I tried to remind myself that guns hadn’t really been a thing on Aerb when he’d been around, and his brain was just running on old programming. The one time me and my dad had brought him to the range hadn’t been a great experience, though not because anything had happened. He just didn’t really like guns.

“I don’t know,” I said. “Try not to sweat it.” I looked at Amaryllis and opened my mouth to ask about holsters, but she was already pulling them out.

It took some time to get everything set up, and I was worried about how much weight I was carrying, not so much because of the strain it was putting on me, but because I wasn’t very used to fighting with guns. I’d used rifles and pistols a few times on Aerb, but not terribly recently, and they’d fallen by the wayside in favor of either my sword or my magics (which had now dwindled away). I’d used void weapons with some regularity, but they handled much differently.

“I don’t suppose these are specially enchanted?” I asked Amaryllis. “Or special materials?”

“No,” she replied. “Looking at your notes, there were too many variables. Cold iron, silver, gold, sulfur, wood — it would have been a total crapshoot.”

“Fair enough,” I said. I had a pistol at either hip, a rucksack, a rifle, and two swords, which all seemed like a bit much, but there was a good chance that I would need all of it going forward. Unlike Uther, I was still at full strength. I’d gotten used to just pulling things from extradimensional space on a whim, but eventually those would fail too, and it was only good luck that they hadn’t yet.

But of course, for all that preparation, the next door we opened led straight into the Landing, and I immediately had to disarm while Arthur stepped forward and engaged in diplomacy. This, thankfully, I could understand: the felheim were close enough to Hellmouth that they’d learned English.

The fourth/first Landing dated to a time when I had absolutely hated all of the standard fantasy fare, and went out of my way to not include elves, dwarves, orcs, or the other staples. I was looking for stuff that was fresh and interesting, rather than rehashed a hundred times over, and my reading and research had gone toward the mythologies and folk tales of other cultures, and finally, toward building up some stuff of my own that was an attempt at creating a fantasy canon that looked like it might be from some parallel universe.

The inhabitants weren’t elves, but they weren’t elves in a really insistent way that made it clear to everyone that they were trying to avoid being elves while still filling somewhat of the same role. Yes, they were gracile and tall, with preternatural reflexes, and yes, they had a certain snootiness to them, but they didn’t have the long hair or the naturalist connections, nor the pointy ears. It was the kind of thing that I’d made at twelve and then looked back on at seventeen wondering what I’d been thinking. Their hook was that they were essentially OCD cockroaches from a deathworld who had come to the Long Stairs because it was, by comparison, extremely hospitable. (When I was twelve years old, I had understood ‘OCD’ to mean keeping things super clean and being really fastidious. When I was seventeen, I saw that in my old notes and tried to do something a little bit more like actual OCD, with anxiety and compulsions that helped soothe that anxiety.)

The felheim checked us for weapons three times, patting us down once we’d voluntarily put everything we had on the ground. They had long, bony fingers, attached to long, bony arms, and I hated the feeling of being touched by them. They were pale and chronically malnourished, in spite of having ample food. Their facial features were flattened, and I couldn’t help but be reminded of pug dogs, despite there not being much of a resemblance. It was just something about their look, like they were a breed of humanoid that had been intentionally bred for some absurd aesthetic purpose and collected a whole bunch of crippling flaws as a side effect.

“Welcome,” one of the felheim said, once it had been confirmed that we were unarmed. His vocalization of English was very imperfect, the vowels rounded in unfortunate ways and the consonants a hair off.

Our weapons were put into a container, and would be carried through the Landing for us, assuming that we were still living at the end of it. Packing up the weapons was a process which involved a lot of nervous tics on the part of our hosts, including wiping down the blades, and sometimes redoing things that they had already done before. They looked through our packs and tossed everything, which needed to be repacked. I even got checked for weapons again in the middle of it. I really didn’t want to go without the vorpal blade, and I also didn’t want them handling the guns — I got muzzle swept again — but it was part of RDP, and we were going to get it all back once we were past the exchange of gifts. Between the three of us, I was pretty sure we would be able to fuck them up regardless of whether or not we had our weapons, and it wouldn’t have been all that much work to take their weapons from them. It still rubbed me the wrong way.

“What is your business in the Landing?” asked our guide. I was pretty sure she was a woman, but it was hard to tell with the felheim. It was important only insofar as they were a semi-matriarchal society with a lot of rules about gender.

“We’re only passing through,” said Arthur. “Heading for the Hellmouth.”

“You will stay one night,” replied our guide. “You will barter for food and supplies. There will be a meeting with the fellinari which you will attend. You will follow our rules and customs.”

We said nothing in response, because there hadn’t actually been a question in there.

The thing about felheim was that it was incredibly hard to know what was deliberate, considered ritual, and what was the result of individual anxieties and compulsions. Our guide stopped to touch the doorframe of every door we passed, but we had no way of knowing whether we were supposed to do that too, except that Arthur had played the campaign before, and I was the one who had written it up. We kept our hands to ourselves.

The environment of the Landing looked like thousands of strips of dried squid, sometimes plain and sometimes with shellac applied. I say ‘dried squid’ because back on Earth I’d picked up a pack from a visit to an Asian market and then never eaten it, and that was explicitly the basis for the Landing. If you’ve never seen a packet of dried squid before, it’s stringy and white, like I imagine ligaments would look if you stripped them from the body and left them to dry in the hot sun. Whatever material they were using, which I assumed (perhaps wrongly) wasn’t dried strips of squid, they used it almost everywhere, though there were occasional black support rods. The ceilings were all fairly low, low enough that I was a bit worried about hitting my head, and the lighting came from lightning bugs the size of basketballs, which were strapped in place on the ceilings. There wasn’t any greenery, but there were a few things that looked like they were living, fungus or mottled patches of bacteria, and once or twice, small, hairless animals in cages.

“These are your rooms,” said our guide. She’d led us to two of the only rooms with doors on them. “The woman in that one, the men in the other. We will collect you for the meeting in the morning.”

I wanted to protest that this was dumb and stupid, but that wasn’t how you were supposed to deal with the felheim. Amaryllis went to her own room without complaint, and Arthur and I went to ours. There were no beds, only hammocks, four of them strung up as temporary sleeping places. There was no food or water either, and no place to use a bathroom. If we were approaching meal time, they would feed us, but that probably wasn’t something that we were particularly interested in, not when we had our own food. The felheim were, if not universally anorexic, then at least possessed of a universal anxiety and obsession toward food that led to some pretty bad compulsions. The anxiety wasn’t about body image though, it was a worry that the food would kill them, because in their ancestral environment, that was probably the case.

“How long of a wait do you think we’re in for?” asked Arthur. “I’m debating taking off my armor.”

“I have no idea,” I said. “This is the kind of stuff you usually skip over in tabletop games.”

I took the toad from my shoulder and pulled a small dish from a mess kit in my pack, then poured a little water into it and let him hop in. He seemed to like it, and splashed around a bit while Arthur and I talked.

“I know that,” he replied, raising an eyebrow in my direction. “But you always had things going on behind the scenes. You decided on things that had jack squat to do with anything we were going to be playing.”

“Some of that was just me trying to pin things down ahead of time,” I replied. “It was always better to over-prepare. And if you can’t over-prepare, be really ready to improvise.”

“Oh come off it,” he replied. He apparently had decided that we would be together for a while, since he was taking off his armor. I was keeping mine on, though it was noticeably less comfortable than it had been earlier in the Long Stairs. “You can just admit that you loved the details for their own sake.”

“Okay,” I said. “I did. I liked thinking up details, and I liked the paths of research that it always sent me down. There were times I temporarily knew a whole lot about the 1860 census, or the hiring preferences of the FBI, or the corner cases of color theory.” I paused. “Sorry, I feel like I’m trying to make a defense, but I don’t know what about.”

“I’ve made you feel defensive,” said Arthur. “It’s my fault. Whatever I believe about you and your role in this world, I think we can be past it.”

“We can be ‘past’ you thinking that I imprisoned you in a crapsack world for forty years?” I asked.

“Aerb isn’t a crapsack world,” he replied. “Or I suppose it wasn’t, when I left. Perhaps things have changed.”

I shrugged. “Maybe that’s putting it too harshly. I was just trying to point to the torture thing, I guess. That’s still, I imagine, the most sensible conclusion from your perspective?”

“See, this is why you were always terrible when we played social deduction games,” smiled Arthur. “Even if you were innocent, you would go into these tortured I-think you-think I-think scenarios rather than just trying to make your case. No one wants to trust the guy who is willing to ruminate at length on how he would expect his actions to look from the outside point of view. Someone would accuse you, and you would say, ‘logically, a denial of my guilt has very little information value to you’.”

“But I’m right,” I said. “It’s still something you think.”

“Of course,” he nodded. “But as I said, we can move past it, even if it remains unresolved. The answer to who did this to me and why isn’t one that I need answered. It doesn’t need to be part of the narrative of me leaving the narrative. My only aim is for all this to end.”

“Sure,” I said. I sighed and hefted myself into a hammock. If I fell asleep, I was probably going to regret not taking off the armor, but we had no idea when the felheim would be coming to get us, and I didn’t want to get dressed again right after I’d taken everything off. If the fairies were still working, I didn’t think they would do too much for sore muscles.

“Do you remember staying up late during sleepovers?” asked Arthur.

“Sure,” I replied, opening my eyes back up. “They weren’t too long ago, from my perspective.”

“Your mom always kept your house so cold,” he said. “It made it hard for me to sleep, so I would talk to you way after the lights had gone out, and you would get less and less coherent as time went on. Your responses would get slower too, and sometimes I didn’t know whether there would be a response. I thought about drawing things on your face or something, but I never did. I snooped a few times though.”

“Snooped?” I asked.

“Yeah,” he replied. “I’d get up from the cot and look inside drawers or in — you remember that wooden box you had?”

“Yeah,” I replied. It wasn’t anything important, just a wooden box I’d found at a thrift shop and kept a bunch of junk in.

“That,” he said. “I never found anything interesting, which maybe you could have guessed. And I shouldn’t have done it, obviously. I felt so guilty about it, for years after, even once I was on Aerb.”

“Kind of a shitty thing to do, yeah,” I said. I shifted around uncomfortably in my hammock. “I, uh, I’m not really sure — what the point of telling me is? Not that I don’t appreciate it.”

“I think when I was younger, I might have said that there was obviously a correspondence between that violation of privacy and what the Dungeon Master did,” said Arthur. “Different levels, obviously, but the feeling of being a snoop might have been similar. Now though, I think it’s just something that happened.”

“You don’t think it’s, uh, part of the narrative?” I asked.

“Oh, I have no idea,” he replied. “You being here makes me think I know the narrative forces less well than I thought, if I’m being honest.”

“Second thoughts?” I asked, for a second time.

“Not at all,” he replied. “No second thoughts, no cold feet, just a tight feeling in my stomach that comes from facing ineffable forces I don’t understand. It’s not a particularly unusual feeling, given some of the things I’ve faced. Everyone I know on Aerb is dead now, with a very few exceptions. The die is cast, the gamble is made.”

“Sorry about your wife,” I said. “And children, and … all that.”

“I had the consent and support of my wife,” he said. “We had a good run of it together, but she was in ailing health, and didn’t want me to see her slowly die. I tried my best to save her, and it became clear that her death was a part of the narrative. There is an ache in my heart where she once was, but it was an ache that had been growing even when we were together, and my work kept us apart more than I had liked. There were, of course, some oddities to our relationship, ways in which it was unconventional, which have already been alluded to.”

“The other women,” I said.

“And a few men,” he replied. “It was an arrangement that —” He looked over at me and stopped. “You should see your face.”

“Sorry, I didn’t think you would, uh, just come out like that,” I said.

“It was only once or twice,” he replied. “I still think of myself as straight. Aerb is so chock full of different genders and sexes that it feels pedestrian to care about it. One or two men, I guess I should say, but there were others as well who fell into different categories. When we knew each other, you always cringed at the lurid details, so I think it would suffice to keep it at that.”

“Ah,” I said. I tried to collect my thoughts. “I talked to Pallida Sade. She said that you went apoplectic when you found out that Dahlia was a lesbian.”

Arthur snorted. “And you’d been wondering about that, what distance there was between the person I’d been and the person I became?”

“I guess,” I replied. “Not really that important, but yeah, it’s one of those things that seemed small when I heard it and then stuck with me for way longer than I’d thought it would. I didn’t know whether it was just the way the world had impacted you, or whether it was something you’d always felt, or what.”

“I was angry,” he said. “Homosexuality had a mild taboo in Anglecynn, though not as much as, say, 1950s America, and with considerable options for greener pastures. I didn’t agree, obviously, but I also didn’t fight too hard against it, not when there was always some new crisis to deal with, not when there were bigger issues at hand. I kept waiting for a flash in the pan, I suppose, something that I could use to draw the attention of the kingdom, but it never came along. It was a problem that faded into the background, and I know that doesn’t excuse it, but … well, you wanted to know about Dahlia? I hated her relationship with Pallida, mostly because I knew Pallida. I said everything I could think of to try to split them apart, knowing that with as hard headed as Dahlia was, it was probably futile.”

“Did you ever apologize?” I asked. “Repair things with her?”

“We were never estranged,” he said. “I was closer to her than to my sons. She had the adventurer’s spirit, and her mother’s strength of will. But if you’re asking if I ever apologized for my outburst, then no, I never did. When she was old enough, she moved to Cidium, an ancient city that Amaryllis mentioned still stands, and began her own life there. I visited her, from time to time, when my schedule allowed. I was introduced to a few girlfriends, and some I approved of. It took me some time to understand her as her own person, to accept that she was going to make mistakes.” He paused. “You and Amaryllis,” he shook his head. “It’s awkward for me, but I appreciated that you kept your displays of affection to a minimum. Amaryllis doesn’t take after Dahlia in that regard. Dahlia never shared her thought process with me, but I imagine she chose Cidium specifically because of its social rules, which favored homosexuality.”

“Favored it,” I said. “Meaning … it was the dominant thing?”

“You don’t know?” he asked. “I would have thought that Cidium would have been one of your direct creations. It had your smell about it.”

“I mean, it was,” I said. “Cities of geological age, imbued with a magic that would keep them functional in perpetuity so that a city could build on top of itself for thousands of generations — and being built down the side of an enormous cliff, that too. But if you’re saying that they’re a place with gay pride parades or something, then no, that wasn’t something I ever contemplated, or knew about until now, if it’s still true. I mean, that’s also not how I would have done it, I would have done something like, I don’t know, extramarital same sex partners or something. Or better, extramarital opposite sex partners for the purposes of procreation and raising children but not otherwise.” I looked over at Arthur, who was staring at me. “Is that exactly what it is?”

“Yes,” he said.

“Yeah,” I said. “About three out of five times I can predict what Aerb is like just by thinking about what I would do if it were me making the world. As superpowers go, it’s pretty mediocre.”

“And what happens with the other two fifths?” he asked.

“If I’m making a declaration outright, and I’m wrong, I look like an asshole,” I said. “But if I’m just pontificating, then it’s not so bad, because I just look like the kind of person who idly speculates about things in order to show off how smart I am.”

“I’m starting to realize how odd this all must have been for you,” he said.

“‘Have been’?” I asked. “Past tense?”

“You know what I mean,” he replied. “One of the only elements of Aerb that I was responsible for was Uther Penndraig, and when I assumed the mantle, he was unknown to anyone. I was free to diverge, and the name might as well have been a coincidence. But for you, you invented those things. It’s like the difference between stepping into a book you’ve been reading and an author doing the same to a book they’d been writing.”

“I guess,” I replied.

“Sorry for earlier,” he said. “All of it. It’s been a long time for me. There are a lot of emotions. And I’m sorry that my apparent death caused you so much pain and distress.”

“No problem,” I said. “I get it,” though if I was being honest, I wasn’t sure that I did get the complexity of everything that was going through his head. We sat there in silence for a bit, and I began to drift off despite myself.

“You and Tiff,” he said. “How’d that happen?”

“I don’t know,” I replied, opening my eyes back up. “I guess after we’d known each other long enough, I just kind of … had a crush on her.” I could feel myself blushing. “And while she was driving me home, I blurted it out, and she said she felt the same. There’s not much to the story.”

“I spent decades thinking about high school,” said Arthur. “It was, in some ways, my job. Can you imagine that? You’re forty years old, and one of the primary things you do, that you feel like you’re forced to do, is to spend a lot of time thinking about the details of your life in high school, going over the principal characters, thinking about their relationships to each other, and how that fed into the games that you all played. You sit there trying to remember every anecdote you possibly can.”

“I can’t imagine being forty,” I said. “Let alone all the other stuff.”

“All that time thinking about high school,” said Arthur. “All that time dissecting people, drawing them, mapping the layout of the town, dredging things up, sometimes with magical assistance, making recreations … and I just never knew this fairly major thing that brings context to everything else. You and Tiff.”

“I think life is like that,” I said. “I mean, people having their own unknowable internal lives.”

“But you don’t want to go back to her,” said Arthur. “You don’t want to return to Earth, even to see her.”

“We broke up,” I said. “After you died. I was an asshole to everyone, including her, and maybe we could have become friends again, but I think it would have been better for her sake to just let me fade away like an ugly bruise. Besides, if I really wanted to talk to Tiff, there’s a version of her on Aerb, one that grew up in Anglecynn with an Aerb version of me. I don’t know, it’s complicated.”

There was a pause, and I let a slow blink turn into allowing my eyes to stay shut.

“You dream-skewered into your own body, right?” asked Arthur.

“I did,” I nodded. “But it was the same for you, wasn’t it? Except that dream-skewering wasn’t a recognized thing in your time. For me, I found out that was what I was almost right away, thanks to your scheme to get me to Speculation and Scrutiny, which nearly got me killed, by the way.”

“You got my message?” he asked. “I had always thought that was an extremely long shot. The mirror messages were done somewhat early on.”

“It was, but still, I got it,” I said. “It wasn’t all that helpful. You could have come back and given me more concrete information, you know. Like, ‘Hello Juniper, I left Aerb and went to these coordinates where there’s a door to the Long Stairs, which lead to Earth, the password is ‘Password1’.’ That would have been helpful.”

“If I had known you’d be coming down the Long Stairs after me, I would probably have done anything in my power to stop it,” said Arthur. “I’d have smashed the mirror. But if you’re really not going to do anything to stop me, if you are, in fact, shepherding me back to Earth, then I suppose it’s immaterial.”

“I just wanted to talk, really,” I said. “I just wanted my friend back. I’m glad you’re coming around to that. I had missed you. You’re completely different, of course, but there are things that are just how I remembered them, when you drop the Uther persona.”

“Oh, it’s not a persona,” he replied, chuckling a bit. “I was, I am Uther. I learned to speak in a specific way as a king, but eventually people expected me to be unconventional, so in time, it drifted into a style of my own. But I can do code switching, the same as anyone.”

“Hrm,” I said. “Thank you, I guess. It’s been nice.”

“Of course,” he replied.

“I wonder how Amaryllis is getting on,” I said, looking at the wall.

“Oh,” he said. “I expect we’ll never see her again.”

I looked over at him, suddenly feeling awake. “What do you mean?”

“We’ve split the party, and it’s likely that we’ll have to make a choice between saving her, or at least reuniting with her, or forging on ahead. At that point we’ll have a confrontation, because I’ll refuse to get wrapped up in that plot, and you’ll have to decide between going with me or staying to save her.” He sighed. “My track record of predicting such plots is actually somewhat poor, considering how formulaic the narrative can be. At any rate, I wouldn’t quite wager that we’ve seen the last of her, but we’ve already been split up.”

“If it comes down to it, I’ll go with you,” I said. “It’s what Amaryllis would want. But I’m not sure that it will come to that, and if it does, I could also just use the crystals to track you and catch up with you, hopefully quickly enough that I could get you some healing.”

“And I would need healing because?” he asked.

“Because it’s pretty likely that without our help you’d be grievously injured,” I replied.

“Fair,” he replied.

We waited for a bit, and this time I did fall asleep with my armor on. When I woke back up, it took me some time to come to my senses and realize where I was and how I had gotten there. I looked over to where Arthur had been sleeping and was relieved to see that he was still there. I was a bit stiff and sore from sleeping in my armor, but the hammock had done a better job than I’d thought it would, keeping me from rolling around too much or laying on any particularly hard bits.

There was another knock on the door, which must have been what woke me up. It was impossible to tell how much time had passed, because there was no outside light in the Long Stairs, and the bug whose glow lit the room was still as strong as it had been when I’d dozed off. I looked over at Arthur’s hammock again, and was surprised to see that he was sleeping, or at least doing a really good job of faking it. Whatever curse or boon the Lord of Dreams had placed on him to make him incapable of sleep, we’d apparently gone far enough up the Long Stairs that it had worn off.

I went to answer the door, and looked expectantly at the felheim standing there.

“You will go now to the elders,” it said.

“Arthur!” I called.

He was awake in an instant and moving to grab a sword that wasn’t there, but he relaxed almost as quickly and spared only a moment to look at his hands and feel his face. “I need to get my armor on,” he said. He seemed a little dazed. “That was the first time I’ve slept in a very, very long time. It’s so … disconcerting.”

I was worried that Arthur getting his armor back on would cause some problems for the felheim, but he or she just stood there, waiting patiently. Arthur was quick about it, strapping things down as though he’d done it hundreds of times before, but I was guessing that this, too, was something new for him, or at least something old being brought back. All the armor he’d regularly worn in the past decade or so would have been the stuff you could just whistle and have it attach itself to you, or that would slither in place onto your body, or simply appear without fanfare.

Once he was done, we were guided down the hallways of the Landing, through their tunnels of dried white ligaments. Amaryllis wasn’t with us, I couldn’t help but notice, and I hoped that Arthur was wrong about us having already seen her for the last time.

The room for the elders was one of the largest we’d seen in the Landing, and it had more than a dozen tunnels leading out from it, allowing the felheim avenues of escape in case something horrible came for them. Being able to escape made the felheim feel secure, and by the opposite side of the coin, putting us in a room with a single door for so long was a way of making us psychologically off-balance. It didn’t have that effect, because we weren’t like them, which was a little funny.

“The exchange of gifts will commence,” said one of the three elder felheim. They were all ancient, with blue veins beneath paper-thin skin, and they sat on impractically tall chairs that weren’t quite ornate enough for me to call them thrones. I knew them all well enough, down to their names, since the not-elves Landing had been the most prominent among Landings in the games we played. If we went against them, they would pull out spears, but I thought we wouldn’t do too terribly in the fight, even though we were unarmed. (They predated Hollow Knight, but after I played the Mantis Lord fight from that game, it was how I saw the elder felheim. That had been one of the last videogames I’d played on Earth, back when I’d developed a habit of going on Steam every night and trying to find a game that would convince me not to kill myself.)

Uther stepped forward. “Among the weapons taken from us was an M4 carbine, a gunpowder weapon with two magazines of ammunition. That is my gift to you.”

I stepped forward. “Among the weapons taken from us was an M9 sidearm,” I said. “It’s a gunpowder weapon with two magazines of ammunition. That is my gift to you.”

I wasn’t sure how my toad would present anything to the felheim, or whether they might expect him to, but he just stayed on my shoulder, and no one said anything about him.

This was all pretty standard, believe it or not. The fireteams that came into the Long Stairs traded away guns, so this was established protocol. One of the first missions that any fireteam went on was to reach the first Landing and do a trade with the elves, usually in exchange for enchantments on their own weapons, or if they already had that, then something else that was magical in nature. Arming the elves wasn’t ideal, and there had been some blowback, but the magic that the elves could provide was deemed to be well worth the problems that giving them weapons had caused. That the problems were mostly for the fireteams and the beneficiaries were mostly those on the surface was something that was discussed a lot during the campaign.

“Your gift will be presented to you,” said the central felheim. “Then you will take your weapons and leave.” They had brought the box in, and I was thankful for that, because I wanted the vorpal sword back as soon as possible. It was incredibly powerful, and seemed like it was likely to keep working all the way to the top.

“Why is my wife not here?” I asked.

“You will be silent while here,” replied the felheim. “You will accept your gifts and leave.” They were being more curt with us than I had expected them to be, which gave me an uneasy feeling. They continued on despite my interruption, showing no particular sign that they ever intended to answer me. “The large one will accept this gift.”

One of the attendants came from a corridor they’d been hiding in, carrying a large cylinder that was hidden by a thin cloth. When he reached me, he paused for a moment and then dramatically removed the cloth, revealing a giant candle. It was ivory, maybe six inches in diameter and two feet long, with three braided wicks. I took it from him, and was surprised by the weight of it. So far as I could tell, it was just a giant candle, but with vibration magic gone I had no ability to see magic.

“The candle does nothing here, and can only be used in the world beyond the depths,” said the rightmost one. “You will save it until your return.”

Now that was interesting. How they knew I was planning to return was … well, probably because they’d been listening in on our conversations. I wasn’t about to take it at face value though.

“For the small one, there is something special,” said the leftmost felheim. If they got down from their chairs, I was pretty sure I would have zero ability to tell them apart.

Another attendant came forward as the previous one retreated, this one with a metal cloche. I didn’t know why they insisted on these things being a secret until they were revealed, but I hoped that it would be something good, or at least relatively unexciting.

The attendant lifted up the cloche and revealed a white mouse.

“Fuck,” I said.

LSP #0001 White Mouse Protocol was one of the first bits of worldbuilding I had ever done for the Long Stairs. If you see a white mouse, you kill it within five minutes. What happened if you waited too long was a mystery, one that I had never deigned to give a solution to. It had been violated only once during a session, the second time we ran the campaign, mostly because Reimer was feeling like pushing things, and I’d declared an instant TPK when the time was up, not even allowing them to know what had killed them.

There were, so far as I could tell, two ways we could play this. The first was to attack right away, killing the mouse seconds after it was uncovered. The second was to graciously take the mouse, then have Arthur crush it to death as soon as possible, hopefully not causing a diplomatic incident in the process. We had no idea why they had thought to give us this mouse, or whether the White Mouse Protocol applied, or whether the timer was ticking down, or had somehow been defused, but there was absolutely no way that I was letting that mouse live for longer than a minute.

I glanced at Arthur, wondering how he was going to deal with this, and saw that he was already heading for our weapons.

I moved to the mouse, snatching it off the silver dish it was on, throwing it against the ground, and stomping it to death in what was nearly one smooth motion, as though I’d practiced it (I had not practiced it). For their part, the felheim seemed stunned by the brazen stomping of a living gift, and the attendant who’d been holding the cloche was the first to act, fleeing down the tunnels.

The elder felheim dropped down from their perches in unison, holding gleaming spears, and right about that time, Arthur threw the vorpal blade at me, spinning it so quickly that it felt like a miracle that I was able to catch it. I brought it up just in time to parry one of their spears, but all three of them were on me at once, and the spears gave them better range. I dodged one and took an unfortunate hit to the chest, instantly feeling wet blood soaking through.

The next attack was a heavy thrust toward my groin, and this time I was able to position the blade for a proper parry. I cut straight through the spear, halving its length, then pressed the advantage, dashing toward him. He tried to parry the second sword strike, but the vorpal blade’s edge was sharp enough to cut through the remainder of his spear, his arm, his armor, and the entirety of his torso. I used the moment of slowed time to take note of where the other two were positioned, and as soon as my blade had swept through, I was on them, using raw aggression to get the upper hand. I was bleeding quite a bit from the wound in my chest, and the fact that they could pierce my armor spoke to the power of the magic they had, or the magic my armor had lost, but the sheer sharpness of the vorpal blade was enough to tear through them.

“Fuck,” I said, once they were laying on the ground in pieces. I reached down to touch my chest. It looked worse than it felt, I was pretty sure.

“We should get moving,” said Arthur. He’d collected his weapons, and handed the rest to me. “More will be coming. They’re proficient with poisons.”

I looked down at the wound on my chest. “Fuck.”

“Hey, think,” he said. “We already went over this. The elders sit up on their perch looking over this stuff. We had a whole session about it. They didn’t keep their spears poisoned because poison decays over time, they’d be going through pots of the stuff. There was a whole argument about it, you came down on my side. Now let’s get going.”

“Amaryllis,” I said.

He stared at me for a moment. “I’m going,” he said. “I’ll make my own way. I’m still good with a sword, and you can track me. Try to catch up.”

I nodded, then took off down the tunnels, trying my best to remember the route we’d taken. The Landing had a few claustrophobic qualities to it, and one of them was how hard it was to navigate. I’d have used the crystals to locate Amaryllis, but it was still giving me a headache.

I managed to navigate my way to the place they’d kept us, but the room she’d been staying in was empty. I only spent a minute or so looking for a note, but it wasn’t as though she would have hid it. I had no idea whether she’d fled when she heard the alarm, or whether she’d been called in to have a meeting with the felheim elders before us, or if there was some third option I wasn’t giving enough attention to. Frustrated, I took off down the tunnels, twice fighting someone who was probably just trying to come to the defense of his home. The blood flowing from my chest wound had slowed, but all the running wasn’t doing wonders.

I wished that I had the blood gauge on a HUD to see how bad it was. It was the first time I’d actually wanted some of the gamification back.

I was following Arthur, who I could track, and when the crystals led me through a door, I kicked through, leading me back into the Long Stairs. I hadn’t missed the seemingly endless rooms and their ridiculous rules. This one was another one with a feast set out, and I bit off a piece of still-warm chicken (or what I hoped was chicken, but tasted more like pork) before rushing to the next door the crystals pointed out.

Whether through bad luck on my part or a headstart for him, it took me five rooms to catch up with him.

“Finally,” he said once I was up there. “Why are you still carrying that thing?”

I looked down at where he was pointing and realized that I’d been carrying the enormous candle with me. “Huh,” I said. “I didn’t even realize I’d grabbed it.”

We both gave the candle a skeptical look.

“I’m not sure you did grab it,” said Arthur.

“I might have grabbed it after you left,” I said. A lot of the running around and killing things was a blur.

“Are you really making excuses for this candle?” asked Arthur. “Juniper, at this point, it’s like making excuses for a friend who’s been bitten by a zombie. The candle is fucky and you know it.” Uther would have never said ‘fucky’, and I wondered whether that was Arthur reverting, or code switching because he was with me.

“I think it might be important though,” I said. “I didn’t get around to telling you this, but in one of my conversations with the Dungeon Master, he had a book of my adventures with the title ‘Worth the Candle’. So, maybe it’s, I don’t know. Important.” The more I said, the more feeble it felt.

“Juniper, how long have you had that memory?” asked Arthur.

“Oh come off it,” I said. “You think that’s a fake memory? There are subordinate memories. I can remember talking to Amaryllis about the title.”

“That’s an indicator of memetic strength,” said Arthur. “What is it you think the candle does that it was so important to take?”

“I don’t know,” I said. “I mean, it is suspicious, but maybe it’s, I don’t know, the secret to all this. Maybe it’s a candle of invocation.”

“A what?” he asked.

“A D&D thing,” I said, slightly taken aback. “Surely you remember Reimer talking about Pun-pun?”

“Oh,” replied Arthur. He folded his arms across his chest. “And you think it’s your path to godhood.”

“Okay, well, maybe?” I asked. “I don’t know how to convince you that the candle might actually be important, whatever other anomalous properties it might have. And I can’t leave it here, because then I might never find it again.”

“It’s pretty clearly a mimic or something worse,” said Arthur.

“Agree to disagree?” I asked.

Arthur sighed, and for a moment he seemed to be weighing the wisdom of trying to take the candle from me, or whether he might be able to cut it into pieces. “Fine. Now let’s go.”

“We should wait for Amaryllis,” I said.

“How long?” asked Arthur, seeming exasperated that his great-great-and-so-on-granddaughter was holding things up by possibly being in mortal danger.

“Half a day,” I said. “I can’t track her, but she can track us, or rather, you, and she can pop the clones from a distance to resolve the issues with the crystal if she really wants to. I think.”

“Fine by me,” he said. He sat down against one of the walls. “I nearly died.”

“When?” I asked.

“When we were separated,” he replied. “I went through a room with an enormous monster that almost took my head clean off.”

“And what?” I asked. “He had armor so thick you couldn’t cut through it?”

“He was a fast regenerator,” replied Arthur. “I cut off his arms and legs and he grew them back in a handful of heartbeats. I cut off his head and he didn’t bother regrowing a new one. From experience, I knew that meant going for a vital point, but his heart was behind some kind of impenetrable layer of bone. When he brought his fists down he cracked the floor, and I had to stay constantly moving while I tried to chunk through his regeneration or find some way to get at something vital. It had been a long time since I’d had a fight like that.”

“You’ve had close calls before,” I said. I was watching him closely. He didn’t look shaken, just a bit stunned, like he’d had a revelation.

“It wasn’t that it was close, it was that I felt weak and powerless,” he said. “The battles I fought in the latter half of my career were difficult, arduous things, but there was never any despair on my part. I would go through the tools in my toolbox, and sometimes need to invent something new on the fly, but this … I honestly felt like I was going to die.”

“Yeah,” I said. “So how’d you end up beating it?”

“I circled around, jumped up onto its back, and drove my sword down his throat hole,” said Arthur. “It was a huge risk, but I had exhausted every other option, and I was gassed, again. I’m out of ammunition, by the way.”

“Well, I’m here now,” I said. “The vorpal blade is one of the most powerful weapons I’ve ever introduced into a campaign, and I have better stamina than you. Plus Bethel still has limited functionality.” Of everything that remained, the five-pound force was the only one worth speaking of, along with the ability to change shape. I could speak to Bethel, but it was like talking to a Markov chain.

“How was a normal fireteam supposed to defeat something like that?” asked Arthur.

“They weren’t,” I replied. “They were supposed to die horribly and then roll new characters. The guy you encountered, he was part of the second iteration of the Long Stairs. We’ve come across a few of them, and my guess is that as we get closer to the Hellmouth, we’ll find more. Eventually, it’ll just be you and me with swords that only have a mild magic to them.” And hopefully, the vorpal blade. “This is what I’ve been trying to tell you.”

“You took your anger out on the others by running a campaign like this,” said Arthur.

“Yeah,” I said. “It was a shitty thing to do, and a shitty thing for us to have to make our way through. I tried explaining, but I guess this is the first time it’s sinking in for you. Look, if you still want to return to Earth —”

“I do,” he replied.

“I think the plan sucks,” I said. “I think there’s a good chance that we’ll both die. But I feel like I have a duty to see it out, so we’re going to try our best to get you to the Hellmouth, and then hope that you’re not vivisected by the War Department. But first, we’re going to hope that Amaryllis makes her way out of the Landing and then doesn’t run into too much trouble on the way to us. That means we wait.”

I was worried about her, but there was nothing I could do except for blindly running back to the Landing and searching around, and for all I knew, she wasn’t there anymore. I knew for a fact that wasn’t what she would have wanted us to do. The mission was the important thing, she would have said. She was ready and willing to sacrifice herself if it meant getting to the end. I wasn’t incredibly confident that she was thinking clearly, but I tried my best to put myself in her shoes.

“Alright,” Arthur replied. “I need a rest anyway.”

We waited twelve hours, resting from the fighting and occasionally talking, mostly to share in memories of school and idle summers in Kansas, or movies we’d enjoyed together. I noticed that Arthur rarely brought up his time on Aerb, which must have been deliberate. I didn’t mind though. Aerb had a tainted taste when he talked about it.

I kept expecting Amaryllis to come through one of the doors, but after the twelve hours were up, she was still nowhere to be seen, and turning the crystals her direction gave me nothing but another headache, which meant she either still had the clones up, or there was some other problem with the alien technology in my head. It was hard to think that she was gone so quickly, not even having a chance to say goodbye or wish us luck. It was like a soap bubble popping.

“Alright,” I said, getting to my feet and securing my equipment. The toad had been hopping around the room and spending some of his time in a bowl of water I’d set out for him, but when I stood, he leaped up six feet to settle onto my shoulder, like he was worried someone else would take his customary spot. “Let’s finish this thing.”

“And you’re taking the candle with you?” he asked.

I glanced down and realized I was carrying it under one arm. “Yeah,” I said. “It might be important.”

Long Live the King

The Long Stairs had, in fact, gotten harder, and I didn’t think it was just a function of us losing power as we went along. If I had to guess, part of it was because we were seeing more of the second iteration of the campaign, which had been more deadly. Because it was more deadly, there were a few TPKs, or TFMs in the parlance of the Long Stairs, and that meant starting over with a new party that was descending down through the Hellmouth and hitting those first few rooms. They had only gotten past the felheim Landing twice. There had always been some questions about how campaign stuff had been integrated into Aerb, and this just raised further questions. I tried not to think about it, because I had enough on my plate.

We nearly died to a swarm of roaches that tried to fly down our throats. I clamped my mouth shut and chewed up the two that had gotten in, then used Bethel to slice through them with telekinetic force until they were no longer biting me or trying to get in my mouth. It was my first time tasting roach, but Arthur was an old hand at it. When it was done, Henry ate half a pound of rations just trying to get the taste out of his mouth.

We nearly died to a debilitating meme that would have swamped me if I hadn’t had a bit of practice with my own shitty form of linear protocol, doing what I was supposed to do even if I didn’t understand why. We were lucky that it was local and stopped affecting us once we were out of the room.

We did die in a time looping room. We died a lot, actually. They were short loops, kind of like the unicorn loops, but confined to a single room with so many traps that there was barely room for our bodies. It took us more than two hundred loops to make it out the other side unscathed, and once it was over, we were thrust right into a pitched battle against a horde of killer rabbits.

There were boring rooms too, which gave an opportunity to talk.

“There’s a specific way to do it,” said Henry. “You put peanut butter on both pieces of bread, then jelly in the center, and use the peanut butter to kind of seal up a pocket of jelly. It keeps the sandwich from getting soggy.”

“Yeah, I get it,” I said. “But how often are you in a situation where you’re trying to save a PB&J until later?”

“Brown bagging, dude,” replied Henry, shaking his head.

“Henry, what’s thirty-eight times forty-two?” asked Arthur.

Henry’s head exploded into strips of flesh with teeth on the ends of them, which wildly flailed around for a few seconds before Arthur sliced him to ribbons.

“How many rooms was he with us?” I asked as Henry fell to the floor in pieces.

“Seven, I think,” said Arthur. “But I remember him being with us for longer.”

That was the kind of thing that happened in the Long Stairs, and you just had to roll with it, because there would be something new around the corner in another five minutes.

Mixed in with the tests of agility, endurance, fortitude, and combat prowess were the weird and strange rooms, which sometimes had tests, challenges, or mysteries of their own, and sometimes were just set dressing. There were rooms filled with a dozen different complicated terrariums, rooms with strange animals in cages, rooms with books, rooms that looked like caves or forests, rooms with floating white spheres, on and on.

The fun part of the Long Stairs was that you never knew whether one of the rooms that had some interesting focal point would turn into the kind of room where you had to fight some terrible monster.

“You know, I never really liked mimics,” I said, after the books in a library we’d been walking through had come to life. Their covers stuck together, making rustling centipedes. They were, thankfully, quite slow and not all that deadly, though I imagined if you didn’t dodge them when they reared up, a pile of books falling on you from twenty feet up might be enough to cause a concussion.

“You put us in a whole mimic mansion once,” replied Arthur. He had gotten up on some nearby shelves so he could have the advantage of the high ground, while I fought among the stacks. Now that the combat was over, I took my turn to climb up, the better to cross the room.

“Well, yeah,” I replied. “But that was just because I hadn’t really done mimics before. I take the things I hate and do my own, good version of them.”

“These aren’t even mimics,” said Arthur, looking at the corpses.

“Sure they are,” I replied.

“It’s just camouflage,” he said. “Is a chameleon a mimic? Is a stick bug a mimic?”

“I mean,” I said. “We’d have to define terms, and you know I hate definition debates.” I looked down at some dead monsters as I leapt from one row of books to the other. “What would you call these things, if you had to give them a name?”

“Bookworms, obviously,” he replied.

“Fuck, that’s terrible,” I said, then I started laughing.

“Is that not what you intended when you made those things?” he asked, looking mildly surprised.

“I’ve got no idea,” I said. “I don’t remember coming up with them. But it does seem like the kind of dumb joke that I’d have included. Or the kind of joke that I didn’t intentionally include, but would be willing to run with once someone pointed it out. I don’t know. That’s a terrible pun though. Hey, did I tell you about the lich’s butler named Terry Phylac?”

And we went on, talking sometimes, resting whenever we had a chance, tending to our wounds, fighting monsters as they came.

“Do you remember Allison?” he asked, as we drank some water from another fountain and watched the toad play in the water. We were running low on supplies, and none of our extradimensional spaces were working. The rooms with food had become a necessity.

“Sure,” I said. I thought for a moment. “When you died, she was one of the people who was really upset about it. I kind of hated it. I mean, she didn’t know you that well, and it was — selfish of me, obviously, to think that I had a monopoly on grief. But yes, I remember her.”

“I’m wondering whether I’ll get a chance to do high school over,” he said. “Or at least finish out the last year.”

“Kind of creepy to be thinking about seventeen-year-old girls as a fifty-five-year-old man,” I said. “No offense.”

“No, I understand where you’re coming from,” he replied. “I’m just thinking about roads not taken, things that I wasn’t capable of doing back then. It just felt impossible to talk to girls, even though I was friends with so many of them.”

“You were?” I asked.

“I was in a lot more activities than you were,” he said. “Mei in mock trial, Allison in yearbook, Chelsea in math club … there’s something pathetic about having a crush on anyone who shows you even the slightest bit of attention, but that’s who I was. I can’t imagine now that I would have any interest at all in someone half my age, or a third my age, but at the time, or if I could do it over? I’d have been more bold. Boldness is rewarded.”

“And youth is wasted on the young,” I added, nodding. “But why Allison?”

“I don’t know,” he said. “Just an idle thought. I told you that it was, essentially, my job to think about high school for the last thirty years, but really, that’s not quite true. Allison, Chelsea, Mei … they were just a few of the people who never showed up. It was you, Reimer, Craig, Tom, and Tiff, for the most part.”

“And Maddie,” I said.

“Sure, her too,” he replied. “So when I think about going back to high school, finishing that final year before going to college, I tend to think about all the things that I haven’t already spent ages on. I never got to know Allison, nor some mirror reflection of her, nor even an allusion to her existence.”

“Hrm,” I said. “Then you’re probably also saying that you won’t play D&D with us anymore.”

He laughed. “Of course not. Why the fuck would I?” There was something so relaxed about him now, like he’d slipped back into acting like a teenager again now that his body had reverted.

“Yeah, I can see that,” I said, but I couldn’t help but feel a little bit glum about it.

“Do you still want to play D&D?” asked Arthur.

“I actually made my own game when I was in Aerb, Arches, which I played with my companions,” I said. “And yeah, if we don’t have a bunch of saving the world ahead of us, I want to play with them again.”

He shook his head, but though I’d expected a rebuttal, none came.

A few rooms later, when we were walking through a field of broken glass, he brought up a subject I hadn’t expected.

“What was special about me?” he asked.

“Uh,” I replied. “In what context?”

“You haven’t changed a bit,” he replied. “What I mean is … I don’t think that I would have reacted as strongly, if you had died. We were friends, obviously. I’d have been crushed. But I don’t think I would have gone into a months-long depression about it. So I guess I’m wondering why I was that important to you.”

“Honestly, and I hope this doesn’t come out wrong, I don’t know how much it was about you,” I said. “That’s me speaking with more than a year’s worth of distance and a lot of time to process, and process how I was processing, and introspect and stuff. I think it hit me hard because I felt guilty about being with Tiff and keeping secrets, but it’s also not like I’d never been depressed before. When you died, it sucked, but it was also like it gave me a reason that I hadn’t had before.”

“A reason to be shitty?” he asked.

“That, but also a reason to shut down, to disengage, to let the depression soak into my bones,” I said. “The depression is probably just neurochemicals, but how you deal with the highs and lows, whether you get stuck in these endless cycles of rumination … I don’t know, I think that’s kind of in your power, to some extent. Of course, if you get depressed, you lose the power when you need it the most, so maybe I don’t know what I’m talking about. For me, your death felt like vindication, almost.”

“Vindication of what?” he asked, kicking aside an especially large chunk of glass that looked like it had once been the top to a bottle almost exactly like the one that the locus had once lived in.

“Vindication of atheism and cynicism,” I said. “I’d always thought the world was a bit shit. When you died, it was like ‘Oh, hey, I was right all along, everything and everybody does indeed suck’. It was like getting permission to be bitter and cruel.”

“So the lesson is that I wasn’t that special,” he said. “You’d have done the same if it was Reimer.”

“Maybe,” I said. “I honestly don’t know. After you died, I built you up a lot in my head, and maybe I would have done the same for Reimer.” I shrugged and kicked some glass away, thankful that I had boots that mundane glass couldn’t cut through. “I mean, not to diminish our friendship or anything. You were the person I most enjoyed spending time with. Probably more than half the movies I’ve ever watched in my life were with you. You introduced me to ideas that helped shape me in ways that I’m proud of.”

“You never had much sentimentality on Earth,” said Arthur.

“Maybe I was just worse at verbalizing it,” I said. “Sorry if I’m getting too sappy, but … I really did cherish you as a friend. I just also think that a lot of my reaction to your death was more about me, not about you.”

I was finally to the point where I could say that out loud and not have it feel like a stinging betrayal of our friendship.

Another six rooms later, we found ourselves wading through some unpleasant-smelling muck. There was a lot of it, and our movement was slow by necessity. Arthur had taken the lead and was poking ahead with a stick, making sure that there wasn’t some hidden dropoff that the muck was covering, or alternately, some kind of monster. It was unpleasant, but better than having to go through yet another fight, especially given that we had virtually nothing in the way of magical healing. I was on edge, because it seemed like the perfect setup for an ambush. I had more of the load than he did, including the big candle, which I kept being periodically surprised I was still carrying. I was hoping that it was important, not just a joke. I was, frankly, hoping that it would end the game, rather than being a key piece to defeating the Void Beast, or clear out the hells, or some other struggle that might potentially be my responsibility back on Aerb.

“You’ve managed to present a better argument for staying than anyone else,” he said.

“Thanks, I guess,” I said.

“I’m not turning back though,” he continued.

“I know,” I said. “I’m trying my best to accept that. If we could just — if we could have a week of hanging out or something, it would be an easier pill to swallow.”

“If I went back, I’d have to face the narrative,” said Arthur. “I’d be captive to it for the rest of my life.”

“Maybe,” I said. “Or maybe there's a narrative waiting for you up on Earth. Or maybe I could,” I hesitated. “Fix things.”

“How?” he asked.

I gave the candle I was cradling a skeptical look. I didn’t have an answer.

“I think once you’re gone, the Dungeon Master is done with both of us,” I said. “Granted, that’s a bit of very optimistic thinking on my part.”

“And if I don’t leave?” he asked. “If we decide, at the precipice, to turn around, what will the Dungeon Master you’ve spoken to decide to do with us? Set us free?”

“I don’t know,” I said.

“This isn’t even goodbye,” said Arthur. “There are two of you, aren’t there? One here, with me, and the other on Earth, unscarred and unchanged by Aerb?”

“Unclear,” I said. “It might be that the other Juniper is on the Other Side, or somewhere else, if he exists at all.”

“I was like a brother to you,” said Arthur. “I understand that. But my own brother, he was much older, and I rarely saw him, except at Christmas and sometimes in the summer, and … Juniper, the relationships we formed in high school were never going to last forever. If I had lived, if I hadn’t died in a car crash, what would the outcome have been? Most likely, we’d have tried to keep in touch, seen each other over the summers while we were at college, if you ended up going to college, and then drifted apart. Maybe we would see each other’s Facebook posts or something.”

“That’s so … grim,” I said. It gave me a deflated feeling. The toad turned slightly to the side and licked my neck, presumably to cheer me up.

“Well, yes,” he said. “From a certain perspective. But it’s also realistic. Do you understand how old I am, how many close friendships I’ve let fade away by this point? There are people I would see again for the first time in a decade and it would be just like old times, but I never mourned that they weren’t a constant presence in my life. There are people I would have dinner with whenever I was in Li’o, people I would send a letter of inquiry to once every six months or so, people who had a presence in my mind but who were not a presence in my life.”

“You’re saying that I shouldn’t have grieved for you,” I said.

“I’m wondering if you learned a lesson at all,” he said. “I’m curious whether your perspective on things has changed in some way, given all that time you spent on Aerb.”

I thought about that for a moment. “Perhaps the lesson is instead that if you wish for someone to come back hard enough, if you lash out at others, then eventually you’ll be swept away to a fantasy world where they’re still alive,” I said. “Though that lesson doesn’t seem like it generalizes well.”

I was doing the thing that Fenn always used to do, deflecting with humor, and I briefly hated myself for it.

“But in point of fact,” he said with a sigh. It was a familiar sigh, the kind he’d used to let out when he was about to make a point that he thought was obvious, or sometimes just to signal that it was obvious as a way of making it seem stronger than it was. In changing his body back to roughly that of a teenager, he sounded so much more like his old self. “We have grown apart, Juniper. Or at the very least, I’ve grown apart from you, even if the reverse hasn’t happened. And I am leaving, never to return. You can come with me, obviously, but you seem adamant that you’re staying.”

“There’s too much work to be done on Aerb,” I said. It felt weak as I said it.

“That’s not the real reason though, is it?” he asked.

“There are lots of reasons,” I replied. “On Aerb, I’m strong, powerful, and important. Aerb matches my aesthetic tastes more than Earth does. I’ve got more friends on Aerb, given all the bridges I burned on Earth.” I shrugged. “And on Earth, who would I have been? Like, let’s say that this is all set up for both of us to return, and I get reduced to who I was then, and all my memories get a factory reset or something. Who would I have ended up becoming? Probably just some loser.”

“Or you’d have found some nice, comfortable life,” said Arthur. “But you always did hate that part of stories where people returned back to the real world.”

“Because it sucks,” I said. “It’s only there because stupid authors think that allowing the fantasy world to actually be better than the real world sends the wrong kind of message to the audience, who are usually children. It’s impolite to say ‘actually, yes, it would be better to be in this fantasy world that doesn’t exist’. And they try to make it bittersweet, instead of just bitter, but — I know, you think it’s immature.”

“Not particularly, no,” he replied. “I think there’s immaturity in thinking that life can only be one way. It’s a very common immaturity, but also a very adult one. On Earth, yes, perhaps I’d have found it immature, because it was a retreat into fantasy, but here, much less so. In fact, we’re opposite sides of the same decision, in a way.”

“We are?” I asked.

“There was a time I tried to make peace with the omnipresence of the narrative in my life,” he said. “When I tried to make peace with everything forever being a set piece or a bit of backstory or a conflict and its resolution. Eventually though, the unreality of it got to me, and I decided that no, I would do my best to escape the narrative rather than live with it. You want to stay on Aerb because you see that it’s a better life. For the same reason, I want to return to Earth.”

We made it to the end of the muck and Arthur went to open the next door, readying himself for a fight and looking at me to make sure that I was ready to go. I gave him a brief nod, and he swung the door open.

We looked at a room carpeted in corpses. It was one of the larger ones, the size of a ballroom, and all of the dead appeared to be fireteam members, wearing the same black combat clothing that was common to them if they didn’t have magical gear on.

“Holy hell,” said Arthur. “How in the world does the government keep something like this quiet?” He hadn’t stepped into the room yet. Corpses, like statues, were prime candidates for coming to life and trying to kill us.

“It’s all the same guy,” I said, once I’d had a chance to look at the corpses. “So just one KIA or MIA that would need to be covered up. I’m not sure whether this all being a single person with hundreds of corpses is better or worse though.”

I moved in, and began searching the nearest corpse for valuables. Like most of the bodies we’d found, it was fresh, still somewhat warm to the touch. Looking around, the cause of death seemed to be different between the bodies. They were very clearly all the same man though, dark-skinned with a moustache.

“Do you remember this one?” asked Arthur.

“No,” I said. “Unless … this might be another time loop room.”

“Elaborate,” said Arthur. He finally stepped into the ballroom. The more I looked around it, the more I thought that was what it was, with chandeliers and high ceilings, and beneath the bodies, in those rare places where they weren’t stacked two or three high, parquet flooring. There were ‘windows’, but rather than having glass, they were painted with outdoor scenes.

“There was a room I made for the players,” I said. “It was a local time loop, like the one we already did, the trap room, but each time through the loop, your body stays behind, until eventually there are hundreds of corpses of you, each from a time you failed.”

“Edgelord,” muttered Arthur.

“Yes, well,” I replied. “It’s probably the most interesting thing I came up with from that time. If this is what it is, then it’s already disarmed.”

The soldier had been well-outfitted, which meant we were close to the Hellmouth, though there was no sign of anyone else from his fireteam, which meant that either he’d gotten separated, or I was wrong about what had created all the identical bodies. I took his ammo and some of his provisions, his mapping book, and then looked through the rest. I pulled out a small bag of pills, which had a sticker affixed to them labeling them as amnestics.

“Memory loss,” I said, looking at them. I wondered what production facility had made them. It wasn’t the kind of thing that had much commercial use. “You think this is your fate?”

“Possibly,” he said. “In a way, I hope so.”

I looked over at him. “You really do?” I asked. “You really just want to hit the reset button on your entire time on Aerb, to undo it so much that you don’t even remember it?”

“I do,” he said. “Even the good memories of Aerb are tainted by how staged everything was. The triumphs were prewritten. The love, the companionship, if any of it ever felt earned, it doesn’t now. And time has passed, more time than a human can stomach, meaning that it all washed away anyhow. Aerb was a cage, and this is my escape. I don’t think I can express how intolerable it all is, and how much I need a way out.”

I wanted to object that he couldn’t know that, that Earth might have just as much narrative, but I’d tried saying that before, and he hadn’t been receptive. He’d cast himself five hundred years into the future; he was right about there being almost nothing or no one for him. He had descendants, but they were so far from removed from him that they might as well have been someone else’s children. At best, what Aerb promised for him was a nostalgia tour, and he could only see that as manipulation. At worst, he’d be right back in the thick of it, fighting demons and Void Beasts and a million other things that were probably waiting in the wings. To him, everything on Aerb was fake, created for him and him alone, and if it was ‘real’, then it was real only in the way that an actor could make you believe their emotions were real.

“I’ve enjoyed visiting with you,” he said, unprompted. “You were the only one that wasn’t a part of my adventures, though your creations were. And it’s been nice to be with someone who shares the deep past.”

He moved over to me and wrapped me in a very unexpected hug. I hugged him back, trying not to feel awkward about it. The room full of corpses of the same guy trapped in endless loops was probably not the best place for it, but I was grateful for it.

“Thanks,” I said. “But you’re still leaving. You’re still going back to Earth.”

“And you’re not coming with me,” he said. “For all that you professed to be torn apart at the thought of my death, for all that you worked to bring me back, for all that, you’re willing to say goodbye and never see me again.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I guess. I suppose when you put it like that, I seem like a pretty crappy friend.”

“No,” he said. “That you think it takes a bad friend to say goodbye is, perhaps, why you’re here.”

We made our way through the corpses, toward one of a dozen doors around the perimeter of the ballroom. The bodies were distributed unevenly, clumped up in places, and we avoided the piles that were big enough that we would have needed to climb. I wondered about the soldier, and what he’d gone through. Most likely there had been a moment of sinking despair when he realized that eventually there would be so many bodies that he would instantly be buried under them when he respawned. Eventually though, he must have made his way out of the cycle.

We opened the door, and faced the largest room we’d seen yet, larger than any other in the Long Stairs. It was completely dark, save for the floodlights that were half a mile away, shining down from a hole that was forty stories up in one small area. Illuminated beneath the floodlights was a demonic version of Stonehenge, looking more like obsidian teeth than anything else.

“Hellmouth,” I said, looking at it. “We’re here.”

“So we are,” said Arthur. He looked at the ‘mouth’, then at the floodlights. The floodlights weren’t a part of the Long Stairs, they had been placed there by the War Department, and there were, I knew, cameras pointing down to look at the huge black stones. Past those floodlights, going up, was an area that humanity, or more specifically, the United States, controlled. This place, Hellmouth, was the last room of the Long Stairs, and it was safe, except for the threat of armed forces rappelling down.

“I thought we had more time,” I said.

“This is it,” said Arthur. He took in a big breath of musty air. “Earth lies beyond.” He looked at me. “You won’t come with me?”

“You won’t stay?” I asked.

He shook his head. “If you’re going back to Aerb, then I hope to hell we never see each other again, no offense. Or if I see you, you’re just a normal teenager on Earth.”

I could feel the sadness welling up inside me. I had been preparing myself for this, and I still wasn’t ready. I was hoping that something, improbably, would change. I watched him as he looked at the Hellmouth, and hoped that he would reconsider.

“Goodbye,” he said. To my surprise, he gave me another hug, and I hugged him back, holding him close for a moment.

“Goodbye,” I said.

He took a steadying breath, then strode forward, dropping his guns and gear as he went. He was the hero of Aerb, the man that had practically been worshiped, his name spoken of in reverent tones, and he had reduced himself to a mostly normal teenager. The crystals in our heads were dormant in Hellmouth, I could feel that. He had his skill with a sword, and wisdom beyond his years, but even that might be stripped away from him. It was, in a sense, death that he was choosing, or at least an afterlife. It was a final escape from a burden that couldn’t be shouldered forever.

I watched the whole time, standing by the door. From my shoulder, the toad croaked, and I took him down to hold in my hands. I started to cry, but only a little, a few salty tears rolling down my cheeks, the kind of crying that could be wiped away and leave no evidence.

All that, for just this.

Eventually Arthur reached the stones, and not too long afterward, an empty metal cage on a cable began descending from up where the floodlights were. It took a long time for it to reach him, but he didn’t move, and I didn’t either. When he stepped up, the cage began moving again, bringing him up. I wished that I could have known what they were saying in the control room, what they were planning for him, but he was half a mile away, barely visible. Eventually, he was past the floodlights, and I couldn’t see him anymore.

I hoped that he and Amaryllis were right, that this was a way for the narrative to end.

I stayed for about half an hour after that. I don’t know what I was waiting for, or what I expected, but there was nothing, no sound from the opening up to Earth, no descending cage, not so much as a whisper.

I felt relieved, but also a little hollow. This was the point where our stories diverged from each other, and if everything went well for him, we would never see each other again, and his story would be of the kind that people had on Earth, rambling and barely coherent. Perhaps there was another Juniper up there, living his normal life, bored and depressed, but it wasn’t me, and if Arthur was friends with him — well, I hoped that whatever the War Department did with him, it wasn’t horrible. I hoped that he got his wish.

I paused once I was through the door and into a new, fresh room, looking back at the stones of Hellmouth, and pulled out the vorpal sword. Arthur wanted to be free, and I wanted him to be free too. I didn’t know whether it would work, or whether it was wise, but I steadied myself and cut the door, trying to cleave it at a metaphysical joint, the place where Earth was connected to the Long Stairs.

I felt something give under the weight of the strike, and Hellmouth disappeared, leaving a black void beyond the cut door frame.

I had worried that doing that was a mistake, or that I would lose my memories of Earth, but no, I had a feeling that what I had tried had worked. The connection between our realms was severed, and there was no going back for either of us. It was, after all, how I would have done things.

“Come on, little buddy,” I said to the still air and the toad I was holding in my hands. “Let’s go home.”

The return journey was about as uneventful as a return journey through the Long Stairs could be. There were tests of strength, skill, wisdom, and knowledge, but I passed them all, and never had any real fear that I wouldn’t. In a way, it felt like the Long Stairs were as subdued as I felt, like an energy they’d possessed had gone out of them.

“Is it done?” Amaryllis asked when I reached the felheim Landing. Whatever had happened in my absence, she seemed to have the situation well under control. Two felheim flanked her, looking like they would pierce me through if I so much as sneezed in her direction.

“Yeah,” I said. I hefted the candle. “Either of you two know what this is?”

The felheim shook their heads.

“Well,” I said. “I didn’t see anything that seemed like a clue about some kind of hidden power, so,” I shrugged. “Let’s hope that this is it, otherwise this was all for,” I was about to say ‘nothing’, but I didn’t actually believe that. “For Arthur, and for me, to the benefit of no one else.”

Amaryllis nodded, and together, we continued on.

We collected Fenn and Raven from the maze Landing. When Raven saw that Arthur wasn’t with us, she broke down into tears, and it took some consoling before we could continue on. She wanted to stay, hoping that he would return for her, then when we said no, she demanded we push forward up the Long Stairs, regardless of the consequences to her health. Fenn rolled her eyes at all that, and given that it had been a few days, I imagined that this was the fourth or fifth time they’d had that argument.

When we got to the crystal people, Grak was waiting for us. He was wearing the same clothes as the crystal people, but from what I could tell, was mostly bored with the wait, and had gone through all the books he’d brought along to read.

When we were making our way through the wet market Landing, Bethel slipped from my finger and resumed her normal humanoid form.

“You were quiet,” I said.

“It was like what I imagine getting drunk and falling asleep must be like,” she said. “I missed most of it. I only hope that I helped.”

“You did,” I said softly.

RDP mandated that I buy something from the market, so I bought a hat for the toad. I wondered quietly what his purpose was, but then decided that he was a locus, and maybe his mere existence was enough to justify him. Not everything needed to have some grand purpose. That was where Uther had gone wrong. Sometimes things just were.

And then, not much more than twenty rooms later, we were out the last door and standing on a platform of bone in the middle of an enormous crater. It was different, but only slightly. It seemed to have rained while we were gone.

I wasted no time in lighting the candle, hoping that it was something good, something that would help with our circumstances, something that would be worth it. There was still the possibility that this would end in one last, unfunny joke, of the kind that the Dungeon Master and I both liked. I watched as the three wicks burned down.

“Why would this work?” asked Raven.

“It could have been anything,” I said, watching the candle burn. “Literally anything.”

“It’s never an entad,” said Raven, though she sounded doubtful.

“It’s not an entad,” said Grak. This was the third or fourth time he’d repeated that. “It looks like a normal candle.”

“So why would this work?” asked Raven.

“Don’t jinx it,” said Fenn.

“It’ll work because it’s over,” I said as I watched the flame. “I did the thing that I think I was put on Aerb to do.” I swallowed, thinking about Uther going off to an uncertain fate. “I said goodbye.”

It happened when the candle was half burned down. The candle was white, and the whiteness began to spread, moving across the bone platform to change its color, then moving through my companions, and the background, and everything else. The sounds of the world around me faded away until I could hear nothing but the pounding of my own heart. Eventually, I was alone in a familiar void of white.

Standing in front of me, as though he’d always been there, was the Dungeon Master. He was wearing a small paper party hat, and as my eyes met his, he blew on a party horn.

Reflection at the End

Chapter Notes

See the end of the chapter for notes

The Dungeon Master looked different. He was still wearing a hoodie. This one said “Dice Girls” on it, and had a d4, d6, d8, d12, and d20, all with legs, arms, and little faces. They were dressed up, each with their own costume. I thought from context they were supposed to be the Spice Girls, but off the top of my head I had no idea what the Spice Girls looked like, and the reference would have been old when I was a baby. The Dungeon Master himself had a goofy grin on his face, and was in better shape than the last time I’d seen him. He’d gotten a haircut, and his beard had been trimmed. When I didn’t respond to his party horn, he blew it again, waggled his eyebrows, then tossed it, and the paper hat, to the side. I might have expected them to vanish, but they just sat there on the white of the void.

“So,” he said.

“So,” I replied.

“Nachlass is a German word,” he said, “It’s used in academia to describe the collection of manuscripts, notes, correspondence, and so on left behind when a scholar dies.”

“Uh,” I said. “Okay?”

“And … ?” he asked.

“And what?” I asked. “Is that supposed to mean something to me?”

“It’s the pun you didn’t get,” he said. “Back in chapter 147.” He looked slightly disappointed. “Oh!” he said, brightening somewhat. He produced, from thin air, the book I’d seen him with earlier, titled Worth the Candle by Juniper Smith. “It’s a present, of sorts.”

I took it from him, not really liking where this was going. “If you’re going to grant me godhood,” I said slowly, “Could you stop time on Aerb or something so that I can maximize how much suffering I’m able to stop?”

“Already done,” he said.

I nodded, then opened the book. It was enormously thick, so thick that it should probably have been split into at least four or five volumes. It took me some time to flip through the chapters and find chapter 147, but eventually I did, and I began to scan it. It seemed to be from my time at Sound and Silence, written from my own perspective, though of course I had no memory of writing it. I started skimming when I didn’t immediately see anything, until eventually I got to the section where I was sitting in Ermaretor’s class. She had procured the use of the Urquhart Stone, which, when you gave it the notes, correspondence, memoranda, and other writing of a person, produced from its black water a sea monster.

“Nachlass … becomes Loch Ness?” I asked. “Loch Ness nachlass?”

The Dungeon Master beamed at me.

I set the book down. “Look, that’s, uh, great, but — is this the end? You said that this was a rule of three thing, that we were only going to meet three times, and I can’t help but notice that this is the fourth time we’re meeting.”

“Ah, all part of a wonderful misdirect,” he said, grinning at me. “See, when you died and went to the hells, you thought that I was gone, but —”

“I really didn’t entertain the idea for too long,” I said. “It was kind of obvious you were still around.” I frowned at him, then picked the book back up and started flipping through it. “Does this book say that I was fooled? Because that’s not accurate.”

“It was a very successful ruse,” he insisted, still seeming quite pleased with himself.

“Last time you weren’t so chipper,” I said, frowning at him. “You seemed kind of like you hated me, or like you were having an off day, or … something.” The Dungeon Master was something that I’d been puzzling over on the return trip down the Long Stairs. I had wondered whether I would ever see him again.

“Yes, but now I’m done,” he replied, still smiling. “Well, except for this part. But overall, I’m done, and I think it’s all worked quite nicely, if not without its warts and bumps. There are so many warts and bumps you’d think that maybe it might need a doctor’s attention, honestly, but it doesn’t matter, done is done. Done is an accomplishment.”

“Okay,” I said, putting the book back down on the floor of the white void, not having found what I wanted, which was … I don’t know. “If Aerb is frozen, then we can start with some answers. We can do the easy stuff first, like having you tell me about the true nature of reality.”

“Sure, let’s start with the explanation that’s simple and clean,” said the Dungeon Master. “I live in a far future world with nearly infinite computing power thanks to technology that’s beyond your ability to understand.”

“So help me understand,” I said. “Boost my intelligence. Or put it into simple, stupid, wrong terms that they would use on the local equivalent of the evening news.”

“Are you going to let me finish?” he asked.

“Fine,” I replied.

“We’ve got computing power and artificial intelligence,” said the Dungeon Master. “Loads of both. All of this has been a simulation run on stellar — powered by the output of a star — hardware millions of light-years from Earth. Your entire life, including your life on what you thought was Earth, was a simulation, one with some corners cut. There was a real Juniper Smith and a real Arthur Blum, and all the others, and I instantiated both of you from all your leftover online data, your postings, your images, all that, including a number of things you wrote or said later in life. The accepted word for which, in my time, is nachlass. In your case I had DNA from an ancestry test you took in your thirties, and in his case I invented DNA given what I knew of him and some forensic genealogy. Much of it was guessing though, and sometimes filling in the gaps with what was compelling rather than what was true.”

I listened patiently, but I wasn’t buying it, partly because of the holes in it, and partly because of the tone he was using, which was a little bit like he was sharing a joke with me.

“Now that it’s all done, I’m giving you the keys to the kingdom and irrevocably forking over my control of a fair chunk of computing power, so much that it will be impossible for you to use it all,” he said. “There will not, unfortunately, be any way for you to break the simulation, nor even explore its boundaries, but you and everything you will have dominion over will be simulated, without limits. The heat death of the universe has been circumvented, by the way, so you don’t even need to worry about that. You and your people will have both eternity and infinity, unless something goes very wrong on the layer above you, but if that happens, you’ll all probably die instantly and peacefully.”

“So,” I said, thinking this over. “I get to run a utopia while there’s a dystopia on the layer above.”

“A dystopia?” he asked, arching an eyebrow.

“Any society that allows mass torture by private citizens is a dystopia, almost by definition,” I said. “And this version of things doesn’t make all that much sense. Arthur got a different deal than I did, but he never got anything like an error message. And you’re saying that you built a game layer in addition to all the other running-a-person stuff, and — look, I just don’t think that you’re telling me the truth.”

“It wouldn’t have to be a dystopia,” said the Dungeon Master. “Maybe what I’m doing is very illegal, but also incredibly difficult to enforce.”

“Sure,” I said. “But I don’t buy it.”

“Well, it’s the easy answer, and perfectly acceptable, I’d think. Does it matter?” he asked. “I’ll stipulate now that there’s no escape from where you are, not for you, or anyone you know. The context of your existence cannot be breached. You’ll never see another trace of errors or limitations. You’ll never have communication from anyone ‘outside’ the context you exist within. That goes for whatever the truth of your situation is, whether it’s a simulation or not. Does it matter whether there’s a dystopia above you?”

“No,” I said. “Conditional on you telling the truth and you being unshakeable about what you’re proposing to do to me, then I think no, a world outside that I can’t do anything about doesn’t substantially change things. If I’m a simulation, which I don’t actually think is the Truth, then it’s something I’ve come to terms with. I’ll make an effort to escape or find the seams anyway, but I know you know that. If there is a dystopia above, it’s the kind of thing I would try not to think about because I was incapable of changing it, and maybe, over time, I would succeed in not having it nag at me. I guess maybe it might affect time discounting or something, since if I thought the world might end in a decade I would act differently than if I thought it would go on forever.”

The Dungeon Master waved away that thought as needlessly pedantic.

“But I don’t know why you’re selling me a lie,” I said. “If I accept that it doesn’t matter, why not tell me the truth?”

“The truth is that I made the simulation stuff up,” said the Dungeon Master. “There is no simulation.”

“And the error messages?” I asked. “I mean, I think Arthur was right, those are fake whether or not it was a simulation. They were too blatant and the error output shouldn’t have been like that, especially given the sophistication of everything else. I’d like an explanation as to why they were there at all.” I had my own guesses about that.

“Think about the differences in how you and Arthur perceived your existence on Aerb,” said the Dungeon Master. “Arthur was always questioning the nature of his reality. If I told you, upfront, that it was all fake, I was hopeful it would help you to come to the conclusion that you came to, that fake or not fake, it doesn’t matter. Better to have an existential crisis early on than dragging it out. You were already having thoughts that it was a simulation right from the start, and how couldn’t you, with the game overlay? In retrospect, I kind of smacked you with it, maybe a bit too hard. Both times, with the big red error messages, it was a good place for them though, because I also needed to communicate something to you.”

“Which was?” I asked. I tried to think like him, which mostly meant thinking like myself. “Let me guess, the first time, it was that you cared about keeping me as a Juniper, that there was some integrity to this thing, the second time, it was because you wanted me to know you saved me?”

He nodded.

“Okay, but then what is the reality of my situation?” I asked. “Obviously I’m your plaything, like Arthur was, but a different kind of plaything.”

“Are you asking what the point of the situation was?” he asked, tapping his foot.

“No,” I said. “I’ll ask that later. I’m asking what’s capital-R Real.”

“I’m a god, of a sort, in this context,” he said. “I make worlds. I made this world for my own purposes, and I put Arthur and then you into it because I had a particular set of whims and needs. When I leave, I vow to leave for good, and this world can keep rolling on forever. That’s a much more true version of reality. And really, that’s so similar to the simulation version that it seems to me like it shouldn’t matter to you.”

“But it’s not the truth,” I said, fidgeting.

“I can’t tell you the truth,” he said. “You wouldn’t understand it, and I know that because I’ve tried telling you before, in a discarded timeline. So in this, the canonical timeline, I’m just not going to tell you.”

Discarded timelines made me real uneasy. “Can you tell me why I don’t understand?” I asked.

“It’s incompatible with your qualia,” he replied.

“Because my qualia aren’t real?” I asked.

“They’re real within this context,” he said. “But I exist outside of this context.” He looked down at himself. “This is just a context-crossing shell.”

“Sure, fine,” I said. This was illuminating nothing. “I just want you to try. I want you to explain it as plainly and simply as you can. If I don’t understand it, fine, but I want the Truth.”

The Dungeon Master hesitated, as though he didn’t want to say it. “Fine, we’ll try this again. You’re a character in a novel,” he said.

I thought about that for a moment, turning it over in my head. “And you mean that literally?” I asked. “You don’t mean it in the sense of, ‘you’re like a character in a novel’, in the sense that, yes, you created me, and my environs, and you in some sense dictate, or predict, or set up my actions, and you’re like an author? You mean actually, for real?”

“Yes,” he replied, nodding.

“Nah,” I said. “That’s nonsense. I know you said that I would say that, so congratulations on being right, but it just — I do have qualia. I’m not a p-zombie. I can see you, touch you, feel you. I have memories of so many things. I can feel my tongue in my mouth. I’d more easily believe that you’re from the far future, simulating me and everything else, or that I’m a brain you put in a jar and hooked up to wires.”

“I can’t prove it to you,” he said. “That’s what I mean about context. You’re not real, and I can’t take you out of there to show you that you aren’t real. It’s words on a page. What’s real are the emotions and thoughts that those words can evoke in people, and specifically, that they evoked in me. Those are real, which were the whole point of this, for me. That’s why your story was fundamentally about reality, a story about stories, about what we choose to take from fiction. Do you see the duality of you and Arthur? He rejected the narratives. He rejected the cycles. You, instead, answered ‘mu’. You said that it didn’t matter, that even if it wasn’t real, it was real to you, and that was enough. You and me, we arrived at the same point. I know it isn’t real. I know that. But to revel in the glory of our own creation anyhow, to make it matter, that’s the whole point.” He seemed to really mean it. The jokingness was stripped away and there was something in his eyes, an intensity.

“I’m sorry,” I said. “It’s just … far more likely that there really is some way to have infinite computing power, or enough that at the simulation fidelity you’re running it at can trick someone into thinking it’s infinite, and Earth and Aerb are running on some monstrously powerful hardware, if you’re running or ran Earth at all. All the stuff you’re saying about it being a story makes more sense if that’s the case. That you think I’m not real — if you’re going to leave me alone to be god, then I don’t care, I’m not going to sit here and try to convince you that I really do experience emotion and sensation and all that jazz.”

“I know,” he said. “I wanted to avoid it, but there you go, that’s the truth, and you’ve rejected it.”

I let out a sigh, feeling frustrated. “Well then, now I’d like to know the whys.”

“Ah,” he replied. He tapped his foot. “I suppose it all started as a misguided form of therapy.”

“Therapy,” I said. It was an answer that I’d been half-expecting. “Therapy? I was tortured, how was that therapy? I was literally murdered. I was raped, how —”

“Oh, don’t be so self-centered,” he said. “Not therapy for you, therapy for me. You’re not the most important person in this world, I am.”

I paused for a moment. “Well?” I asked. “Did it work?”

“More or less,” he replied, shrugging. “I’d say it worked more than it didn’t work.”

I closed my eyes, thinking, trying to piece things together. “Okay,” I said. “So do I need to do a reconstruction of events on my own, or can you just give it to me?”

“Hmm,” he said. “I suppose I’ll throw you a bone. Do you mind if we get a bit more comfortable though?” Without waiting to hear a response, he summoned a couch from nowhere for me, and a comfy chair for himself. For a moment, I wanted to stay standing, just on principle, but I sat, and it was one of the most comfortable pieces of furniture I’d ever sat on, perfectly contoured to my body.

The Dungeon Master leaned back. “It started with Arthur, naturally. Or perhaps I should say it started with a boy who wasn’t Arthur, who died in that liminal time just before our adulthood. He was a close friend of mine. It haunted me for a long time. I thought to myself one night that I needed to exorcise my demons somehow, or at least find comfort, and I’d always had an interest in creating worlds, so I thought to myself, why not? And thus, a primitive version of Aerb was formed, and Arthur was thrust into it.”

“But, no,” I said. “Arthur wasn’t — I’m not you, and Arthur wasn’t actually your friend. Right?”

“True enough,” replied the Dungeon Master. “There’s a feeling we sometimes get, and here I don’t mean the general we, but we specifically, me and you, Juniper Smith and whatever you want to call me — there’s a feeling of coming back to something in search of the way it made us feel, and realizing that it doesn’t produce that emotion for us anymore. We do this constantly. The most distinct time you felt that feeling of not-feeling was reading through the Pippi Longstocking books. You’d read them when you were young, and you had one of your first crushes, on Pippi. Then when reading them again at fifteen, you realized that you’d been completely wrong. Pippi Longstocking was, in fact, an annoying child. You realized that the feeling you’d been chasing by cracking those books again could never be reproduced by them.” He shook his head. “The self-reflection made the not-feeling stronger, because it wasn’t just a momentary disappointment, it was a disappointment that stretched into the future, a realization that you’d never get the feeling back, not in that way, that the well you’d gotten such sweet water from was now and forever dry.” He paused. “It’s a feeling that comes from indulging in nostalgia and having the memory crumple and the emotions fail to appear. The neurons don’t fire and the brain chemicals don’t get released. It’s like trying to light a firecracker a second time, hoping that it will cause the same explosion.”

“And so you do what I did?” I asked. “You write your own Pippi Longstocking books?” This was normally something so embarrassing that I would never speak a word of it to anyone, but I knew that the Dungeon Master knew. The kinds of books that a fifteen-year-old Juniper wrote about Pippi Longstocking while trying to produce the feeling of an early childhood crush were, obviously, an affront to good taste and would probably bring legal action from the estate of Astrid Lindgren, even if I had aged Pippi up.

The Dungeon Master nodded. “Your entire group was made to evoke certain feelings in me,” he said. “If I had used the real people, my real friends, striving for accuracy, I don’t believe I would have gotten as much from it. And I made you to be a stand-in for me, not necessarily accurate to how I was, but able to bring forward certain emotions in me. You are me, heightened in some ways, sanded down in others, changed and warped to serve the purpose. True, though, to my perceptions.” He looked at me, as though examining his work, and I felt uncomfortable in my seat.

“Anyway,” he said. “To get back to the timeline, I created Aerb, and Arthur, and the people he’d known, and the town he’d lived in, hoping that some new life for Arthur would help to soothe me.”

“You didn’t think of him as real,” I said.

“I didn’t,” replied the Dungeon Master. “I don’t. I don’t think of you as real either. I don’t think of this shell as real, or this conversation as real. But just because a thing isn’t ‘real’ doesn’t mean that it can’t have its impacts. You’re a dungeon master, you know that better than most.” Again there was something like pleading in his eyes, as though wishing it might make me understand. “It doesn’t mean that it’s ineffective therapy.”

“Maybe you should, I dunno, talk to a real therapist, if they have them where you are?” I asked. “I’m not being flippant, I really think maybe that would help.”

“Sure, sure,” he replied. “At any rate, things with Arthur went swimmingly. It was everything that I’d wanted when I started, barring those hiccups at the beginning, which we’ve already gone over. Arthur defeating the Dark King with his motley crew was just,” he made the ‘chef’s kiss’ gesture. “And then, as discussed, I wanted more, and more, and more. Early on it was fairly simple, but the premise began to wear thin, and one day, out of the blue, the metafictional elements started cropping up.”

“No,” I said. “The metafictional elements were always there, right from the start. You were inserting him into a campaign world that I had come up with.”

“Perhaps we should sidestep a definitional debate,” said the Dungeon Master. “I know you hate those. When I say ‘metafictional’, I don’t mean characters from your campaigns, or worldbuilding, or anything like that. All that could have been some form of prophecy. Uther recognizing things doesn’t make for metafiction, not in any real sense. I mean the narrative itself.”

“Ah,” I said. “So when you say it came out of the blue, you don’t mean him realizing that it was all bits and pieces of campaigns he’d played, you mean he realized that he was a part of a story, or something like it,” I said. And it was clear that we were in stories, and had been, just not what kind of substrate those stories lived in. I was still banking on hypercomplex far-future simulation, but it seemed like I wasn’t going to get an answer.

The Dungeon Master nodded. “It wasn’t right away, or all at once, but the thoughts were there, and they grew with time. Part of it was that I’d been a bit lazy about how I’d structured things, and the solutions that I allowed to happen at particular plot points. There was all kinds of unintentional evidence. But once the seed of the metaplot was there, it kept growing, and I indulged it in various ways. The schlossvolk — I always hated the name and said so as Vervain, but he was insistent, and there was an Arthurness to the name — were a wrinkle in the whole thing, entities that provided a diegetic explanation for some laziness on my part. Ironically, the schlossvolk themselves had been retroactively added into the world. I did that a lot, back in the day. The world of Aerb wasn’t built all at once, it was built over the course of a decade of Arthur’s life. At a certain point, I mostly stopped making new things and allowed it to all play out.”

There were elements of this story that didn’t sound quite right, or that I thought were more reflections of how he thought about things than whatever the seemingly irrelevant truth of reality was. I tried to put myself in his mindset, thinking about things like a dungeon master thought about his games, and that helped, somewhat. He thought that Arthur wasn’t real, but he didn’t have it in him to curb Arthur, to make Arthur do or say things that were unArthurlike. He felt it important that I was me, that Amaryllis was Amaryllis, and that we weren’t some puppets whose minds were changed on a whim. He had opinions on the integrity of the thing.

“It wasn’t pleasant for him,” I said.

“I know,” nodded the Dungeon Master. “And more importantly, it wasn’t particularly pleasant for me, either.”

“Then why?” I asked, clenching a fist. “Why put both of you through that? I could understand if you thought he wasn’t real, but if you are, or whatever is behind this shell in some other context or … whatever — why do that to yourself?”

He scoffed. “You’re no stranger to doing things that make you and others unhappy. But to be honest,” replied the Dungeon Master. “In the end, I was just letting things run without direct involvement on my part. They were still real in his context, they happened, but they were less real for me. I had set up the Long Stairs as a way out for him, and once he went in the first time, I knew he would eventually be back. When Vervain died, that was the last I really paid much attention to it. I knew the path Arthur would take. I wanted him to take it.”

“You abandoned the world,” I said. “Except … not, because exclusions were still happening, and there’s five hundred years of history, and I know that it has my mark on it, which means your mark.”

“Oh, once he was gone, I was setting up for you, and even a bit before that,” said the Dungeon Master. “Obviously. Where Arthur’s placement on Aerb was a way for me to find some comfort in his death, or to reject his death entirely, your placement on Aerb was a way for me to more directly deal with some of my problems, and to relive a period of my life that had already passed. I didn’t need to do the growing that you needed to do, but the reflection on those times and their emotional truths — it was helpful, I think, though I’m sure you don’t care in the slightest.”

“I do care,” I said. “I don’t wish pain on others.”

“You do, sometimes,” said the Dungeon Master, shrugging. “But I appreciate the sentiment nonetheless.”

“So,” I said. “I had a shitty childhood because you had a shitty childhood, and I dated Tiff because you dated Tiff, and my life is just an echo of yours. Do I have that right?”

He nodded. “Of course, all your friends were inventions of my own, so there was no Tiff until I created her. The Tiff you knew was created to be an emotionally true version of a girl I dated in high school. That girl, as she actually was, if I could have recreated her at all, wouldn’t have fit my purposes quite right. I wouldn’t have gotten the same feelings out of it.”

He’d completely abandoned the pretense that I had been a real person from the real Earth. “And Maddie?” I asked.

“Is that hard for you to figure out?” asked the Dungeon Master. “Do you need me to connect the dots? Different details, but emotionally true. Legal, in my case, but still something that I carry deep regrets about.”

“So you are from Earth,” I said. “And from, or invested in, local time. I mean, even if you’re from the subjective future —” But I knew that wasn’t quite right either.

“Or I’m a god of unimaginable power, and speaking to you in a way that you would understand, for purposes that are too obtuse for you to fathom,” he said with a sigh. “Perhaps my true form is something like a giant crab, and I just have a fascination with these two-legged beings I invented called humans. Perhaps this is all translation from something higher or different.”

I paused. “Is it?”

The Dungeon Master rolled his eyes. “If you want to know how and what, then I’m not going to answer that again. It’s incoherent in this context, even if it makes sense from the context I’m from. If you want to know why, then I’m doing my best to answer that right now. From my perspective, the why is what’s important, and it’s also the part that I wanted to talk to you about. This is the end, Juniper. You’re going to be in charge of designing a paradise. It’s a good ending for you. I want you to know why all this happened.”

“Fine,” I said. “And if this whole thing was some kind of therapy that you were attempting to create for yourself, whether I was mined from the past or directly created, then that applies to Aerb too? All those adventures, did they have some literal or metaphorical relevance to you?”

“It wasn’t even that many adventures,” he said. “But yes, they did. You already knew that though, didn’t you? You and Amaryllis worked out that many of the elements you came across had some specific or personal meaning to you. By association, they had specific or personal meaning to me.”

“Except there was also stuff that didn’t have any specific meaning to me,” I said. “All that shit with Fallatehr, did that have meaning to you?”

“Yes,” he replied. “A betrayal I suffered, and how I dealt with it. It was the feeling of being understandably unable to trust, and having that make things worse.”

“Oh,” I said. “Huh.” That wasn’t quite my interpretation of how things had gone down. “But then — both my time on Earth and my time on Aerb were just for you to get your kicks?”

“That’s reductive,” he said, frowning at me. “It’s not a lossless compression of what I was doing. But sure, if you want to say that.”

“Okay,” I said. “But then what happened to you in college, or the context-whatever equivalent of college you went through? Surely not a giant monster you had to use several types of magic to murder with the help of your sentient house that ended up raping you, right?”

“Metaphorically,” he replied, and then seemed about to leave it at that before reconsidering. “I’m sorry about how things went with Bethel.”

“‘How things went’?” I asked. I wasn’t sure I wanted him to say it out loud, but it felt like a coward’s move not to be plain about it.

“I doubt that you’ll believe me, but I never intended it to happen. That said, I didn’t revise it, and I didn’t stop it, so …” he shrugged. “It probably won’t help for you to know that it was extremely difficult and emotional for me.” He was right. “I’m sure you’ll be a better god than me, because our aims are different. You’re inside the context where this is real, and I’m not.”

“Sure,” I said. “Whatever, I don’t want to get into how much of a shit you are, it’ll just make me mad.” When I wasn’t thinking about it, I could almost like him, or at least empathize. We shared sensibilities.

“Then what else is left?” he asked. “So far as I’m concerned, we’re mostly done. I’ll show you around, but if you realize that I made my mistakes with Arthur, and that this was all about me as a person, then I don’t think there’s much left.”

“So the ‘why me’ question was always just ‘you did this to yourself’?” I asked.

“More or less,” he replied. “Of course, you are your own person.” He paused, as if thinking about whether what he’d just said was true. “Now then, can we start the tour?”

“What happened to Arthur?” I asked.

“That’s a dangerous question to ask me, after all that work of saying goodbye,” replied the Dungeon Master, clucking his tongue. “Here’s what I decided on: Arthur got to go back home and live his life. This wasn’t the first time the War Department had to deal with someone like him, so they gave him some amnestics, wiped away most of his memories, and when he died in Kansas, they were there, waiting, and switched the dead Arthur for the living one. All in accordance with RDP. He would then wake up, and go through some reorientation, maybe have a few good memories from Aerb, and otherwise, live as normal. Nothing that couldn’t be chalked up to the extended coma or vivid dreams. His skills are gone, as is his Knack. The War Department quietly ceases to exist not long afterward. And that’s it. That’s as far as I go.”

I was silent for a moment. “That’s time travel,” I said.

“I’m a fucking god, Juniper, I do whatever the fuck I want,” replied the Dungeon Master. “I am completely capable of time travel. I’m capable of reshaping reality to my whims.” He was more flippant about it than angry. “If I want to be a big old softie about it, and make it so the gentle return happens, rather than the more realistic thing of him being detained for quite a bit and released into WITSEC, never able to truly come back to the life I’d denied him for so long — you understand that his stories were much more high fantasy, and didn’t need to follow the rules of realism so strictly as yours. In an Arthur story, he was right, the ending for him was a return to the world he’d known, stripping everything of Aerb away from him except some of the growth and the lessons, ending up almost exactly where he’d started.”

“Yeah,” I said. “Sure. But … if I want to know what happens next, then you want to know what happens next, right? I mean, I made peace, kind of, but I still want to know. So that means you still want to know.”

“Of course I want to know what happens next,” he replied. “I had this great idea, which was that the War Department might keep tabs on people like him, and one day he might discover his trackers, or his Knack might start coming back, and perhaps his memories could start to return, without him being so beleaguered by it all. I had a thought that an undercover operative might befriend him under false pretenses, and then she might fall in love with him in spite of that, and …” he slowed down, probably because of the horrified look on my face. “You understand why I’m leaving it where it is, right?”

I nodded.

“You’re cut off from Earth,” he said. “It’s on a different server cluster, if that analogy tracks. You’re free to recreate it, but I know that you won’t. That means you could recreate Arthur. Again, I know that you won’t.”

“No,” I said softly. “I won’t.”

“Now did you want to take the tour?” he asked, brightening.

I looked around the white void. The only notable features were me, him, the party hat and party horn, the couch and chair, and the enormous book. “Sure,” I said.

The Dungeon Master waved a hand, and a wall of the void opened up. It was a cozy tavern, and there were a few people around. I recognized only one of them, the Layman, who was throwing peanuts up into the air and catching them in his mouth. Aside from the Layman, there was a lot of costuming going on, and none of it really seemed to mesh very well. My eyes went to a table that appeared to have a cactus person sitting at it, along with a large and varied party of other people. One of them, apparently a human, glanced my way, and I froze in place.

“Who the fuck is that?” I asked, pointing at the guy. He looked a bit too much like me, which is to say he looked exactly like me.

The guy stood up from his seat and came over to me. He was wearing sintered armor and giving me a skeptical look, and once he was done sizing me up, he gave the Dungeon Master a sigh.

“Juniper Smith,” he said, holding out his hand to me.

I shook his hand. “You mean that your name is also Juniper Smith?”

He nodded. “I’m the person you displaced.”

I looked over at the Dungeon Master. “Wait, this is the Aerb version of Juniper? Is this going to be a turtles-all-the-way-down kind of thing, where there’s another Juniper that he displaced?”

“No, nothing like that,” replied the Dungeon Master. “You see, about half the time when you dream-skewer, the displaced person doesn’t get overwritten, they get pushed out somewhere, and that place is the Other Side, where they’re temporarily without a body until they learn a bit of formation magic, which allows them to construct their body again, Jon Osterman style.”

“I don’t know who that is,” said Aerb Juniper.

“A lot of the references were lost on this poor, inferior Juniper,” said the Dungeon Master. The poor, inferior Juniper remained stoic, as though he was used to this kind of abuse. “Anyway, he was bumming around the Other Side, which should really be called the B-side, but the two of you never ended up running into each other, so oh well. Part of tabletop games is not pushing the players too hard and allowing a fertile plot thread to hang itself, and tabletop games were the feel I was going for, as you correctly intuited. He did manage to defeat the Union Empire though.”

“We’re cool?” B-side Juniper asked me.

“Sure, we’re cool,” I said with a shrug. I looked at the Dungeon Master. “I don’t really get why he’s here.”

“He finished early,” said the Dungeon Master. “I had some trouble lining things up, and didn’t want to abuse the timeline anymore, so I let him chill here.” He looked at B-side Juniper. “You can sit back down.”

B-side Juniper shrugged, then went back to his table, seating himself next to the cactus.

“So what happens to him?” I asked. “I mean, if I was playing for godhood, then are we going to be co-gods?”

“Not unless you want to,” said the Dungeon Master. “No, the Union Empire was a credible threat to the Empire of Common Cause. He was trying to stop them from unleashing a superweapon, and also secure a path home for himself, all of which he did. Of course, it was all made moot a week later, which I found absolutely hilarious.” He pointed over at the table and lowered his voice. “Those are his companions. Guess which ones he’s had sex with.”

Aside from the cactus person, there was an anthropomorphic otter, a non-anthropomorphic octopus, a woman whose hair seemed to be made up of precious gems, a fairly normal halfling, and a woman who flickered and changed appearance whenever I tried to look directly at her.

I frowned. “I don’t really think it’s appropriate to speculate on —”

“All of them,” replied the Dungeon Master. He seemed a bit too giddy about it for my tastes.

“So?” I asked. “I mean, I don’t think we should judge people for —”

“Neither do I, obviously,” he said. “But it’s nice to show someone something that they have trouble admitting about themselves.”

“Look, the whole harem thing,” I began.

“There were things you needed to learn about how you view and deal with women,” he said. “I don’t think we got it all out of your system, but I did put in some effort. And obviously much of it was for my benefit as well, to help me learn, grow, and process.”

“Sure,” I said. “Fine. Or you were just watching and getting off on it, with a thin veneer of deconstruction and learning a lesson.” I wondered whether he’d watched me have sex, and how often, if he’d been staring over my shoulder when I jerked off.

“The world may never know,” replied the Dungeon Master. “Anyway, there’s the Layman, who you met, there’s the Scribe, who hand-writes all the notes, there’s the Architect,” pointing to a tall guy in a rumpled suit, “There’s the Warden,” a woman whose whole aesthetic seemed to be chains, a little on the nose for my tastes. “Oh, and there’s the Actor.” He waved at a very plain looking man, also in a suit, but much more handsome, in a Hollywood kind of way.

“Juniper!” called the Actor, coming forward. “A pleasure to meet you. Here’s my card, if you need anything.” He produced a crisp eggshell white card from his pocket, and I took it from him, somewhat dumbfounded. On one side, it said ‘Thespian’. The other side was blank.

“And your role is … ?” I asked.

“Oh, anything that’s needed,” he said. “Whenever you need a character, they can be played by me.”

I looked at the Dungeon Master. “Meaning?” I asked.

“He’s useful,” shrugged the Dungeon Master. “In case you wanted to have people who weren’t people, who were just happily acting like they were, say, in pain, or in love, without actually being those things.”

“And did you do that?” I asked.

“No,” replied the Dungeon Master. “Only as Vervain, when I wasn’t speaking and acting as Vervain myself. Everyone else was real.”

“Even the hells?” I asked. “Because … shit, that’s a lot of people that will need therapy. That’s horrible. Is there any way you could,” I paused.

“Yes?” he asked.

“Retroactively make it so that,” I paused again. “I don’t want you to erase real people, but is it possible that you could, um, in your context, outside of time, maybe make it so the hells didn’t exist?”

“No,” replied the Dungeon Master. “They’re an important part of the story.”

“Then the Thespian, the Actor,” I said. “Could you make it so that he was playing the part?”

“Of whom?” asked the Dungeon Master, raising an eyebrow.

“Everyone in the hells except the members of my party, when we were there,” I said. “The infernals, and the tortured. Again, I don’t want to erase anyone’s experience from existence, but if there’s a way for it to have not happened without doing that, if you’re a god who can bend reality from a perspective outside time, then … that’s my request.”

“Sure,” he said with a shrug. “Done. No one in the hells was ever real, except for the people involved in rescuing you from it.”

“Sorry, this is making my head hurt,” I said. I really hoped what I’d asked him to do was the right thing.

“I’m not being intentionally confusing,” said the Dungeon Master. “I understand it’s a lot though. But there’s something I want to show you that I think you will like.” He opened a door in the side of the tavern, and walked us out into a green space that seemed to go on for quite a while, with shrubs and grasses and trees. Sitting in the middle of it was a small, picturesque cottage.

“What is this?” I asked.

“It’s something I think you’ll like, I said that already,” replied the Dungeon Master.

“You know that what I want most of all is to go back to Aerb and start on fixing things with my phenomenal cosmic powers, right?” I asked as I followed behind him. “I don’t need to see behind the scenes.”

“Just a few more things, I promise,” he said. He opened the door without knocking, and I reluctantly followed him in. It was a fairly open place, small and cozy but also with a fair amount of room to move around. I couldn’t see any sign of a kitchen or bathroom, it was just a bed, a sofa, and a desk with a small computer on it. There was a man sitting at the computer, and I could tell right away he was a Juniper, but sitting on the couch was someone I hadn’t expected to be there in the slightest: Fenn.

She was dressed in a green tank top and some black athletic shorts, eating cheesy puffs. She stood up when I came in, setting the bag to the side, and licked her fingers quickly before coming forward.

“You’re here!” she said.

“Fenn?” I asked.

“Sup?” she asked. She came forward and wrapped me in a hug. “I’m not fully caught up, but I know you’ve been through some shit. Congrats on the win.”

I looked at the Dungeon Master. “What is this, please?”

“Fenn died,” he replied. “She was always meant to die, it was part of how I’d envisioned things happening. She was expendable, really.” Fenn pouted. “I’d originally meant for it to happen when she got cut in half in the forest and hastily put back together, but you came up with the transfusion thing, and I thought, well, let’s just let it roll, that’s fair play.”

“She was fated to die,” I said slowly. “There was no way of avoiding it?”

“Maybe,” he replied. “Nothing is set in stone. You removed her from the poison last, and you could have chosen differently. I do try to play fair, the majority of the time, same as you. Fel Seed being one obvious exception.”

“Who?” I asked.

Fenn was grinning. “But as it turns out, my superpower isn’t arrows, it’s that when I die, I get sent to heaven! I am, no shit, the only person on Aerb to ever get into heaven.”

“You came back to life though,” I said, looking her up and down.

“She wasn’t supposed to do that,” said the Dungeon Master. “But after you died, Amaryllis had this plan to bring you back, and logically, there was no way she wouldn’t bring Fenn back too. I thought about fudging it, or stopping it, but,” he shrugged. “I’ve been trying to abide by good DMing principles, where possible. That’s part of why I’m showing you what I’m showing you, it’s not just to display the scraps of plans that never came to fruition, which I know you hate.” He turned to regard Fenn. “Fenn coming back to life left us with a problem though, because this Fenn had been sitting around in heaven for almost three years. I thought for a moment about sending her back down anyway, but the timing was off for it, so with her consent, I made a copy.”

“She’s going to be pissed off when she learns about that,” said Fenn, clucking her tongue. “In my defense, I was told that you might have an easier time if you had a Fenn with you. A better chance of success.”

“So there was a chance I would fail?” I asked, looking at the Dungeon Master.

“That’s what he said,” replied Fenn. “I don’t believe a damned word of it.”

“And you’ve just been … living here?” I asked Fenn. “Just hanging out?”

“Oh, sure,” she said. She held up her fingers. “Check ‘em out.”

I looked at her hand and saw nothing. “What am I seeing?”

“I was eating cheese puffs,” she said. “And I got to lick my fingers clean, but then there was nothing left on them, no stickiness or anything. It’s heaven!”

“That’s the Narrator,” said the Dungeon Master, gesturing at the Juniper behind the computer. He gave a lazy wave without looking back at me. He seemed focused on typing. “In case you were wondering. It’s actually fairly interesting how I conceptualized him as being — alright, you don’t care, I understand.”

“So there are two Fenns?” I asked.

“We’re gonna bang,” said Fenn. “Me and the clone, not you and me, sorry, I can see where you’d find that confusing.” She must have seen my expression. “Me and the Narrator Juniper are already hooking up, in case that wasn’t clear from us living in the same cottage and sharing a bed.”

I stared at her.

“I’m seeing that it wasn’t clear,” said Fenn. “It happened not too long after I moved in. He’s great.”

“But,” I said. “We broke up.”

“Right,” said Fenn. “And I was therefore free to date other people.” She gestured at Narrator Juniper, who seemed like he was an exact copy of me.

“He’s not an exact copy of you,” said the Dungeon Master, possibly reading my mind. “He’s you, with some extra perspective on what’s going on, a little bit of future sight, better recall of the past, and a few other tweaks. Oh, he’s also a better writer, obviously, since that’s his main job.”

“Huh,” I said. I looked back at Fenn. “And … that was enough?”

“Narrator Juniper understood our problems,” said Fenn. “I mean, he feels what you feel, but he’s got extra perspective, and during some downtime, he went through and pointed out all the parts of the story that showed just how right I was. And you know me, if someone shows me even the slightest bit of positive attention, I fall head over heels.”

“Huh,” I said again.

“But the game’s all done now, so I guess I’ll be seeing you around,” said Fenn. “Don’t be a stranger.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I … guess I won’t be.”

“So,” said the Dungeon Master as the cottage was ripped away and we were back in the white void together. “I guess all that’s left is for me to hand you the keys.” He had literal keys in his hand.

I took them from him, not wanting to wait. They felt solid and real in my hand, one final piece of loot, one final entad. “Not that I want to do anything with them, but you’re not going to make me fight the Void Beast? Or go fight the hells?”

“Nope,” he replied. “You were never going to beat the Void Beast. I mean, it’s a metaphor for various coordination problems, most notably global warming, as you know, so what does it mean if you punch it in the face hard enough to kill it? I mean, on the object level, maybe that would be cool, but it wouldn’t work with the metaphor. I never built in a solution for that one. It was always there to end the world at some point. Sacrificing pieces of Aerb to slow it was the best you could do, short of an autocratic government that was somehow capable enough to stop everyone from all over the world from using void tools, which seems both horrifying and farfetched to me.”

“But,” I said. “That means you have global warming outside of here? In that other context you live in? There are other people for you to have coordination problems with?”

“Sure,” he replied.

I frowned, not sure what to make of that. “And the hells were also some kind of metaphor?” I asked.

“For the constant endless suffering of the world,” he said. “The senseless cruelty and pain of everyday existence for most people. But you didn’t want them to exist, and I knew that from the start, so they were never as real as you are. All that suffering has never actually happened except for its emotional truth and the time we spent ruminating on it. It’s somewhat a load off my mind.”

“You’re welcome, I guess,” I said, looking down at the keys.

“You can’t use them until I’m gone,” he said. “They’re safe, they do what you mean. No tricks, no traps, just the chance to build a paradise.”

“Not that I haven’t enjoyed the chat,” I said. “Or this weird place you’ve set up with aspects of yourself and a surplus Fenn. But I kind of want to get started on my tenure as god.”

“Of course,” he replied. He gave me a salute. “Good luck, Juniper.”

“Thanks,” I said. “And … sorry about your friend. I hope you’re feeling better.”

“You too,” he said, then vanished in a clatter of dice.

Then, all at once, I had the power, and got started on making a better world.

THE END

Chapter End Notes

There it is. I hope you liked it. I hope I made it feel real, if just for a bit. 1.6 million words across almost exactly four years. It was a lot. You probably weren't here when it began, but I'm glad I picked you up along the way. I hope you ...

Discuss on reddit r/rational!
Join my subreddit!
Chat on my Discord!
Visit my website!
Read the worldbuilding document!
Or the side story where the group plays Arches!
Or the Christmas special!
Or the side story without any of the characters you know and (presumably) like!
I don't know that finishing this and then immediately going on to read that stuff makes sense, but you could, if you want to!

There might be a few epilogue chapters, all of which are written, and some which might be available to you now, depending on when you read this. And after that, a speedrun version of the story, and maybe a version where characters are memes of themselves, and maybe some other stuff.

And after that, more words, always more words, something light and fluffy to cleanse my palatte, something less committed to self-reflection and honesty.

The End of the World

The world didn’t end the same way for everyone.

Rance Su was a farmer, though not as diversified as the common conception of a farmer. He had no chickens or cows, no marbats or pigs. He had a single crop he tended to, taking three harvests of milk leaves a year from his numerous fields, and during the winter months, he did some basic maintenance, then traveled south and did some simple labor in the city.

When the world ended, he was going through his fields and plucking the worst of the weeds, the ones that stuck their heads up above the milk leaves.

He saw the woman coming from a half mile off, but didn’t stop what he was doing until she was quite close to him. He took a long drink from his bottle of water and regarded her, then crossed over through the field to see what it was she wanted. Normally he would have been annoyed by the interruption, but it was hot, and he found himself grateful for the break. She wasn’t dressed for the weather, but didn’t seem to mind it too much. She was a businesswoman, by the looks of it, dressed in imperial fashion, though the conservative end of it, not showing much flesh, more was the pity. She was mezin, like him, with a long, elegant neck.

“Rance Su?” she asked, once he was close enough.

He nodded. “That’s me. Somethin’ the matter?”

“No, nothing wrong at all,” she said. “I’m an avatar of Transition Services. Do you have a few moments?”

“Sure do,” he replied, wiping the sweat from his brow. The words she’d said hadn’t made much sense. She spoke the imperial dialect better than he did, in a way that marked her as possibly being a bureaucrat. There was something comforting about bureaucrats: you knew where they stood. “Are you sellin’ somethin’?”

She reached into a bag at her side and produced a clipboard. “No,” she replied. She looked at the clipboard for a moment, then looked at him. “The world ended about ten minutes ago, but that’s perfectly fine, because we have a new one.”

“Did it end?” he asked, raising an eyebrow. He’d have thought she was crazy, if she hadn’t been so put together, and if she didn’t have that air to her, like someone had put her in charge.

She nodded. “The physical world still exists, obviously, because we’re standing in it having this conversation, but a very large number of key institutions, conventions, and foundations of reality have been made obsolete and replaced or changed. When I say that the world has ended, I mean that nothing you take for granted in your life applies anymore. The transition will be jarring for some, which is why Transition Services exists, and why I’m here.”

“Ten minutes ago?” he asked, looking her up and down. “You work fast?”

“With you, because the circumstances allowed it, we’re moving fairly slowly,” she replied. She still hadn’t given him her name. “We want you to have a smooth transition, and in our opinion, that’s best served by having me here. Now, the bad news is that much of your work in this field over the past few months has been pointless. The good news is that you never have to work another day in your life.”

“The milk leaves are pointless?” he asked, raising an eyebrow again. He looked out at the crops. “Why?”

“One way to put it would be that the market is flooded,” said the woman. “But that’s not quite true, because there is no market anymore. Anyone can have all the milk leaves they want, at any time.”

“Oh?” he asked. “So you’re sayin’ the crop is worthless. And the land, and the tractor.”

She nodded. “If it helps give you an idea of what I’m talking about, you can imagine that some entad has just been created which allows anyone to instantly have all the milk leaves they want, in whatever form they want, from anywhere in the world, with only a thought, and at no cost. Except this also applies to everything else.”

“So if I wanted a pocket full of obols?” he asked. “No, let me do better. I want a stack of obols.” He pointed to a spot on the road. “Right there.”

To his disbelief, the stack of obols appeared right where he’d pointed. It was taller than he’d been expecting, coming nearly up to his hips.

“Obols are functionally worthless,” said the woman. “Every organization of nearly any size has been dissolved, effective thirteen minutes ago. Anything you want, except insofar as it affects other thinking people, can be had immediately.”

He stared at the money.

“Transition Services exists to help you transition to the new world,” she said. “We’re here to help you think through all the immediate changes you want to make to your life, as well as to help you opt-in to several programs and relocate to one of the heavens, which you can think of as an anti-hell.”

“Programs?” he asked, eyes still on the money.

“Are you currently feeling any pain?” she asked.

He looked at her, then squinted. “Sure, a bit,” he replied. “In the left knee.” He’d had that since he was a kid. There was a reason he didn’t raise animals.

“Is it okay with you if I take a look and then make the pain go away?” she asked. “I won’t need to touch you or have you remove your clothes.”

“Sure,” he replied, squinting at her.

The result was instant, and a mild pain that had been with Rance for three decades was suddenly gone.

“Huh,” he said, flexing it.

“If you’d like, I can identify and make other bodily changes to bring you in line with your concept of your best self,” she said. “You’d be giving consent only for a limited time, and we would ask again before doing any other identification or changes.”

“Sure,” he replied again.

Again, the change happened instantly, and he found himself standing taller. He was feeling good, or rather, not bad, in a way he hadn’t really felt since he was a child, and maybe not even then. His vision had sharpened, he’d lost the fat on his belly, his muscles moved freely without any complaint, a minor pain in one of his back teeth was completely gone, and he was clean, as though he’d just gotten out of a shower and brushed his teeth.

“Wow,” he said, looking at his hands. “Wait. I got an aunt in the hospital, if —”

“She’ll be visiting with someone from Transition Services too,” replied the woman with a smile. “No one is going to live with pain or illness anymore unless they choose it.”

“Who would?” asked Rance, but as soon as it was past his lips the thought occurred to him that there were always people who would do weird things for weird reasons. “How much power do you people got?”

“All of it,” she replied. “And I’m not really a person, only an avatar.”

“But you can do anythin’?” he asked. “Anythin’ at all?”

“Anything that we have the informed consent of those involved for,” she said. “Though there are exceptions where people are incapable of giving informed consent, or where there’s an issue of suffering. In the near term, is there anything you need, any way you’d like for us to use our power? Our intent is that transition will be as gentle as possible. We want you to be able to properly process things.”

Rance tried to think. “How much time do I have?”

“As much as you want,” she replied. “I’m your personal assistant, though you’re free to either make changes to me or ask for a replacement. You would be accommodated immediately.”

“I can … change you?” he asked.

“I’m not a person,” she replied. “I’m a small thread of a larger intelligence that’s running Transition Services, and indeed, all aspects of reality. We refer to this intelligence, in the abstract, as the Authority. My appearance was based on what we thought would best suit you, but because we restrict ourselves from being able to read your thoughts, we couldn’t know for sure that it would work for you. If you’d like, I could take the form of any species, any class, any gender. I can change my speech as well, to use a different dialect or different words.”

“Nah,” he said. “It works for me.” He looked off at the horizon. “And everyone gets one of you?”

“Yes,” she replied. “Following transition, while the world takes a few months to reach a stable state, I’ll become a regular assistant to you, arguing for your interests, doing any errands you’d like, ensuring that your needs are met before you even know that you have needs, things like that. I will give you information I think you would want, or by direct request. I cannot lie to you. If you would prefer, I can disappear entirely, or take on less of an appearance of intelligence. I can be silent or have a personality. I can disappear and do my work without ever being seen or heard by you. You are allowed as many of me as you’d like, but more than one is typically superfluous.”

“Seems too good to be true,” he said skeptically, though that skepticism was allayed by the improved body he was standing in. Even the heat of the sun seemed warm and gentle, like the weather had somehow changed. Still, it was like the stories they told of devils, always offering something grand, with many strings attached.

“There will be changes,” she replied. “There will be so many unavoidable changes as a result of minimizing suffering that society will be unrecognizable, and as I said, almost every large institution no longer exists in any meaningful capacity, given that we supersede them.”

Rance looked out on the fields. “Let’s say that all this is true,” he said. “Milk leaves and any other crop, they’re all worthless. What am I gonna do then?”

“You don’t have to do anything,” replied the woman. “Anything you want will be instantly provided to you so long as you ask. If, later on, you give informed consent for us to see your thoughts, your needs can be provided for without you needing to ask. The choice of what to do with your time is up to you. We think most people will engage in creative pursuits, self-betterment, travel, social engagements, exploration, or relaxation. You can go anywhere you want to go, see anything you want to see, read any book ever written, visit new places, or make something of your own. However, if you would like, we can place you in a lower heaven which does require labor, or you can stay here, and be subject to most of the same constraints as before, barring some changes during transition.”

“The land,” he said, gesturing to the crops around them. “Do I still own it?”

“You do,” she replied. “We’ve done our best to respect property rights during this transition. Though of course, the land is worthless for all but sentimental reasons.”

He frowned at her. “Land is still land,” he said. “People still need a place to live, to play, even if they aren’t workin’.”

“We can create more land,” she replied. “There were, before the transition, hundreds of millions living in abject poverty. It wouldn’t be enough to remove their suffering and provide for their needs. A true end to scarcity means an end to the scarcity of land. That is one aspect of what the heavens represent.” There was a way she had of saying things, like she was reading from a script, that Rance quite liked.

He looked at the crops around him again, and a sweeping sense of loss started to well up in him. All the work he’d done on these plants, all the work he’d ever done was wasted. His entire life, up until this point, had no point or purpose, and going forward, it sounded like he would have no purpose either.

“It’s okay to be sad during the transition,” she said, seeing the expression on his face. “The pre-transitional period was one of suffering and hardship. Moreover, you engaged in hard labor with some diligence, and not only is there no particular reward for that labor, diligence, or your upstanding moral character, there is no punishment for anyone else. The emotions you might be feeling are a perfectly natural part of transition. There will be several options to help you deal with those unpleasant and unnecessary emotions, if they don’t abate on their own, and if they interfere with your happiness in any way.”

“Go on,” he said. “Tell me more.”

They called the kind of room Garrett Voss lived in a coffin apartment. It was just barely big enough for him to sleep in. It might have been one thing if it had been built that way from the beginning, but it hadn’t been, it had been a normal, cramped, bachelor’s apartment that had been subdivided into eight with nothing more than mesh wire partitions. There was an achingly small communal toilet with no shower or sink, a kitchen area that was constantly dirty, and that was about it. The combination living room and dining room were now several coffin apartments. It was the kind of place you lived in, if you were lowest of the low.

“Garrett?” asked a woman’s voice. She had come as if from nowhere, and she looked entirely out of place, dressed too nice. “I’m with Transition Services, do I have your consent to teleport you out of here?”

Garrett stared at her, then nodded slowly. She reached a hand for him, and he braced, having heard how painful teleportation was but having never experienced it for himself.

It was, instead, a pleasant experience, one that took them from his coffin apartment to a clearing in the woods. Garrett had only been in the woods once before, as part of a break while he was doing a stint of field labor. He’d always thought the woods were magical.

“Garrett, would you like to be better?” asked the woman. “Would you like to think more easily, like you did before the accident?”

“Yes,” he said slowly. It had been some time since then, and the shape of his skull had never been quite right after. They made you wait, if you didn’t have the money to pay the healers. They’d waited too long.

“Can I make you better?” asked the woman.

Garrett nodded.

It felt like a veil being lifted from his mind, like waking up from a long slumber, and he was suddenly alert, able to focus on the woman and the strangeness of her bringing him to this place. Things were clicking into place though, memories sharpening, and he began to weep with joy.

“We have a lot to talk about,” said the woman with her soft mother’s voice. “We’ve only just begun to make things better for you.”

For Perrina Wharf, it took about ten minutes from the time she got the full explanation to the time she made her first demand.

“Bring my son back,” she said.

“It’s going to take some time,” replied the man from Transition Services. “We need to do an analysis.”

“You said that you could do anything,” Perrina snapped. “You said that you had all the power, that you were capable of healing anyone, of solving any problem. You said that there was one of you for every person on Aerb, maybe more. Why does it take time?” There was a nervous energy in her chest, a fluttering, because this seemed too good to be true. And this man, from Transition Services, was offering a return of her son, the one thing that Perrina had been praying about for three years, in the vain hope one of the gods would answer her with a miracle. She had thought he would give her a simple no and say that it was impossible, but he hadn’t, he had only said that it would take time.

“We need to know that it’s a net good,” said the man. “Analysis involves talking to everyone involved, that is what takes time. Talking to everyone involved can’t be done now without affecting transition, which is still in progress.”

“He’s my son,” said Perrina. Tears were in her eyes. “Who else could you possibly need to speak to?”

“His father,” replied the man. “His friends. Your extended family. Bringing someone back to life has impacts, and it’s one of the few things we don’t do lightly.”

“You can look into their heads, can’t you?” asked Perrina. “You can see that they want him back too?”

“We can’t look into their heads unless they allow us to,” replied the man, shaking his head slowly. “I’m sorry, but informed consent is one of the cornerstones of the world we’re in. It’s going to take time. Right now, we estimate three hours.”

Perrina froze in place, clutching her dress. “That’s it?” she asked.

“Yes,” replied the man, nodding. “It’s important that you understand —”

“I don’t want to wait,” she said. “I don’t want to experience the time between now and then.”

And without any change seeming to have happened at all, Perrina’s son was standing in front of her, just as he’d been on the day he died.

Sutsu Su was deep in the middle of studying when someone rapped on the door of her dorm room. She was broken out of the study trance in an instant, but it took her time to surface back into the real world. Once she realized that someone was at the door, her first reaction was intense annoyance.

“Yes?” she asked when she opened the door. Standing there was a short human woman in a nicely-fitted suit, a bright and smiling woman who immediately made Sutsu feel bad for being annoyed.

“It’s the Ascension!” said the woman.

“It is?” asked Sutsu.

The woman gave an eager nod. “Not in the way that you thought would happen, but it’s still pretty much exactly the Ascension, just a lot faster and better than planned.” The woman put a hand to her chest. “I’m an avatar from Transition Services, here to make your dreams come true. Now, we place a relatively strong priority on informed consent, so before I make any changes —”

“I want to be smarter,” said Sutsu. “I want to be wise, pretty, slim, fit, I want to speak every language and — this is for everyone, right?”

“Do I have your consent to read your mind?” asked the woman from Transition Services.

Sutsu nodded eagerly.

The changes came quickly, one after the other, and Sutsu found herself transformed into the perfect version of herself, stronger, faster, with a mind that ran like a freight locomotive and access to an unbelievable amount of knowledge. She ascended through the realms that had been constructed only seconds ago and took her place as one of the first in the high heavens.

Mercen Honth had been teaching class when a tall woman dressed in black stepped into the classroom.

“Yes?” he asked, voice sharp.

He didn’t particularly like to be interrupted, not when he was in the middle of a lecture. He worked as a teacher at the athenaeum but had no particular magical ability, which in the eyes of some, put him on a lower level, as though his classes were unimportant in the scheme of things. It was a sore point. He was, additionally, a dwarf, and often struggled with a perception of dwarves as ignorant dirt-diggers, not that imperial society was so far gone anyone would say that to his face.

“The world has ended, but a new one has been made,” the woman announced in a high, sharp voice. “I am an avatar of Transition Services, and will be speaking to you individually.” As she finished, Mercen saw his students blipping out of existence one by one.

“What is this?” he asked. “The world ended? What does that mean?”

“Mercen,” said the woman. “The world as you knew it is functionally over. All nations, companies, and even this athenaeum, are now under our control. There is no money anymore, no scarcity, and very little pain. We’re coming to people directly in order to minimize the negative impacts of this disruption.”

“‘Very little pain’,” he said. “That’s a phrase that causes some alarm for any student of history familiar with regime changes. You’re people of some significant magical power, that’s clear from what you’ve done, but who will be experiencing this pain and why?” He was feeling off-kilter, but Mercen was a strong-willed dwarf, and if it was a debate this woman wanted, he would give her a debate. He had some sense that he should run and go call for help, but it seemed unwise, unsafe, and unlikely to help.

“Free will is one of the pillars of our values,” replied the woman. “People are free to choose pain for themselves, but not for others. This is a fairly small amount of the remaining pain. Beyond that, a significant fraction of pain comes from associations between people. Because no one has control over anyone else, people are still capable of hurting each other in social or emotional ways. By the way, we’ve noticed your limp. Would you like us to fix that?”

“Not at the moment, no,” replied Mercen.

“You could have a seat,” said the woman. “I suspect that we’ll be here a while.”

Mercen went over to the desk, and sat down in the chair there. He regarded the woman as she crossed the classroom and pulled forward a chair, then sat down as well.

“Where did you people come from?” he asked. “What are you capable of doing?”

“We are capable of anything and everything,” the woman replied, answering the second question rather than the first. “We can alter reality in accordance with our values. Those values are, chiefly, happiness, freedom, and informed consent.”

“And yet you whisked away my students without asking,” said Mercen.

It was frightening, incredibly so, but ‘Transition Services’ had sent someone to speak with him directly, so she couldn’t be all that powerful or important, and instead was likely a low-level functionary. This conversation was unlikely to be an important one, but it might help him understand who these people were and what they wanted.

“Informed consent requires information,” said the woman. “Part of what Transition Services is meant to achieve is quickly providing information in a calm and non-disruptive manner so that informed consent can be obtained.”

“It was a show of force,” said Mercen. “Not just to me, but to the students. Power has coercive properties even when not used, because the threat of use hangs over the conversation. Have you heard the term power dynamic?”

“We have,” replied the woman. “We believe that a power dynamic was unavoidable, and that it was better to be upfront about it in this instance. We will grant you power, at your request, to within certain limits defined by us, but a power dynamic will always exist between us.”

Mercen nodded. “You offer power, but if I told you to bring my students back, would you decline?”

“Your students are engaged in conversation with other avatars of Transition Services,” said the woman. “None of them have asked to be returned to this classroom. We will not bring the subject up with them unless we believe that it would be in their best interests.”

“You had bribes to offer them,” he said. His leg was bothering him, with a low, dull pain in the thigh.

“We offered them what we believed they would want and attempted to quickly minimize ongoing pain,” said the woman. “If we have consent, we can immediately fix any physical problem, including minor annoyances like a lack of sleep or hunger. Material problems, like a lack of money, no longer exist. We have ended scarcity except insofar as people find it desirable.”

“You claim to have removed scarcity,” he said, leaning back in the chair and steepling his fingers. “But there will always be scarcity.”

“From what source?” asked the woman.

“If you remove scarcity of materials, there will be scarcity of labor, scarcity of services,” he replied. “Take something like cutting hair, for example.”

“We would cut your hair for you, if asked,” she said with a mild voice.

“Art, then,” he sighed.

“We can paint a painting for you,” she said. “Though after transition, such things will largely be limited to the higher heavens.”

“Land?” he asked. He was skeptical that they could paint a painting, but there were other questions to ask.

“There was once a magic which allowed the creation of something called a demiplane,” she said. “Land was once a scarce but not finite thing that you could make more of with effort. Now, we can do it without any effort at all. There is as much land in any configuration as anyone could want.”

“Location, then,” he said. “There are only so many businesses and buildings that can be located in downtown ‘Brast.”

“Location is now no more than a matter of convention,” she said. “We can teleport you instantly, freely, and without pain. Space can be warped to place as many businesses in downtown ‘Brast as people might possibly want. What is limited is, instead, social and emotional aspects of existence, including attention. All restaurants can be a single step away from downtown ‘Brast, but restaurants still compete with each other for customers, word of mouth, and things of that nature.”

“And who regulates this competition?” asked Mercen. It had the feeling of a nice, incisive question, the kind he loved to give at thesis defenses.

“Most people will elect to have assistants,” the woman replied. “Those assistants form the backbone of our defense against malicious actors and perverse incentives. But I should also point out that no one will run a restaurant unless they choose to, which will blunt competition and incentives all by itself. Further, there will be Service-run restaurants where no one is available, at least in the middle heavens and higher. You may think of heaven as a similar term to anti-hell, with multiple layers.”

“And you gate who goes where,” he said, nodding. This, at least, made sense.

“No, no gates,” she replied. “People choose which ‘level’ of heaven they go to, with advice from their assistant. The levels exist only because people have different needs, and because it’s helpful to have a common framework in a social context when speaking of which heaven they reside in, but each heaven will be bespoke, and the rules are less concrete than they might first sound. There are some limits on movement between the heavens, largely to keep them oriented toward those who choose to live in them.”

“And you’re saying that there are some places, some heavens, in which there aren’t restaurants run by this government you’re planning to create?” he asked.

“The Service is not a government,” she replied. “It might be helpful or even pleasing for you to think of it like that, but it is all the work of a single cohesive mind of unlimited power and intellect whose goal is to satisfy the people under its domain. We term it the Authority.”

“And how many people are under its domain?” asked Mercen.

“The entirety of Aerb, the disjoint planes, the elemental planes, the hells, and every other plane accessible from any of those,” the woman replied.

Mercen stirred in his chair. He wasn’t sure whether he believed any of that. “I suppose you have proof then?” he asked.

“What would constitute proof, for you?” she asked.

“You don’t already know, if you have those powers?” he asked.

“We don’t have informed consent to look into your mind,” she replied.

“And you’re not going to ask for it?” he asked.

“Not when we anticipate that you would answer no,” she replied.

“My leg,” he said. “You anticipated yes?”

“No,” she replied. “But we thought that it was better to offer, in the context of our conversation.”

“You asked some of the students,” he said, looking out at the empty seats. “You asked them for access to their minds.”

“We asked those we thought would say yes,” she replied. “Many of them are now gone to the high or middle heavens to start their new lives.”

“You use ‘high’ and ‘low’,” he replied, distracting himself away from the reality of this, which was starting to sink in. “Those words carry natural valence and were chosen, if they were chosen carefully, because of the inherent bias they contain. If they were chosen without care, then they reveal the biases of those who chose them.”

“This is true,” she replied. “We believe that most people will be happier in the high heavens, and refer to them as ‘high’ because we hope that it will shift thinking. Would you like an overview of the heavens, as well as a recommendation for where we think you’d be most comfortable?”

“No,” said Mercen, shaking his head. “You consider the mind to be sacrosanct,” he said after a moment.

“We consider your mind to be your own to do with as you wish,” she said. “We will not peer into your mind unless you give us explicit permission, or permission to act on implicit or extrapolated permission. At the moment, your body betrays your mind in various ways, allowing us some insight into what you’re thinking. Would you like us to give you an intuitive control of your body such that this is no longer possible for us? If you say no, we’ll still do our best to read into you no better than a normal person could, as we’ve been doing so far.”

Mercen hesitated. “No,” he finally said. “Keep me as I am.”

The woman, just for a moment, looked sad. “Okay,” she said. “There are a number of concepts that you’ll need in order to familiarize yourself with the new world. I’d like to start with the heavens.”

“Go ahead,” Mercen replied with a sigh.

“We’re in Aerb right now,” said the woman. “It will still exist, going forward. People will want to leave though, which will create problems for those who want to stay. Our solution is to employ something called a thespian, or a ‘spian for short. These, like me, are avatars, small threads of a much greater entity. The ‘spians will act like normal people, going about their daily lives, with the one major exception being that they will not hurt anyone, under any circumstances, and that they will answer honestly if you ask them whether or not they’re a ‘spian.”

“Fake people,” said Mercen, shaking his head.

“If you choose to stay in Old Aerb, you will be free to continue teaching your classes,” said the woman, not denying the charge. “We can keep your class size the same, but as of right now, it would be roughly forty percent ‘spian, and we predict that by the end of this conversation eighty percent of your students will have gone to the heavens.”

Mercen grimaced.

“We will control all the institutions on Aerb,” said the woman. “We will do our best to make sure those institutions minimize harm done, but no more than a competent organization which was being operated by members of the mortal species. This means that there will be ample social programs to help the less fortunate who choose not to ascend to higher heavens, and pains will be taken to deal with a number of other problems. The ‘spians will not act as perfect citizens, and will only replace those who left, the better to not change the amount of labor on Aerb. There will be no new exclusions, but also no exclusions will be lifted. Natural disasters will cease to happen unless we somehow have the informed consent of everyone involved, which seems unlikely. We will default to not granting requests in Old Aerb except for in exceptional circumstances. Animals are all being placed in their own heavens, and will be replaced by ‘spians, who are incapable of feeling pain.”

“What?” asked Mercen. “Why?”

“If you were capable of making it so that animals did not suffer, would you?” asked the woman.

“I suppose,” he replied, rubbing his chin. “It seems … like misplaced priorities.”

“We are doing everything in our vast power to reduce suffering and increase happiness while preserving free will, autonomy, consent, and some basic throughlines of self-identity,” said the woman. There was something in the way she said it, like reading from a script, that made Mercen feel powerless, as though this had all been completely thought out years ago, and was being repeated to him by someone who was nothing more than a gramophone. He wondered whether that was the intent. “Would you like me to fix your leg now?”

“You’re asking because you think I’ll say yes,” replied Mercen.

“I am,” replied the woman, nodding.

“Yes, fix the leg,” he said.

It was instant, healed in a flash, as though it had never been broken before, as though she’d reached down into his soul and healed the damage there in a way that other healing magic never had before.

“What heaven do you suggest for me?” he asked.

“The middle heavens,” the woman replied. “You would have complete control of your biological functions and physical form, have access to plentiful food and entertainment, non-invasive augmentation by an assistant, and still have some value from your own work. We also believe that you would be able to find a good, welcoming community there where you could engage in intellectual debate and create petitions against the Authority.”

“Meaning you?” asked Mercen. “I’d be allowed to argue against you?” He wrinkled his nose. That had the stink of some of the awful things the Second Empire had done, with their contained discourses and protests in authorized fashion only.

“Anyone is allowed to argue against us in any heaven,” said the woman. “But we won’t appear on Old Aerb unless directly summoned. In the Low Heavens and above, we will listen patiently to any grievance and attempt to find workable solutions. In the Middle Heavens, we believe there will inevitably form a society of like-minded individuals with specific complaints against the Authority.”

“Complaints you have no intention of listening to,” said Mercen. “Complaints you can see coming.”

“We will listen,” said the woman, nodding. “And, perhaps, we will change our mind.”

Mercen looked out on the empty seats. No one had come back. Perhaps when all was said and done, no one would come back. It was sad and frightening.

“I need to stay here,” he said. “For my students, if they return from their conversations.”

“We understand,” replied the woman. “I’ll wait with you, if that’s alright.”

Mercen nodded. He had some duty to fulfill here, but he didn’t want to stay on Old Aerb for any longer than he had to.

“What in the fuck do you mean he’s not going to be punished?” asked Randall Vox.

“We don’t do that,” said the man from Transition Services.

“You said you know everything,” said Randall. “That means you know what he did, and if that doesn’t deserve punishment, I don’t know what would.”

“We don’t believe anything does,” replied the man.

“What, anything? You’re taking over and you’re not punishing anything at all?” Randall might have been astounded if everything else he’d heard about heavens and thespians and a new world order wasn’t overshadowing that.

“No,” replied the man. “We believe in minimizing suffering as best we can. We don’t hurt people, and where possible, we don’t allow them to be hurt. If someone has done something wrong, we’ll do our best to make sure that they don’t cause any more harm, and we’ll also try to correct whatever aspect of their personality caused them to do wrong in the first place. It’s about reform and harm reduction, not retribution.”

“And what about me?” asked Randall, sitting back. “Do you know what it’s like, sitting here, knowing that he gets this ‘heaven’ too?”

“We will help you work on yourself,” said the man. “We will help you take out your rage and frustration. If you’d like, we can bring in a ‘spian for you to beat, torture, or murder.”

“A ‘spian of Joyce?” asked Randall. “You’re allowed to do that, to bring in someone like that?”

“I am a finger of the Authority,” said the man. “No one allows me to do anything, I just either do or not according to my principles. My principles allow me to offer you a ‘spian of Joyce. It can either react as we believe Joyce would react, or as we believe you would most benefit from it reacting, or whatever other option you prefer.”

Randall thought about this for a moment. “But he could do the same to me?” he asked. “He could have a … a doll of me that would scream and whimper as he killed it?”

“We do our best to balance competing interests,” said the man. “There are image rights and privacy rights that are considered when indulging someone with a ‘spian. The bar is fairly high. We would allow you to do what you plan on doing with a ‘spian of Joyce, but we wouldn’t offer the reverse for him.”

“Selective laws, then?” asked Randall.

“We have no laws, except in the sense that there are things we will or won’t do,” said the man. “There are some things we’ve locked ourselves into because we know if we did something once, people would worry every time thereafter. That’s one of the reasons we never lie. But we’re not a government, we’re a single entity, the Authority, and we don’t have a bureaucracy, or a need for law, not as people think of it. We can approach each case on its own merits.”

“Huh,” said Randall. “Then send in the ‘spian, I guess. Maybe I’ll be more reasonable once I’ve beaten it to death with my fists.”

Pollanny FePonn initially didn’t think it was on purpose, but later, she would wonder, even though she never ended up asking.

The avatar from Transition Services was a tall, well-groomed man with large knuckles and a deep, prominent lobe divide. Not overtly handsome, but certainly with a calm, relaxed demeanor and a kind of manliness she found herself willing to yield to. She was sitting on her bed, and had been since this conversation started, while he stood next to the doorway, with a solid, unmoving gentleness.

“So,” she said, after everything had been explained to her. “You’re my assistant, and you’ll do what I say?”

He nodded. “So long as it doesn’t harm other people too much.”

“What could you do that would hurt people a little?” she asked.

“I could deliver a letter from you informing them that you don’t like them, though of course they could have their assistant screen letters,” he said. “Or, for a different kind of hurting, I could assume the form of a celebrity.”

“You could?” she asked. “But not a normal person?”

“Expectations are different,” he replied. “And it depends on the celebrity and the individual person, and how much impact we expect a violation of image rights to have. Obviously we prefer to get consent.”

“Oh,” said Pollanny, nodding. “But you’ll do anything I say?”

“Yes,” he nodded.

“Could I,” she began, eyeing him. “Do people … you know what I’m thinking, right?”

“You gave me permission,” he replied.

“Do people ever have sex with their assistant?” asked Pollanny. The words came out in a rush, like she’d unknowingly been holding them in.

“Of course,” he replied, smiling at her.

“And do you … enjoy it?” she asked, voice soft.

“No,” he replied, seeming apologetic. “It’s one of our commitments that nothing causes us emotion of any kind. We take that seriously. But that said, any assistant is capable of serving as a ‘spian, in a pinch. There’s really not much difference, as we’re all just fingers of the Authority. We don’t judge what you do with us, and we won’t tell. I’m going to be your assistant, unless you’d like another one. I’ll do whatever you tell me to, and behave how you’d like me to behave. I can take the lead, if you want me to act on your desires.”

Pollanny bit her lip and nodded, laying back slightly on her bed.

Mark Perperson had the conversational style of a spider. He liked to sit back, waiting for the other person to speak, thinking and planning, and only when it seemed like he had the right opening would he start talking, or rather, saying anything of importance.

“Okay,” he said. “So … people aren’t allowed to create life?”

“They are,” replied the woman from Transition Services. “It takes a petition to the Authority though, and along with interactions between people and keeping the heavens distinct, it is one of the few things we regulate.”

“But then,” he said, going slow. “When you talk about Old Aerb sitting here, plugging along with ‘spians, then you also mean that women won’t be capable of getting pregnant?”

“They will, if they petition the Authority,” said the woman with a nod. “If they don’t, then no, they won’t get pregnant.”

“Isn’t that a violation of autonomy and free will?” asked Mark.

“It is,” replied the woman.

“And … that’s it, you’re not going to offer some kind of explanation for why that’s okay?” he asked.

“People don’t ask to be born into the world,” said the woman. “They cannot give informed consent for their own creation, by definition. Worse, as children, they aren’t able to give informed consent, because they lack foundational understanding along with intellectual and moral development.”

“So you’re doing this to protect the children,” he said. “Or, the potential children.”

“Old Aerb, the Aerb that existed up until roughly an hour ago, wasn’t always a good place to grow up,” said the woman. “Children were raised in ignorance. They were born with deformities. They got sick. They were physically and emotionally abused. We will not allow children to be born into these conditions unless we believe, on balance, that it’s a good thing for both parents and children.”

“And you’ll take children away,” said Mark, as realization dawned on him. “You’ll take them away from their parents if, in your judgment, they’d be better off apart.” A chill ran down his spine.

“Governments already do that,” replied the woman. “We’re effectively replacing the government, but without the bureaucracy, the waiting times, the false positives, the power trips, the taxation — we can act on perfect information, every time, with the exception of your minds, which are yours to keep closed to us if you choose.”

“And if I stay here,” said Mark. “If I stay on Old Aerb, the place where you’re supposed to leave us alone, I’ll just end up surrounded by actors. There’ll be no new children. There will be no true autonomy.” He was feeling hollow, scooped out, and if he believed everything she said, which he was starting to think he did, then the place he’d grown up would be an existential hell.

“Or,” she said.

He looked at her. “Or?”

“I know you hate the thought, but the lowest heavens aren’t all that different,” she said. “There are going to be many communities there, filled with people like you, who believe what you believe. We would try to help you find the best one to suit you. In most of them, you would be allowed to take things along with you, to a plot of land that would be yours. Your apartment wouldn’t have to change, or you could allow us to make some minor adaptations. We could help you find a job like the job you have now. There’s true purpose in the lower heavens.”

“True purpose,” he said. “And fake animals.”

“No,” she said. “The animals won’t be ‘spian. They’ll be real. Different, in some ways that we can explain to you, but real.”

“And the children?” he asked. “Still no natural pregnancies?”

“It depends on what you mean by that,” she said. “In some of the low heavens there will be chance pregnancies, and there will definitely be deliberate ones.”

Mark hesitated. “And it would be a way to escape the ‘spians? I … really don’t like the idea of them.”

“It would be, yes,” she replied. “After the initial settlement, nothing would be supplied or created by us. All work would be done by real, actual people. In the lowest of the low heavens, you would be able to get hurt, to hurt others, to die.”

Mark sat for a moment to think about that, taking his time. She seemed patient, but then, she was, or claimed to be, some aspect of a new god. “Unless those people say ‘no’,” he said. “Unless those in the low heavens say ‘I would rather not be hurt today’.”

“That’s right,” she said. “You are able to consent to pain, but that consent can be revoked at any moment, for any reason. The exact rules, when that happens, will vary in accordance with the heavens, but in the lowest of the low heavens, revoking consent to pain will result in removal from that heaven.”

“Okay,” he said. “Alright. Then I guess … I guess I want to be in one of the lower heavens, rather than the mockery you’re making of the home of the mortal species.”

Heaven. The word just didn’t sit right on his lips.

Roughly two hours after the world ended, Clarabell Brown was laying on the beach, soaking in the sun on a perfect day, with her new house in the background. Her assistant was beside her, getting some sun too, which Clara was taking some delight in. Quite a lot had been explained, and Clara was sure there was more, but if someone came to you and said that all the limits of daily life had been stripped out, that all the pain and suffering was going away, you should celebrate. Later on, she would call her parents, and talk to her friends, but for the time being, she was going to be with her assistant — no, strike that, companion — and just chill out.

“I don’t see how anyone could hate this,” sighed Clara.

“Eh, people suck butts,” said Trish. That was what Clara had named her assistant.

“They truly do,” said Clara. “But that wasn’t just me being wistful, I really did want to know.”

“I know, I know,” said Trish. “But you know I love to talk about how people suck butts.” She looked over at Clara. “Or you should know that, if you want to be besties.”

“Of course,” Clara giggled.

“Alright,” said Trish. “So. A lot of people obsess, just absolutely obsess over what’s real and what’s not. And do you know why?”

“Because they suck butts?” asked Clara, giggling again. She liked Trish, a lot. There was something both immature and intelligent about her, a potent combination.

“Because they suck butts,” Trish agreed. “Let’s call that the first camp. The second camp, those are the guys who just hate change. Any disruption to their daily routine, like, even something small like their local cafe being out of milk for a drink, makes them super upset. Not everyone is like you, ready to go with the flow. Now, some of those people don’t totally suck butts, because hey, we get it, you worked for a long time on something and it turned out to be totally irrelevant. That sucks. Hard work feels totally irrelevant, and there are the lower heavens if, for some idiotic reason, you still want to have everything made by labor. Like, the real problem is that people have these two ideas inside them, the one being that you should always do as much work as efficiently as possible, and the other being that you should do hard work.”

“So if you can do something instantly, you should do it instantly,” said Clara. “But then you’re not doing the work! Oh no!”

“A lot of the work is going to be helping people understand things,” said Trish. “There are a lot of real obstinate people who hate change and progress and taking it easy.”

“Shame,” said Clara.

“Shame,” nodded Trish.

“Alright,” said the avatar of Transition Services. “That’s that. To start with, do you have any requests?”

“I never want to see another Doris Finch again,” said Doris Finch.

A tall woman appeared in the center of the children’s ward in an instant, and by the time anyone registered that she was standing there, the healing was already complete.

“I’m from a new agency called Transition Services,” she said in a loud, firm voice. “You have been healed by the Authority. If you want us to make you sick again, let us know.”

There was a silence around the ward that lasted for a handful of seconds, and then all the children started talking at once. The woman split, becoming a dozen of herself, one for each child, and moved over to speak with them in more detail.

(Juniper had pictured this moment a number of times, and when he did, it was hard for him to do it without imagining righteous fury on the avatar’s face. It was hard for him to think about it without having the avatar add in some line about how it was a travesty that any of this had happened in the first place. But when it did finally come to fruition, the avatar spoke with conviction and authority, but also kindness and understanding, because the kind of anger that Juniper felt wasn’t something that would benefit the children to see.)

“But what I don’t understand is why everything is going so fast, I mean,” Sonee took a breath. “I understand wanting to minimize suffering and everything, but why do this all in one go? It’s not like ripping a band-aid off.”

“It is, in a way,” replied the squat man who had announced himself as being from Transition Services. He had said that he didn’t have a name, but when pressed on it, he had said that Sonee could call him Roj. “Our first priority was to stop ongoing suffering. We filled every stomach, quenched every thirst, cured every disease, healed every wound, and restored the infirm. Where possible, we asked before we did these things, but in some cases consent was so self-evident that it was done the instant we took control. The disruption would have been immediate and far-reaching.”

“Yes,” said Sonee. “I can see that. But … I don’t know, I think that people would have liked to be eased into it.”

“I can see that argument,” replied Roj. “We considered it. But to ease people into the heavens would mean easing them out of suffering, and most people, especially those who are suffering the most, would not want the lifting of their burdens to be slow and gentle.”

“I suppose,” said Sonee. “But … surely you could have spread things out over a day or more?”

“We thought this would create a rapid, disordered cascade,” said Roj. “We were always going to go into the hospitals and heal the sick and injured as soon as we could. We were always going to pull people from jobs they hated. We were going to remove children from abusive homes, get started on resurrecting the dead, — we were always going to do those things as soon as possible, and because of that, it made sense to do everything as soon as possible.”

“Right,” said Sonee. “Sure. I just … I guess we’ll all have to trust you.”

“No,” replied Roj. “Plenty of people won’t trust us. But we think that you’ll be happier if you do, and we hope that we can provide you with a reason to trust.”

“Let me ask this,” said Pallida Sade. She was either fifteen years old or thirty thousand years old depending on your perspective. “What is there left to steal?”

“Theft is impossible, except from those people who have opted to leave themselves open to theft,” said the avatar of Transition Services. She was pink-skinned, like Pallida, but decidedly not renacim.

“Alright, let’s say that you’re right,” said Pallida. “I could still trick someone into opening themselves up for theft, right?”

“This is true,” said the avatar. “Because scarcity has been eliminated except in the lowest heavens, you will be restricted in your ability to steal from people except in certain particular cases. The first is a low heaven in which theft is permitted. The second is a case where the nebulous element of authenticity is desired, and where we are able to definitively say that there is some continuity of existence for the object in question. The third and final are social or experiential thefts.”

Pallida frowned at that. “You’re saying one of my options, if I want to continue on being a thief, is to steal someone’s friends?”

“There will be many options in that vein, yes,” said the avatar. “The heavens will have various organizations, some of them in conflict with each other, and there will be some possibility for poaching people from one to the other, though obviously with the lack of scarcity this will be significantly more difficult than simply providing a better offer. An experiential theft would be something like taking someone’s possibility for a valued experience, or contrarily, giving them an experience they wouldn’t wish to have.”

“And you allow this?” asked Pallida.

“We do,” replied the avatar. “But only against those for whom protections have been declined. If asked, or sometimes if we feel an offer is prudent and the offer is accepted, we will put up defenses against even these more esoteric forms of theft.”

“So it’s con games,” nodded Pallida. “I can work with that.”

“It is, alternately, possible for us to place you in a heaven of our own creation,” continued the avatar, as though Pallida hadn’t spoken. “We could give you limitless targets that would test your skills, and a rich, vibrant community of fellow thieves, fences, and investigators.”

Pallida considered that for a moment. “All ‘spians though,” she said.

“No,” replied the avatar. “As with many heavens, we will recruit people who are interested. For the heaven we have in mind, which is not yet constructed given our uncertainty about the participants, we have a guess of roughly a thousand people.”

“Okay,” said Pallida. “Sure, sounds fun. But … why investigators? Why police, if it’s a heaven for criminals?”

The avatar smiled. “We do not believe you would enjoy stealing if it were as simple as walking in and taking something with no risk of retribution. The thrill is in getting away with something.”

“I guess,” said Pallida. “Yeah, that tracks. And if I don’t want to be a thief, I guess I have other skills to fall back on.” She smiled. “Fine, take me to heaven. And thanks, Juniper.”

Worlds were constructed, being built in a flash to fit all kinds of needs. The Authority had certain ideas about how things would be, but it had limited its own ability to read the future by limiting its own ability to read minds. As people opened their minds to it, the fullness of the heavens began to take its true shape, and some of these places began to exist for real, rather than being planned and imagined.

It was all horribly complicated, of course. The easiest thing to do, which would have minimized the most suffering, would have been to place everyone in their own bubble of reality and simply not tell them that everyone in their life was an actor. This, the Authority had not been willing to do. People had a right to know the truth, and a right to keep their own minds secret, and because people would still be interacting with each other, they would still be able to hurt each other, except in less physical ways than before. There were complex structures that would develop, wide-spanning compacts of mutual agreement, and there would be unavoidable politics that arose from affiliations between people and differences in value.

Juniper had often thought that you could never have a utopia, because one person’s utopia would always be the dystopia of someone else. The Authority had proven this, with what it called the Utopia Incompleteness Theorem.

It had done its best though, and that would have to be enough.

Princess!

Amaryllis stood in the kitchen of our new home, the morning after the end of the world, cooking breakfast and singing a little song to herself. She was wearing her faded pink ‘Princess!’ t-shirt, which was at least four years old at this point, maybe more, and beneath that, pink and white striped undies. She had a sleeve tattoo on her left arm which hadn’t been there the night before, but already looked slightly worn in, as though she’d had it for years. It depicted our party and our adventures, including a few things that I didn’t think I would have chosen to put on my body, like a unicorn, or Grak going into Darili Irid.

“♫ Makin’ bacon, and eggs, and bacon and eggs,” she sang to herself. “♫ Makin’ bakin’,” she shifted her bare feet to the right, “♫ Makon bacon,” in a lower voice, then feet to the left, “♫ Makin’ the bacon, shakin’ the bacon,” she moved the cast iron pan from side to side, “♫ Wakin’ and shakin’ and makin’ some bakin,” she wiggled her butt as she sang to herself.

She turned to me. “Juniper!” she said. “I found a problem with heaven. You made a mistake.”

“Oh?” I asked.

“Makin’ and bacon don’t rhyme,” she said. She held up her thumb and forefinger. “They’re about this close.”

I thought about that for a moment. “We could make them rhyme,” I said. “At least, locally, in this context. We could give ourselves the right dialect so that it would work.”

“Nah,” she said, returning to the eggs and bacon. She used her spatula to scoop them onto a plate, then laid some thick slices of bread in the bacon fat to make some quick toast.

“How are you doing?” I asked.

“How do I seem like I’m doing?” she asked, looking at me from over her shoulder. Her hair was long, going halfway down her back, in messy half-curls. There was a grin on her face.

“Happy,” I said.

“We won,” she said. “And now we get a reward of bacon.” She used the spatula to flip the toast into the air, and caught it on the plate. “I made some for you, obviously.”

“Thanks,” I said, taking a seat at the breakfast table. Amaryllis set out plates down, then sat across from me.

“Top ten best things about heaven, you start,” she said.

“No suffering of innocents,” I said.

“No risk of being splattered by bacon grease,” said Amaryllis.

“No poverty,” I said.

“Being able to eat unlimited bacon,” said Amaryllis.

“Was that an issue for you before?” I asked. “I don’t remember you ever having to watch your figure.”

“Juniper, unlimited bacon,” said Amaryllis. “Before, how many pounds of bacon would I be able to eat without getting sick? How many before my stomach was completely full? And before either of those, I would have stopped getting as much joy from the bacon.” She held up a slice of bacon, then closed one eye to look at it. “The very first bite of bacon was always the best, and every bite after the first was a little bit less. But now, as we’re in heaven, I’ve made it so I don’t get tired of eating bacon, I've made my stomach have infinite capacity, and I’ve made each bite equally good, so long as other factors like cook time, fat composition, rendering, and the like remain the same. No hedonic treadmill, no limits, not for bacon.” She took a bite of bacon. “Something is up with you.”

“We’ve got six more to go,” I said. “Here’s one: being with you.”

“Free housing,” said Amaryllis, looking around our new kitchen.

“Affordable healthcare,” I said.

“Good schools,” said Amaryllis. “Not that it’s an issue yet.”

“Low taxes,” I said.

“Final one,” said Amaryllis, shivering slightly. “I have to say, I’m feeling the pressure. Let’s see … oh, temperature control, obviously. There’s nothing like cooking bacon in your underwear and not having to worry that it’s too cold in the kitchen.”

I smiled at her, and ate some of the food. It was quite good, without being literally perfect.

“Juniper,” said Amaryllis. She was watching me. “Spill the beans. What’s on your mind?”

The night before had been a good one. I had ascended, spent an enormous amount of time planning things out while the world was frozen, consulted with a number of people who were unfrozen for that purpose, consulted with avatars of my party members, then created a splinter of myself with none of the godly memories to keep living in my place. Then, I had been placed back with the others, as though I had never left. We’d gotten a visit from Transition Services, who spoke to us as a group and explained the way of things, then we’d had a little party back in Poran with Valencia, and then we’d temporarily gone our separate ways, but not before Fenn had made us promise that we would get together every six months for reunions, if we didn’t all end up in the same neighborhood.

Amaryllis and I had built the house, or rather, had the house built for us, and then we’d gone into our bedroom and slept the sleep of the dead. We’d done that by mutual agreement: obviously it was within our power to edit out the need for sleep, to feel instantly refreshed with no side effects, and a whole host of other things. I had wanted to sleep though, to sleep with her in my arms, cuddled close together.

It wasn’t until the morning that I realized we needed a reckoning. Perhaps the image of my darling wife wiggling her butt and singing a bacon song had been too cute and too perfect. That was a disordered way of thinking, but …

“It’s over, isn’t it?” I asked.

“Yep,” she said. “Unless he decides that it isn’t.”

“I think he’s done with us,” I said.

Amaryllis shrugged. “I think even if he isn’t, that’s not such a bad thing. I think the narrative is over. This is just the part at the end where we live happily ever after. Let’s enjoy it.”

“Right,” I said slowly. It seemed very final to me though. “But.”

“But what?” she asked, taking a very innocent bite of toast. I swear she fluttered her eyelids.

“I want to know,” I said. “I want to know the things that you didn’t tell me before. The stuff that you couldn’t say because of opsec, or because it would have risked the narrative, or … I don’t know. The stuff that you wouldn’t tell me unless I asked nicely.”

“I wrote you a letter,” said Amaryllis. She reached up into the air and with a twist of her hand, produced a letter. That was one of the house rules we’d established last night: if you were going to circumvent normal physical reality, you had to look cool doing it.

“A letter?” I asked, taking it from her. “You thought you were going to die.”

“Yes,” said Amaryllis. “When I went down into the hells, I was tempting fate. Going to Fel Seed,” I’d given us our memories back, “I was tempting fate. Going down the Long Stairs I was tempting fate. Somehow, three times, I was spared. So, you can read it, and then we can talk, if we need to.”

I looked at the letter. “It’s a callback.”

“Yes,” said Amaryllis. “The original was with me in the Long Stairs and got Waltered, but I had backups, not that we couldn’t just reconstruct it from nothing.”

I slowly opened the letter and read it while Amaryllis ate. It was in her precise, meticulous hand.

Dear Juniper,

If you’re reading this, then I am dead. I’m writing this roughly a month before we attempt to pull you from the hells. If we succeed in doing that, then depending on the specifics, we might have to immediately go fight Fel Seed. If we improbably win against Fel Seed, then there’s a good chance we’ll be going right down the Long Stairs. I don’t know which of those points I’m most likely to die at, but I worry about all of them. If you’re reading this, then I didn’t make it. Stay on target. If you become god, you have my full-throated consent to recreate me. The mission is what’s important.

What follows is my attempt to explain the hows and whys of my actions over the last three years, and ideally, what I might have been doing when I died.

Your death was a shock. I had expected some of us to die when we went against Fel Seed, simply because the narrative might have benefited from high stakes at that point in time. I had known that the hells were there, waiting for some kind of story interaction, especially given the Helldiver option you’d left checked, but I had also thought that the hells might be a cast off from Uther’s time on Aerb, or a plot that he had dropped when he left, not actually meant for us. The existence of Valencia obviously meant that something might end up happening in the hells, but I suppose you might call me an optimist. I’d thought it would be infernal invasion. Really, what I had expected more than anything was a TPK.

I knew fairly early that I would have to mount a rescue attempt, but I had no idea how to go about doing it, or what the narrative required of me. I didn’t know whether I was in your story or one of my own. When Fenn died, I felt like we had exhausted all the possibilities, not that research into removing someone from the hells was a new problem. I kept running into the problem of planar disjunction, which I read far too much of without really understanding it, in part because those who came before me didn’t understand it either. My novel research on the subject didn’t bear fruit.

Eventually I settled on the Outer Reaches, but I had no good way in. The easiest way to get into the conceptual space required some level of fame, enough that there would be a concept of you in the collective consciousness, and lucky for me, I had already been working on mass manufacture of television with an attendant stranglehold on programming and the mother of all first mover advantages. Funny how that worked out.

I still had all my clones though, and I was sending them all over the place. I sent one of them to Cidium looking for Dahlia, and got a handful of stories, along with a few interviews with people who were old enough to remember her. It illuminated nothing about our lives, which are parallel in some ways and wildly divergent in others, but it did help to solidify my thinking about my place in the world. The Dungeon Master likes me, I think. That makes sense, if we assume he’s kindred spirits with you.

I was thinking about the narrative in every step that I took. I didn’t know whether the focus was on me, or whether you would simply get a time skip and wake up years down the road. I didn’t know whether you were bottled or tortured, or if perhaps we’d missed you in the hells, which was entirely possible, if a bit unlikely.

When I went into the Outer Reaches, it was like someone had turned my sense of narrative up as high as it would go. The schlossvolk love narrative, they practically bathe in it, and when they’re inserting things into Aerb, it’s always with the eye toward what kind of stories it will allow, and how they might get a conceptual interplay. That’s to say nothing of the narratives that go on between them, and the wars fought over mantles and anchors and implements and all kinds of things. It was insanity. When I went to make the portal out of hell, which I hope you were able to use, I was fighting hard against a basic fact of the world, which was that no one comes out of the hells, ever, by any means. Worse, I was fighting against narrative considerations, and against the scope of the project. There aren’t concrete rules for the schlossvolk, who I was temporarily one of, but there are things that twist and pull, especially when dealing with Aerb. Worse still, worse than everything else, I knew better than them that this was all narrative, that the escape I was setting up needed to be suitably dramatic.

I try not to let my thinking be completely consumed by the narrative. I try to play it like you play it, as though you’re unaware of what the narrative has in store, as though the object level is all there is. I think it’s a helpful mode, because the narrative has pitfalls you don’t want to fall into. On that particular occasion, I failed, and looking back at what I’ve set up, and what comes next, I think that perhaps there are other failures as well. It’s sometimes hard to tell.

I knew the Void Beast was coming. I knew that it was a form of time pressure, though a light one, not liable to be too serious of a problem for a decade, maybe more. I also knew that we almost certainly weren’t working on the scale of that many years. In the course of my negotiations with members of the Empire, it became obvious that there were parties that would benefit from a relaxation of the rules surrounding void tools. Perhaps that was what led to the explosion at the void factory, or perhaps the weak stance on void caused the uptick. I worried, after that explosion happened, and after we saw a much higher trajectory than expected, that it was something I had done. With the narrative, I worried a lot about self-fulfilling prophecies.

And I say that, but I’ve been working hard to set up this rune bomb, which we’re planning to drop straight into Fel Seed’s city to blow everything there to bits. It is, almost certainly, going to cause an exclusion. Oh, there are other things we’ll try first, ways that we might kill or unbottle you from a great distance, but I’m extremely skeptical they’ll work. Once I thought to use the great and terrible weapon of antimatter, introduced from Earth and dreamt up by your own mind, I knew that it was what would happen. I could see it clearly.

Risking exclusion of rune magic to bring you back makes no sense on the object level. All we have is your word that the Dungeon Master suggested you might become a god if you were able to get to the end of the game. I’ve never spoken to the Dungeon Master, though I desperately want to, and I pray to him almost every night. I have relatively little to go on, as far as your claims go. The companion powers are a clear, tangible phenomenon, you have knowledge that you shouldn’t have about the world, and we’ve all seen your skill. All that together shouldn’t lead to unshakeable faith.

But if we don’t bring you back, what then? The only thing that might remain is for you to escape on your own, and you’ve been gone a long time.

I’ve had trouble convincing people. I’ve kept word of what we’re doing to a small, trusted few. The narrative is easy to see, but even if I can get people to see it, they don’t always agree that it’s the most important thing in the world.

I try to keep in mind what you’ve said about tabletop games, and stakes, and saying ‘yes, and’ or ‘yes, but’. I hope that those rules apply to me.

I’ve decided that I’m going down into the hells to help you make your return. I’m setting myself up to die in some permanent fashion, I know, but for you to be pulled from the hells, there needs to be a cost, probably above and beyond the other tangible costs, and I’m offering myself. There are other methods of pulling you from the hells, aside from the machine I schlossed into the Omega Hell, but I know that they won’t work, just as I know that the antimatter bomb is the only thing that works. I’ll pray for a subversion, but I know the rules, at least for something like this.

I’ll try to survive down there, when it inevitably comes to that. I’ll try to live. I won’t be surprised if I fail though. We know a lot about the infernals, and we know that they’re preparing to move against us, trying to find some resilience against the kind of attack they know we’re capable of. I won’t say too much about it here, just in case, but I believe their plan to counter us is something they suspect we have no method of acting against: the people stuck down there.

And if it’s not the hells, then it’s Fel Seed, and if it’s not him, it’s the Long Stairs. I have a feeling pressing down on me like a weight, letting me know that I’m fated to die, especially if Fenn comes back. I’ve accepted that. I’ve paved the path. My death, when it comes, might be justified by the choices I’ve made. I might have fallen into a self-fulfilling prophecy.

The problem, I think, is that I’m pretty useless in a fight compared to the others, and that seems to be all that’s left for us. At the same time, you and I have put our romance through its paces. The only thing left for us to do was to have children together, and I don’t think that’s a narratively compelling reason to keep me around. I don’t have any particular investment in seeing Uther either.

If I’m dead, I don’t want to leave you feeling hopeless and alone, not when there’s work to be done, so I’ll leave you with this thought: my death will be worth it if you get to the end and achieve godhood.

~Your Love,
Amaryllis

“Huh,” I said once I was done reading. “And none of that came to pass.”

“It did,” said Amaryllis. She’d finished her bacon and eggs while I read. “We had to use the antimatter bomb, we caused a rune magic exclusion, and we had to use the Omega Hell gate.”

“But you didn’t die,” I said. “Even though it would have been narratively better, in your opinion, if you did?”

“Well, I don’t know,” said Amaryllis. She paused. “First, are you upset with me for putting the world in danger to get you back?”

“No,” I said. “I guess not. It worked, in the end.” That felt weak. It felt like there was a quibble I wasn’t making.

“Well, then regarding what would be best narratively,” said Amaryllis, thinking for a moment. “I’d anticipated that this was a narrative about letting go. One of the main problems with one of us dying, either before the end or during it, was that it would cloud things with Uther, and in some ways, undercut that meeting. The other big problem is that our deaths wouldn’t be permanent unless you somehow had to cut the hells loose from Aerb, or otherwise had lesser powers than we’d been anticipating. If I had died, it mostly wouldn’t have mattered , and I’m not even sure how sad you would have been about it.”

“I guess,” I said. “Wait, did we know that this was about letting go? Because I don’t think I knew that.”

“It was my read on the Dungeon Master,” said Amaryllis with a shrug. “There were a few pieces of evidence that helped to put the whole thing together. We had to presume that he was you, or someone like you, especially with all that stuff you had said about a connection to him. He was also older though, and even if he hadn’t been, I think we still would have made the nostalgia connection. Aerb is a place with all of your old campaigns, after all. And, because the Dungeon Master is all-powerful, we needed to make some assumptions about why things turned out the way they did with Arthur. I didn’t believe that the Dungeon Master accidentally let Arthur get into a bad state like that, unhappy and questioning his reality. I think the Dungeon Master wanted that, or at least felt it was appropriate.”

“Huh,” I said. “I guess. That’s not what I would have said, given the evidence we had at the time.”

“It’s what I thought,” said Amaryllis. “I didn’t share it, for obvious reasons.”

“It would have screwed with the narrative,” I said.

“It would have screwed with the narrative and if it hadn’t, then the conclusion was probably worthless,” said Amaryllis. “There was no upside.”

“It felt like there were so many possibilities, going into the Long Stairs,” I said.

“I think there were,” said Amaryllis. “I was serious when I said to you that it would be narratively appropriate for you to die.”

“And what would have happened then?” I asked.

“I have no idea,” said Amaryllis. “Most likely I would have tried to go to Earth with Uther.”

“And do what?” I asked.

“Die in the process,” said Amaryllis with a shrug. “But if we hadn’t, then there would be fertile new ground to cover, at least as far as the narrative was concerned. I would be the one transported to another world, albeit with almost no advantages to my name, unless the clones still worked. I would stick with Arthur and hope that we could make something of it. Or, perhaps, Aerb would still get the good ending somehow, and I would be your weeping widow.”

I looked down at the letter in my hands. “You made a big gamble.”

“Yes,” said Amaryllis. “And I think it’s quite tempting to say that I had no other choice, that a completely rational actor would obviously have done what I did.”

“But that’s not true?” I asked.

“I don’t know,” she said. “It’s hard to say. I know we could interrogate it with the use of assistants, but I’d rather hold off on that. It felt, at times, like I was leaning on faith, hope, and prayers. It felt like another version of myself who had all the same sets of facts could have decided on something else. Some of it might have just been my love of you.” She shrugged. “I’m not sure it’s important, per se. I don’t think I want the answer. To know, flatly, from a scan that went deep into my mind and memories, that I made the wrong decisions but was rewarded for it …” she shivered. “No, I think not.”

“It says here about Dahlia, then never explains,” I said.

“I don’t know that it’s true,” said Amaryllis. “But I went to Cidium, and learned as much as I could about Dahlia, using one of my clones. I spoke to a few long-lived people who knew her. She had a feeling to her, like she was a protagonist in her own right. She even got a cool scar from the Grand Finale. There are several large, important differences between the two of us, but I felt the hand of the Dungeon Master in her life. I think he liked her. There are also similarities between her and the Whore of Blades, from your flesh.txt.”

“The Whore of Blades was decidedly straight,” I said. “Or like … ninety percent.”

“And Dahlia was complicated, in that regard,” said Amaryllis. “Pallida was wrong, she did sleep with men, but only when using her girdle to take the shape of a man. Dahlia seemed to delight in shifting between male and female, masculine and feminine. I acquired the girdle, —”

“You did?” I asked.

“Yes,” said Amaryllis. “Before Li’o, actually. There was never much cause to use it though. I’d wanted to play a prank on you, but … well, events as they happened made that seem like a bad idea.”

“Huh,” I said.

“I used the girdle, naturally, and made myself a man, or at least a woman in a man’s body. From what I know of Dahlia, she delighted in the change, and being able to change nearly at will. For me … it was just a penis awkwardly sticking out from me.” She looked at me. “Sorry if that makes you uncomfortable.”

“Nah,” I said. “Surprisingly not, actually. It’s something I’ve thought about.”

Amaryllis raised an eyebrow.

“When I was thinking about why I wasn’t attracted to Grak, not for other reasons,” I said. “I was trying to run my brain through some scenarios and see how I felt about them, to see what my objection was, or what part of my brain was getting tripped.”

“And your conclusion was that you wouldn’t care if I had a penis?” asked Amaryllis.

“Um,” I said. “I’d prefer you as you are.”

“But it wouldn’t be a non-starter, is what you’re saying,” said Amaryllis, still raising an eyebrow.

“I think I fundamentally don’t understand what women find attractive about men,” I said. “But yes, ‘male’ and ‘masculine’ are fuzzy categories, at least in our glorious transhumanist present, and they were fuzzy on Aerb, and even before that, a bit fuzzy on Earth in various ways. And when I thought about Grak, and why I had no desire for him, even if there was some implication that I should, I think it just came down to my personal modes of attraction being so off-set from both his physical appearance and his personality.”

“Interesting,” said Amaryllis, tapping her fingers on the table.

“I think the companions were, in some ways, all introduced because there was some element of them that the Dungeon Master wanted to look at, or have me look at,” I said.

“And that brings us back to Dahlia,” said Amaryllis. “I think that for the Dungeon Master, it was a bit of prurient interest, or at least an exploration of … something. There was something Arthur said to you about the way that gender and sex were mixed up and blended on Aerb. Beyond that, we can assume that the Dungeon Master would think of me as attractive, above and beyond what a normal person would think. Wish fulfillment, on his part, in the same way that the early parts of Arthur’s time on Aerb were. So when it came time to make me, to make some commentary on … something, I think that I was a reused asset, in some sense.”

“Ouch,” I said.

“Well I don’t care,” said Amaryllis. “But I think it makes the commentary that I provided for the Dungeon Master more stark, if I’m an archetype of attraction for him and you, but without the sexual attraction.” She paused. “How old do you think the Dungeon Master is?”

“Unknowable,” I said.

“My guess would be in his early to late thirties,” said Amaryllis. “And he confessed to you that he’s been to college, even if perhaps he didn’t finish. If he wasn’t actually from Earth, in the end, I think that there’s still some mapping to be done, and things to get from assuming that he was, even if it’s not directly true. So I asked myself questions like, ‘what happened to Juniper after high school?’, and the answers I came up with seemed like they might make sense.”

I frowned. “And do you think … do you think that he had an asexual girlfriend?”

“Not necessarily,” said Amaryllis. “I think that I’m a heightening of someone, though it’s possible that like other things on Aerb, it was only an exploration of feelings, conflicts, or things the Dungeon Master and you thought were neat. Maybe we’re reading too much into it. But when I think about who he really was, and what his life after what you know might have been like, I think it’s possible that I’m a heightening of something he encountered and felt he needed to figure out. I was built in the image of Dahlia, who you and presumably he thought was the most attractive woman in the world, and then to contrast that, and to turn the contrast up, I have no interest in sex with you.”

“Huh,” I said.

“I could be wrong, and I don’t want to read into him too much,” said Amaryllis. “It feels rude, somehow, even given the circumstances. He did give us a good end, after all.”

“You know, we could probably figure out if there’s a diegetic answer to the connection between you and Dahlia,” I said. “I saw the whole world when I was god, including the distant past and the possible futures, so if there was an answer, it’s there somewhere. I gave myself a few memories, the ones I thought were important, but I left quite a bit for me to discover on my own.”

“I’m not sure I care about plots that never happened,” said Amaryllis.

“I do,” I said. “But mostly because now that the danger is past, I can look at the Dungeon Master’s work and take more joy from it. I can see it as … not serious, I guess. As the creation of someone who was like-minded.”

“‘But it was alright,’” said Amaryllis, smiling at me, obviously quoting something. “‘Everything was alright, the struggle was finished. He had won the victory over himself. He loved the Dungeon Master.’”

“You read 1984?” I asked.

“It was one of the ones I loaned to Perisev,” said Amaryllis. “Reading a culture’s dystopia fiction is a way of getting to know what they value, and what they see as their problems.”

“I don’t love him,” I said. “For the record. But if you can see yourself in someone, it’s hard to hate them too much.”

“I suppose,” said Amaryllis.

“So,” I said as I finished my last bit of bacon. It hadn’t gone cold, because this was heaven. “What are we going to do with the first day of the rest of our lives?”

“We have a whole heaven to explore,” said Amaryllis, gesturing out one of the windows.

“Yeah,” I said, following the sweep of her hand and taking in the seas and valleys we could see from high up where our home was perched. “But I was thinking that I might like to build something instead.”

Quite a bit later, I did go looking into Dahlia, mostly to satisfy my own curiosity. Amaryllis was satisfied with the narrative, symbolic answer she’d come up with, but the Dungeon Master usually came up with something that worked within the world as well. With the power of the assistants, it didn’t take all that long to find the answer, and as Amaryllis predicted, it was a bit of a let-down, because it hadn’t actually happened, and I was just peeking behind the curtain to see what notes the Dungeon Master had written down.

Dahlia had been something like a superhero, or about as close to a superhero as Zorro was. She had gone on all kinds of adventures in and around Cidium, and the more I looked, the more I agreed with Amaryllis that it did seem like the kind of thing that the Dungeon Master would have set up for his own amusement, because it was the kind of thing that I found compelling.

At a certain point during her long and illustrious career as the Red Mask, she had stopped what I suppose I would generously call a cult, one whose interest was chiefly in circumventing death. They were scientifically minded, and had found a backdoor into the process of soul creation through a combination of three fairly powerful entads. It allowed alterations to not just the unborn, but those who hadn’t been conceived. They had some limited success in what they called ‘soul insertion’, allowing a complete overwrite of preconception souls, which was what had caused them to come to Dahlia’s attention in the first place: there had been a rash of babies born looking utterly unlike their parents, preternaturally gifted and aware.

Dahlia had apparently thought it was an abomination, not just because it risked a fairly serious exclusion related to the background mechanism of the soul, but because it was depriving parents of their children. Whether or not she equated it to the renacim, who seemed to share some similar functionality, and possibly even the same mechanism, I wasn’t able to figure out. She had killed everyone involved, and in the few scraps of conversation I was allowed to see, seemed to justify it in terms of what might happen if the technology and process had become widespread. It was the same justification that Uther had used for erasing knowledge of spirit from the face of Aerb.

And then, in her twilight years, facing her own mortality, Dahlia had a change of heart, or perhaps a shift in perspective. The laboratory she’d cut through like a scythe was still there. The research had been saved. Dahlia hadn’t wanted to die, and while duplication onto the soul of the unborn wasn’t quite immortality, it was something close. She had believed herself to be a good person, a smart, cunning, brave, and bold person, one who the world could do with more of. Perhaps she was suffering from as much of the same protagonist-induced narcissism as I was, or perhaps it was just an honest assessment of her abilities.

It took her quite a while to get it how she wanted it. She didn’t want to be an obvious cuckoo, she wanted to blend in. The targets, then, needed to have some selections applied to them, so that the ‘clones’ of Dahlia required as few changes as possible, and only that which was necessary would be altered. She was in over her head, frankly, working with prototype-level technology and attempting to do something that had never been done before. She worked with only a single assistant, a half-Mezin half-Broshe woman who was a loyal follower. She made some mistakes.

Amaryllis wasn’t the only Dahlia clone. There had been hundreds of them, spread out over five centuries and the entirety of Aerb. If anyone had ever noticed, they had chalked it up to coincidence, but it was pretty easy to hide duplicates among the billions, and so far as I could find, again being limited by the Authority’s concern for the privacy of the dead, they mostly lived normal lives. Sometimes, with the later ones, there were clear fragments of Dahlia’s memory floating around, but most of the time there was nothing at all.

I could see the Dungeon Master’s prints all over it. If Amaryllis died, there would have been others. But there was also some kind of commentary on Amaryllis buried in it, the way that Dahlia had wanted the technology eradicated because of the effects that it might have had on society, but was completely fine using it herself. I could see it as a criticism of Amaryllis, easily. But there was also something there for Uther, if he had ever come across it, and I wondered how many of these things there were, across Aerb, plots and plans that never came to fruition.

In the following years, I spent a fair amount of my time chasing those kinds of things down, looking for signs of the elusive Dungeon Master and imagining the kinds of plots that he had set up just in case we decided to go running headfirst into them. I spoke with those who had been resurrected, and in a few instances, petitioned resurrections. Eventually, the feeling that the Dungeon Master was still there somewhere, with us, faded away. Amaryllis was right, as usual. If he was around, it was just for the part where we got our (mostly) happy endings.

There's No Knowing Where We're Going

We drove down I-90 in a navy blue 2008 Dodge Grand Caravan, listening to Fenn’s eclectic mix of songs that were playing from her phone that sat beside her in the front passenger seat (she’d called shotgun). Amaryllis was driving, her hands at ten and two and her eyes straight ahead, while the rest of us sat in back. I had a seat by the door, Valencia was beside me in the middle row, and Grak was next to her. In the back row was Raven, and beside her, taking up most of the space, was the locus, who had donned her humanoid form for the purposes of this road trip.

South Dakota was incredibly flat, and worse, there were butt-ugly billboards everywhere that made a journey through the plains and fields look that much less aesthetically pleasing. I was doing my best to not complain, but it wasn’t too hard for me to believe that this was, in fact, some kind of torture.

“We’re going to have to stop for gas soon,” said Amaryllis, briefly looking down at the dashboard.

“Fuck yeah,” said Fenn. “Time to stock up on snacks.”

“You know,” I said. “If we were being truly authentic, you’d have to worry about gut rot from all the Mountain Dew.”

“Bah,” said Fenn. “Bah, I say! Fuck authenticity!” She was the one who had insisted on authenticity. Almost all our enhancements were shut off, our bodies had been reduced to baseline, and we were wearing clothing that plausibly could have been bought by or for a middle class teenager in the Midwest circa the 2010s. We had all consented to this, obviously, but still.

“Oh,” I said, leaning forward. “Hey, try this. You stick your hand out the window, then wiggle it up and down, like it’s a bird flying on the wind.”

I heard a bunch of windows roll down, and watched as everyone did what I said.

“Neat,” said Fenn five minutes later. “So you would just chill out like that? Listen to music and chat and stuff? I mean, was it different with your parents?”

“Stopping for gas now,” said Amaryllis. She took an exit and drove to a Sinclair station in Planinkton, then began pumping gas. “If you’re going to get food, do it now, or go stretch out.”

“I don’t like having a bladder,” grumbled Grak.

“There’s something very nice about peeing,” said Valencia as she slipped out of the car after me. “I haven’t given it up yet. I changed it around a bit, but I still go pee.”

“Mmm,” said Grak. The rules about authenticity had been relaxed for him, given how hard it would have been to get clothes that fit. It was close enough though, a pair of gym shorts and a t-shirt that offered free tickets to the gun show.

I went around to the side of the van, where Amaryllis was still filling up. She was dressed in short shorts, a tank top that exposed her midriff, and giant sunglasses that seemed like they covered way too much of her face. It was exactly identical to the outfit that Fenn was wearing, which had delighted Fenn to no end when she realized what Amaryllis had done. While the tank filled, Amaryllis was looking off into the distance.

“Let me know if you need to switch it up,” I said. “I don’t want you to have to drive the whole way.”

“Nah, it’s fine,” said Amaryllis. She grinned at me. “So, we’re eight hours in. Is this the stupidest fucking thing that we’ve ever done?”

“The stupidest thing we’ve done so far, ” I replied.

“I kind of like it though,” said Amaryllis. “Given how terrible her taste in television is, Fenn’s got pretty good taste in music. Besides, it’s been good to have all of us back together again.”

“Yeah,” I said.

“Grab me a Frappuccino,” said Amaryllis. “Surprise me with the flavor.”

As I turned around to go into the gas station, she reached forward and slapped my butt. “Love you.”

“Love you too,” I replied.

There were other people, but they were all played by the Thespian. They were treating us like normal people on a normal field trip, and going about their own business. There was a teenager behind the counter of the gas station chatting with her much older coworker about a DWI, and there were other tourists milling about, along with two truckers having a gas station lunch together. None of them remarked on Fenn’s pointed ears, or Grak’s stature, but other than that, they were perfectly convincing people who you could be mistaken for having their own inner lives. We were all more or less used to it, though I knew Grak lived in a place without a lot of ‘spians.

“Hey,” I said to Raven, who was looking over the options for chips. We hadn’t talked together much, not since the end times, and not during the trip. “How’s it going?”

“Fine,” she said. “You know, I think I probably know the least about Earth in this group.”

I looked across the gas station, where I saw the locus, who towered above everything else, poking at the fluorescent light bulbs.

“You know what I mean,” she said.

“Sure,” I replied. “When it’s my turn to pick, we’re definitely not doing Earth. I think by the end of this, it’ll have been enough Earth for all of us for at least another ten years.”

“He agreed to see me, by the way,” said Raven. She picked up a bag of dill pickle chips with a frown on her face.

“Oh,” I said. “I didn’t know you’d asked again.”

Raven nodded. “Two denials, and then the third time, success,” she said. “Rule of threes. Funny, in a way.”

“Maybe we should talk about this in private,” I said. “Somewhere that’s not a gas station in the middle of South Dakota.”

She shrugged. “There’s nothing much to talk about.” She looked at the ingredients list on the back of the bag, which I’d talked to her about at the last stop. “Are these good?”

“They’re my favorite,” I said. “When did you find out?”

“A half hour ago,” said Raven, moving down to the Little Debbie stuff. She seemed skeptical about the Snowballs, but grabbed one anyway.

“We’re supposed to have notifications off,” I said.

“Talk to the assistants,” said Raven with a shrug. “They let it through, probably because it was a priority for me.”

“I think if you’re not going to try autotherapy, you should try actual therapy,” I said.

“Maybe I like my own brand of misery,” said Raven. “You get that. Besides, it’s not like I’m that miserable.” She looked over at me. “But I can see the pity in your eyes.”

Raven had an Uther-shaped ‘spian. He didn’t have all of Uther’s memories, that kind of thing wasn’t allowed without informed consent, but he did have all of Raven’s memories of Uther, along with a lot of public documentation. Worse, he was different from Uther in a number of significant ways, namely in that he had an admiration and respect for Raven, and a desire to stay on Aerb. There was also, apparently, a strong sexual chemistry between the two of them, though I’d only heard that through the grapevine, which had, in that case, ended with Fenn. Having a dildo I could understand, but he was more than that, he was an emotional dildo. Raven and the ‘spian Uther had been living together for months. She’d even requested that he come on the trip with us, which I only found out through back channels because other people had said no before I had a chance to.

“I don’t think you should see him,” I said. The ‘him’ in question was Arthur, the Aerb version of him. I didn’t consider him to be quite the same person, and I’d already said my goodbyes to the Arthur I’d known, but Raven still lacked closure.

Raven shrugged. “I gave him some time. He learned about his Earth counterpart. I requested, he said no, then no again, then yes. I don’t even know if the first requests went through, or if he saw them, but now there is a yes, so I’ll be meeting with him. We have assistant approval. It’s a tenet of heaven that you’re allowed to do what you’d like.”

“He won’t be Uther,” I said. “He won’t even be Earth Arthur. He’ll just be a sixteen-year-old boy.”

“True,” said Raven as she set her stuff on the counter. She gave the cashier a nod. “But come on, Juniper, I won’t be allowed to seriously hurt him.”

“I’m not worried about him,” I said. “I’m worried about you.”

“We’ll talk later,” said Raven. “Sorry if I’m ruining the trip for you.”

“It’s South Dakota,” I said as she paid for her stuff and left. “It’s not like it’s the experience of a lifetime.”

Except for the locus, who I had to lead out of the store, I was the last one to come back to the van, though I had a load of junk food with me, including the drink Amaryllis had requested. We continued our long trip down I-90, and Valencia and Grak continued a conversation that they’d apparently been having for quite a bit.

“Oh, I love it all,” said Valencia. “Not the extremes, but for the most part I’ll take the biological pleasures as they come. Sneezing is great.”

“I do not sneeze,” said Grak.

“But here you do, right?” asked Fenn, turning around in her seat and lowering her shades to look at him. She’d gotten an enormous slushie, which had turned her mouth a bright shade of blue.

“Hail authenticity,” he said to her with a smile.

“Hail authenticity!” yelled Fenn. “Fuck yeah!”

“Farts?” asked Valencia, looking at Grak. “In your normal, non-vacation life, do you fart?”

“No,” he replied.

“That’s crazy, ” said Valencia. “Farts are great.”

“I wouldn’t say they’re great,” I said.

“They’re funny,” said Fenn, through a mouthful of slushie.

“They’re not that funny,” said Raven from the back. I looked back there, and the locus was curled up with her head on Raven’s lap, taking a nap.

“Wait,” said Fenn from the front. “Are Ell farts —”

“Yes,” said Raven.

Fenn burst out laughing. “I’m sorry, that’s just —”

“I’m mostly a non-biological human now,” said Raven. “There’s a good reason for that.”

“Me too,” said Amaryllis. “Though each of the clones has different needs.”

“Boo,” said Fenn. She turned to me. “Juniper?”

“Optimized biological human,” I said. “I kept everything, it’s just been tuned so that there’s never any pain and it happens on a convenient schedule. No having to stop in the middle of a movie to go pee or anything like that.”

“Who would choose to be an unoptimized person?” asked Grak. This was largely rhetorical, I knew, a question of bafflement rather than a request for examples, since he could name a lot of them off the top of his head. “Are there people who like being interrupted by their bodies?”

“It can be nice,” said Valencia. “I like being kicked out of what I’m doing. It helps with mindfulness, I think.”

“I stripped out almost everything,” said Amaryllis. “I don’t even blink.”

“Some days she doesn’t even wear a body,” I said.

“Can we not talk politics?” asked Fenn.

“Is it politics?” asked Valencia. She seemed genuinely curious. “Why would it be?”

“Eh,” said Fenn. “Traditionalist versus modifiers. I hate politics.”

“Can I squeak in one final thought?” asked Amaryllis.

“Fine,” said Fenn. I was pretty sure that beneath her sunglasses, she was narrowing her eyes.

“If you want the fun of biological function, I don’t understand why you don’t go further,” said Amaryllis. “Why not heighten the pleasure? Why not orgasm when you sneeze? Why not sit on the toilet convulsing from the sheer ecstasy of defecation? The answer, obviously, is that you’re just attached to keeping things the way they are.”

“See?” asked Fenn. “This is why I don’t like politics.”

Amaryllis waved her objection away with a lazy hand.

“Dear god!” I fake-shouted. “Keep your hands on the wheel!”

Amaryllis giggled, and shot me a grin before turning back to focus on the road.

Behind me, the locus rose from where she’d been napping on Raven’s lap. She had been drooling slightly, and looked at me with bleary eyes before settling back down for the nap. When I looked over at Grak, he met my eyes.

“Do you think,” he began. “Do you think she heard you shout ‘deer god’?”

I cracked up at that.

“‘Don’t Shrug for Wall Drug’,” said Fenn.

“‘Find Transcendental Enlightenment at Wall Drug’,” said Amaryllis. “‘Wall Drug — Wealth Beyond Meaning’. ‘Free Custom Organs at Wall Drug’.”

“I feel like you’re not even trying,” said Fenn, shaking her head.

“‘Unplug at Wall Drug’,” said Grak. He was looking at his phone, and I frowned at the screen.

“Grak is using rhymezone.com, is that cheating?” I asked.

“Most of them don’t rhyme, so I think it’s fine,” said Valencia. “How about this one. ‘Giant Talking Deer, Only At Wall Drug’.”

“She doesn’t talk,” I said.

Valencia turned around to look at the locus, who was doing something like yoga in the backseat, much to Raven’s consternation.

“To be honest,” said Valencia. “I kind of forgot we had a giant deer with us, I was just picking a random animal.”

“Man, we should have brought Solace,” said Fenn. “I regret not inviting her. She was a cool old lady.”

“You missed the tail end of that relationship,” I said. “And I doubt she’d have come. She’s not even a druid anymore. Besides, we have a cool old lady, it’s you.”

“So you’re saying you’re fucking an old lady?” asked Fenn. “Gross.”

“I mean,” I said. “I’m not. The Narrator is.”

“You’re sharing memories with him,” said Fenn, pointing a finger at me. “He told me you were.”

“He has it in his head to write an epilogue,” I said. “I figured, why not? He’ll clear it with all of you before he shows the book to anyone though. There’s some personal stuff in there, I know.”

“Why did the Dungeon Master want it, anyway?” asked Valencia. “I never really understood that.”

“Book fetish,” said Raven from the back seat. She had been pushed off to one side by the locus.

“Says the librarian?” I asked.

“I like books,” Raven shrugged. “But there are better forms of information preservation and absorption today. I’ve been keeping track of some of the work people are doing in the Mid-Uppers. It makes me wonder why such an archaic medium would be his choice.”

“It should have been a TV show,” said Amaryllis. “Or maybe VR.”

“I do not consent,” said Grak.

“Yeah, that would be a problem,” I said. “Plus there’s a lot you’d have to cut anyway, if you wanted people to actually watch it. Or read it, for that matter.” I frowned, as dark thoughts crossed my mind. “Has anyone else read it?”

“I did,” said Amaryllis. “It was okay.”

“As an accurate log or a work of art?” asked Valencia.

“Both,” said Amaryllis. “I think I come off pretty well, but it is shown through Juniper’s eyes. And I think he comes off pretty poorly, but it is shown through Juniper’s eyes.”

“I read it,” said Grak. “It helped to put things in perspective for me. I learned something from it.”

“I haven’t read it,” said Valencia. “I’m not sure that I want to. I think I’d cringe at every page I have a line on.”

“Yes, probably,” said Amaryllis.

“Well, I’m waiting for a rewrite,” said Fenn. “One where I’m not dead for half of it. Or one where we check in with Heaven Fenn every ten chapters or so to get her screaming hot takes.” Heaven Fenn, sometimes called Henn if you wanted to annoy her, or the Angel if you wanted to flatter her, was also not on the trip, but had a memory-sharing arrangement with Fenn. Both Fenns lived together with the Narrator.

“Seems unfair that you two get to have clones,” said Valencia, folding her arms. “Where’s my clone?”

“They usually approve a clone request,” I said. “Did you make one?”

“Well, no,” she replied. “But it’s still a little suspect that you got grandfathered in, isn’t it?”

“I mean, they would almost certainly give you a clone,” I said.

“Ah, just giving you a hard time,” said Valencia. “You’re being no fun about it.”

“Top Five Least Awesome Things About Heaven!” called Fenn. “Go go go!”

“Other people,” I immediately said.

“Resurrection restrictions,” said Raven. I felt a jolt of unpleasantness at that. Really, the whole listing thing wasn’t really to my tastes, since I, or a version of me, was the one who had built everything.

“Time,” said Grak.

“What, just time?” I asked. “You don’t like that the very concept of time exists in heaven? Or is it just the length of this road trip?”

Fenn turned around in her seat and glared at me. “I’m only allowing that because complaining about the length of the road trip is an authentic part of the road trip experience.”

“There’s another sign,” said Amaryllis.

“‘Wall Drug — 5 cent coffee’,” Fenn read. “Fuck yeah.”

“‘Wall Drug, we’ve got loss leaders’,” I said. “How many signs have we seen now that have mentioned the 5 cent coffee?”

“It’s probably pretty good coffee though, right?” asked Fenn.

“I dunno, I never had it,” I said.

“Well, that alone justifies the trip,” said Fenn, grinning at me. “New things!”

“Sit straight,” said Amaryllis. “You don’t want to be twisted around in your seat if we get in a car accident.”

Fenn looked at her for a long moment. “Fine, for the sake of authenticity.”

“And another,” said Amaryllis, nodding forward. “‘Wall Drug — Free Ice Water’.”

“Luxurious,” said Grak. He had returned to his phone, which was connected to the Earth internet. “Google Maps lists this place as a ‘sprawling shopping complex and attraction’. The adjective ‘sprawling’ seems odd. Almost ominous.”

“Like a tangled overgrowth,” I said. “Which tracks?”

“I’m excited,” said Valencia. “But how much further is it going to be?”

“It’s not about the destination,” said Fenn. “Also, Google Maps says two hours.”

“I need to switch places with someone,” said Raven from the back. I looked at her, and saw the locus had turned back into a deer and was taking up most of the room. Raven had been with the locus since Sioux Falls, giving up her spot in the front passenger seat.

“Fine,” said Amaryllis. “Let’s make another stop and stretch our legs.”

We pulled off into the town of Presho, and Amaryllis once again went to a gas station, but she turned back to us once she put it into park. “Are we eating here?”

“Sure,” said Fenn, peering out the car. “Where’s all the fast food though?”

“We’re in the middle of nowhere,” said Amaryllis. “They’re short on franchises. Either you get something from Cenex, or you go to a diner.”

“We’ve been in the middle of nowhere for almost two hours,” said Valencia.

“Sorry,” said Fenn, frowning a bit before undoing her seatbelt and getting out of the car.

“You know,” I said as I stretched out. “We could just teleport to Wall Drug.”

“Authenticity, Juniper,” said Fenn, but she seemed a bit beleaguered. “Besides, we’ve come this far. Looking back, I probably should have chosen for this to be a shorter trip.”

“We could also shorten it,” I said. “I mean … make the van go faster, make there be less space between, something like that.”

“I’m still having a good time,” said Valencia as she extended her arms above her. “I didn’t mean to gripe. It’s nice for us to all be together.”

“Agreed,” huffed Grak as he got out. He stretched too, touching his toes.

“Well, I’mma find some food,” said Fenn, looking around. There wasn’t much to see. “Next time we do a road trip like this, we’ll plan it out a little better.” She stayed where she was though, close to us.

“You’re insane if you think I’m ever doing this again,” said Raven. “Once is going to be more than enough.”

“Our agreement was a get-together twice a year,” said Fenn. “It was my turn to pick.”

“It was a good pick,” I said. “But I think maybe the idea of us taking a trip from my hometown up to Wall Drug was, perhaps, a little funnier in concept than in execution.”

“We are doing this early,” said Grak. “In twenty years people will start doing the same. They’ll seek novelty and weirdness for its own sake.”

“Nah,” I said. “You can strip the novelty circuits out of your head, or rewire them. You can make it so that each time you read a book it’s like the first, without needing to strip out your memories.”

“I stand by my prediction,” said Grak.

I noticed Amaryllis and Raven in conversation with each other, and wished I knew what they were saying, mostly because their voices were low.

“Isn’t it weird for the two of you?” asked Valencia, looking at me and Fenn.

“Weird?” I asked. “Why?”

“Knowing that she’s romantically involved with a duplicate of you,” Valencia.

“That’s, uh,” I said. “Very blunt.”

Valencia shrugged. “It’s not even that blunt. I could be lots more blunt.”

“Well, it’s not weird for me,” I said. “I’m happy for her. I don’t really understand why they’re sharing a Juniper, but,” I shrugged.

“Because it’s fucking great,” said Fenn, beaming at me. “We can tag team him. Oh come on, don’t be juvenile, I meant we tag team him with jokes and teasing and stuff. Though obviously we tag team him in a sexual way, which I will proceed to describe to you in graphic detail.”

“Fenn,” I said, rolling my eyes.

“See?” asked Fenn. “If we had a second Fenn here, we could keep going back and forth, and you could play the straight man. How could that not appeal to you?”

“I — it does,” I said.

“Oh,” said Fenn, “Plus, you know what I’m great at? Calling people on their shit. It’s definitely in the top five best things about me. So with two of me, we can call each other on our shit, and Juniper doesn’t have to do as much emotional labor.”

“You’re actually terrible at calling people on their shit,” said Valencia, frowning. “You’re too self-conscious about whether they’ll still like you afterward. This is balanced out by your tendency to torpedo good things because you think they’re too good for you, but —”

“I thought you weren’t using devils anymore?” asked Fenn, lowering her enormous sunglasses so she could squint at Valencia.

“I’m not,” said Valencia. “But I did pick up a thing or two.”

“And how are you?” I asked. “How are you and Jorge doing? And the kids?” We saw them every so often, but before this trip it had been three weeks.

“It’s wonderful,” Valencia said with a wistful sigh. “I miss him dearly, but it’s the kind of homesickness that I think this trip is supposed to be about. The kids are sometimes difficult, mostly because they’re so different from each other. Amy is such a quiet, solitary child, and she comes to me with these questions sometimes, out of the blue, asking me about why some mushrooms are bad to eat. Juniper is quiet in a much different way, always with her head buried in a book, but when she’s not reading, she’s talking constantly about what she read. Having nannies for them has been a load off my mind. Having them be safe and secure, incapable of being hurt too badly, has been wonderful.”

“Good,” I said. “I’m glad.”

“Well,” said Fenn, looking over at Amaryllis and Raven. “Their secret talk is taking too long, so let’s leave them to it and get some grub.” She set off, and I followed behind her. Val fell in beside me, and the locus did too, bounding over on bare feet from where she’d been playing with Grak, once again in human form.

“Amaryllis says you might have kids,” said Valencia. “That you’re thinking about it, anyway.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I’m really, really nervous.”

“She said she wants to go traditional, which I found surprising,” said Valencia. “A full pregnancy, rather than just instantly having a baby in her arms.”

“Solace left a mark on her,” I said, looking back at Amaryllis, who was still in conversation with Raven. “It’s one of the things I think about, when I think about how things ended.”

“It’s not ended though,” said Grak.

“You know what I mean,” I replied. “There are a few things that just don’t get resolved by everyone being in heaven.” I looked back at Amaryllis and Raven, this time focusing more on Raven. “Things that still aren’t resolved.”

“They will be, in time,” said Valencia. “You didn’t build a bad heaven. Raven will just have to work through things, if she’s not willing to edit.”

“I know,” I said. “I just … the thing with the ‘spian Uther is … I don’t know. It feels like a bad end.”

“Takes her a hundred times longer to let go, right?” asked Fenn. “Bad worldbuilding, if you ask me.”

“She’s basically human now,” I said. “Or, as much as any other human in these times.”

“I know,” said Fenn. “Sad.”

“Not sad,” said Grak. “Everyone should be the person they want to be.”

“It’s sad that she didn’t like who she was,” said Fenn. “I dunno.”

We had reached the small diner, which wasn’t too far away from where the van was parked, and quickly found ourselves a booth. The locus was pretty tall, and barefoot, and I kind of wished that she would turn back into a deer, just for the laughs. Instead, she took the inside seat and began looking at the menu, not in the way that you or I would look at a menu, but like she was interested in what it was. Fenn sat beside me, while Grak was squeezed between the locus and Valencia.

“How ya folks doin’?” asked the waitress. She was in her fifties, graying and giving us a forced smile that a couple of decades had probably etched into her face. Her name tag labeled her Aubery. She, like everyone else in the diner, was a ‘spian.

“Good!” replied Fenn. “We’re on a road trip!”

“Anythin’ I can getcha to drink while you figure out what you want?” she asked.

“A round of Cokes,” said Fenn, twirling her finger.

“Water for me,” I said. “And the locus.”

“Wait,” said Valencia. “Do you have kefir?”

“I’d hafta check in back,” said the waitress scrunching up her nose. “That’s two Cokes, two waters, and whattid you say honey? A kefir?”

“If you have it, please, yes,” said Valencia. “If not, a Coke is fine.”

“We had kefir in Barren Jewel,” I said.

“I know,” replied Valencia. “Grak mentioned it to me.”

“Then they shouldn’t have it here, should they?” asked Fenn. “Authenticity, after all.”

“It’s an Earth drink too,” Grak said.

“Yeah,” I said. “But they shouldn’t have it here, because it’s the middle of nowhere. It’s a yuppie thing, I think.”

“You looked it up?” asked Grak.

“Yes,” I said. “Because Worth the Candle exposed some holes in my knowledge.” I’d needed an assistant to point them out though, once I finally realized I was being made fun of.

We looked at the menus for a bit. It wasn’t a terribly fancy place, the kind that only had a few options for a late dinner, and my guess was that it wouldn’t be good, or at least not classically good. It would be an authentic experience though, I was pretty sure of that.

Amaryllis and Raven came in after us, and elected to sit together at a table some distance away from us, to continue their conversation.

“What do you think they’re talking about?” I asked.

“Bonsai,” said Valencia.

“What?” I asked.

“It’s a joke,” said Grak.

“I don’t get it,” I said.

“You suggested bonsai to Raven,” said Valencia. “She got pretty into it.”

“Weeb,” said Fenn.

“Anyway,” continued Valencia with a grin. “The tree she almost exclusively works with is a,” she pointed at me.

“Ah,” I said. “A juniper. They’re talking about me.”

“You or Uther,” said Fenn. “My guess is Uther.”

“It’s not really any of our business,” said Grak.

“Aren’t you normally the group gossip?” I asked.

“I have been trying to better myself,” said Grak.

“How’s that going?” I asked.

He shrugged. I thought he was going to leave it at that, but then he spoke up. “Gossip is a way of making sense of the social connections around us. It is a way of placing ourselves within our social spheres. Finding better ways to relate to people is difficult.”

“Huh,” I said. “And … how are things with Darili Irid?”

“Good,” said Grak, letting out a little sigh. “There are many dwarfholds in the lower heavens. It sits there among them. It might be hard to believe that everyone there was dead for several years.”

“You went to visit again?” I asked.

Grak nodded. “My father is still under the impression that I had brought them all back.”

“In a way,” I began.

“Yes. In a way,” replied Grak. I was surprised to hear him accept even that. “He wanted me to come home, and asked me again. He wanted me to take my place. I refused him, again.”

“Ouch,” I said.

“Fenn and I spoke of it at length,” said Grak. “Sometimes there is a disconnect between you and the people who raise you.”

“Fenn said that?” I asked, raising an eyebrow.

Fenn stuck out her tongue at me.

“No,” said Grak. “But it was the conclusion that I came to after speaking with her.”

I looked at Fenn, and she smiled at me. “I give good advice sometimes,” she said.

“You were a good sounding board,” said Grak. It had the feeling of being a correction.

“Hey, you know what’s fucked up?” asked Fenn.

But the waitress came back over with our drinks, and took our orders, so it took some time for Fenn to get back around to it. Me, Fenn, and Valencia ordered burgers, but with a few variations on toppings, and Grak wanted a sampler of fried things. For the locus, the waitress offered some mixed vegetables and fruits. It turned out they did have kefir, which I was skeptical was truly authentic.

“What’s fucked up is that she’s Heaven Fenn, and I’m Hell Fenn,” said Fenn. “Like she’s an angel and I’m a demon, no offense Val.”

“Those days are long behind me,” said Valencia with a little laugh.

“How about you Grak?” I asked. “Still doing any warding?”

He laughed. “Not a single bit. A month ago I woke up from a nightmare that I was still a warder. I turned nightmares off after that.”

“Well, I’m still arching,” said Fenn.

“That’s not the right word,” said Grak.

“Me and angel Fenn had a contest,” said Fenn.

“Being in heaven doesn’t make you an angel,” said Valencia.

“Yeah,” I said. “Otherwise we’d all be angels, right?”

“We had a contest,” continued Fenn, soldiering on. “It was to see who could tag the other with an arrow at a hundred paces.”

“Taking turns, or both at the same time?” I asked.

“Same time,” said Fenn. “I got absolutely pin cushioned, but I think she got a bit worse. So yes, I still do arching, but only really in dumb contests with my clone.” She looked at me. “And you? Still do any, uh, saving damsels?”

“Amaryllis has me open jars for her,” I said, grinning. Even just saying it, I couldn’t stop grinning. “Like, she’ll act all frustrated that a jar isn’t opening, and ask me to come do it, and then give me a kiss when I inevitably conquer it.”

“You set up your heaven to have jars only you can open?” asked Grak. “Or does she just pretend?”

I frowned. “She just pretends,” I said. “Look, don’t dissect it, it’s silly, it’s cute, and I like it.”

“You’re allowed to like things,” said Grak with a mild tone.

“You’re also allowed to have a mix of emotions about liking a happy domesticity between the two of you,” said Valencia. “I think people undervalue the mental benefits of taboo breaking.”

Fenn squinted at Valencia. “Okay, so if you’re not using devils, did you just bump up your mind?”

“A bit,” replied Valencia. “I’m in the High Heavens, it’s allowed. For this trip, we were all supposed to go as we were during the adventure, weren’t we? So I think it’s fine.”

Our food came then, and for a moment there was only the sounds of eating, with mumbles about how good the food was. I was surprised by the quality, frankly, not just of the burger, but the fries. After protracted negotiation with Grak, I traded him a bite of my burger for one of his onion rings, but Fenn ended up stealing half of it.

We talked some more, and caught up, as we’d been doing. I enjoyed it, visiting with friends and having no stakes in play, though I wasn’t looking forward to getting back on the road.

It was dusk when we finished, and as we were leaving the cafe, Amaryllis slipped her arm into mine. “Sidebar, my love,” she said.

“Okay,” I said, feeling a twinge of anxiety. We went some distance from the others, keeping back so we could talk in private.

“I had a lovely talk with Raven,” said Amaryllis.

“Mmm,” I said.

“You set up the heavens,” said Amaryllis. “You set up the ‘spians. You went through a whole thing about how it doesn’t really matter whether it’s real, so long as it’s real to you.”

“So I shouldn’t judge her for having a ‘spian Uther,” I said. “Yeah, I guess.”

“We need to get at the root of why you think that’s a bad ending for her,” said Amaryllis. “And then, because it’s probably a stupid reason, we need to crush it.”

“Okay,” I said. “Can I get some time to think?”

“Tell you what,” said Amaryllis. “It’s getting dark, we’re going to be in Wall Drug soon, where we’re going to be renting some rooms. Why don’t you sit in the back with the locus and think about what you’ve done, okay?” She smiled at me.

“Alright,” I said. “Would it be bad of me to just do some edits?”

“Of course not,” said Amaryllis. “But I know you, and I know you’re going to try to wrestle through it first, possibly at great length with much wailing and gnashing of teeth.”

“Yeah,” I said.

“I love you,” said Amaryllis. She leaned forward and kissed me on the cheek, gripping my arm for balance, or maybe just because she liked to touch me.

“I love you too,” I replied.

I sat in the back and thought about Raven while a frankly ridiculous conversation took place between Amaryllis and Fenn. We were supposed to have left Bumblefuck, Kansas, at 7:30am, so that we could get to Wall, SD early enough that it would just be a one day thing. Fenn had overslept though, and then it had taken longer than expected to get everything packed. There was a round of recriminations about the number of stops we’d taken, who had been dawdling when, and things of that nature. It was a conversation that everyone was engaging in with great pomposity and exaggeration, and occasionally Fenn would interject with ‘Hail authenticity!’.

The locus cuddled up in the back with me though, and I thought about Raven.

There were a couple of factors. The first was that her Uther wasn’t real, he was just a ‘spian, capable of perfectly expressing love but not of feeling it. Of course, the ‘spian, all of the ‘spians, were part of what I had engineered when I was supreme god, and the god that ran everything was, in a lot of ways, still a heightened version of me, smarter, wiser, with all the Juniper bumps removed and several thousand subjective years of reflection and studying.

But it wasn’t that her Uther was a ‘spian, because I didn’t really have problems with them. If someone had a social or emotional hole in their life, and they wanted to fill it with something that had been created for that purpose, who was I to judge? But perhaps I did have a set of biases against them, and made some unfavorable comparisons, at least when it came to the individual case.

The thing a ‘spian couldn’t give you was true cognition and connection. If you told a ‘spian who had been pretending to love you that it should hate you instead, it would immediately do that. You could lock yourself under some consensual bindings that would make you think that it was real, but there were always ways to undo those locks, and conditions that they could lift under.

In the post-heaven world, the one thing that was most limited was other people. You couldn’t make other people do what you wanted them to do. You couldn’t make someone love you or care for you. There were matchmaking programs, and mutual editing solutions, and all kinds of things that would help you to find and keep someone as a friend or lover, but there were still limits, even in the higher heavens. Real, true, life could be created, but the Authority was stingy. It made the ‘spians feel more like substitutes for things you couldn’t have.

I wondered whether Raven had entertained the notion of creating an Uther for herself, or at least someone who would fill the hole. If she requested that of the Authority, I wondered whether it would be granted. Creations needed to have autonomy, and free will, and everything that a normal person had, and in fact, they would be indistinguishable from a normal person in pretty much every way. They had to be built to consent to their own creation, and had to have a lifetime that was predicted as being relatively free of suffering, and there were a few other rules, mostly the same rules that governed other life creation, but if Raven put in the request, it might have been granted.

The fact that Raven hadn’t requested a creation, or had been denied, and the fact that she wanted to go visit the Aerb version of Arthur, all added up to a tragically imperfect life for her. It was heaven, for fuck’s sake.

I had asked her, when we were riding on The Underline together, whether she’d thought about removing her grief, pain, and unresolved feelings for Uther via soul magic, and she had used the excuse that her soul was too marked and scarred for a soul mage to work on it. Now, that wasn’t a problem, but she still hadn’t done it. I understood that, since I preferred to self-actualize under relatively ‘normal’ circumstances, editing sparsely, but it still made me feel bad for her.

“Raven,” I said, leaning forward, “Can I possibly get you to trade places with the locus?”

“Um, sure,” she said. She looked forward. “Do we need to stop the car for that?”

“There’s literally zero chance of us crashing, and if we did, we’d be completely fine and could reconstruct the car in an eyeblink,” I said.

“That wouldn’t be very authentic,” she said.

“When I was on Earth, we did this kind of thing all the time,” I said. “Low risk.”

“Okay,” she said.

The biggest problem with the move was getting the locus to trade places, which took more time than I would have liked, and involved me being kicked in the shoulder as she tumbled over the seat. Raven was much more graceful in moving, which wasn’t saying all that much, and the whole thing was uncomfortable and complicated, all because of the desire for authenticity.

“Okay,” she said when she was finally situated. “What did you want to talk about?”

“I’m sorry,” I said.

Raven nodded. She was wearing a black t-shirt with a vaguely punk design on the front, along with blue jeans that I thought were a little unseasonably warm. She had a dark red lipstick and her hair back in black pigtails that both looked a little childish, and also like she was doing something ineffably subversive. I wondered why she’d picked that, from all the outfits she could have picked, but I hadn’t asked. “What are you sorry for?”

“For,” I said. “I don’t know. For not respecting the way you’re choosing to handle things. For being a shitty friend about it. For not visiting you more.”

“I didn’t visit you either,” she said. “Once we were done, we just … didn’t see a need to see each other.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I’m also sorry I carry too much of my feelings about Maddie into my relationship with you. I think maybe that explains some of my discomfort.”

“You have a hard time seeing me as anything but an immature child,” said Raven. “So to you, me having sex with someone must necessarily be a violation.” The sentences hit me like a one-two punch, both of them delivered with a chilly power. “I understand that. It’s the same way you thought of me on Aerb, there was no reason for it to change now that we’re in heaven.”

“It’s a toxic way to look at someone who is obviously her own person,” I said. “I’ll tell you what, I’ll give myself another week to sort it out, and if I can’t, then I’ll just do an edit. Okay?”

“I’m not comfortable with the edits,” said Raven. “You didn’t live through the Second Empire like I did. Giving people that power over themselves, even with failsafes, even with guidance — you didn’t ask me to sit next to you so I could lecture you on the problems I have with your implementation of the heavens.”

“No,” I said. “But I hope you’re happy, or that you find happiness.”

“I think you might have the wrong impression of me and him,” said Raven. “The construct isn’t — I think, perhaps, in your mind, it’s this grossly unhealthy wish fulfillment that’s only halfway fulfilling the wish. I think for you, what I’m doing is like the Dungeon Master running Arthur through a particular kind of hell that made both of them miserable, or where Arthur was made miserable as a reflection of the Dungeon Master being miserable. Like playing with my puppet is making me sad.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I guess.”

“I didn’t make him like that,” said Raven. “I didn’t make or call him into being for that purpose. Do you think, if we’d ever have brought Uther out of the Long Stairs, if he had somehow fallen in love with me, that it would have satisfied me?”

“It’s weird to hear you admit all that stuff out loud,” I said. “To admit that’s what you wanted. Love.”

“There was a lot I wanted,” said Raven. “There was a lot that I genuinely thought would have been for the best for Aerb, and for Uther. But those things I’m admitting now, those are the things that I tried to keep to myself.”

“Anyway,” I said. “No. I think that you had some vague feelings toward Uther, maybe a girlhood crush, and you built him up over time, and …” I paused. “Did you say you read the book?”

“I didn’t say, but yes, I have read the book,” said Raven. “It was quite emotional. There was a lot that was very personal, about all of us.”

“Well, the thing the Dungeon Master said, at the end,” I said. “About Pippi Longstocking.”

“You think that Uther was my Pippi Longstocking?” asked Raven.

“Sorry if that’s stupid or insulting,” I said.

“I can see how it would fit,” said Raven, briefly looking to the ceiling. I let out a breath. I’d been worried that it was a dumb comparison to make.

“But then … okay, explain your thinking to me, I guess.” I was trying not to think of her as Maddie, and ironically, her getup was helping with that somehow. She was dressed more like Maddie than I’d ever seen her before, and that made the differences stand out more, somehow.

“You’re not attracted to Pippi Longstocking anymore, right?” asked Raven.

“Correct,” I said.

“Well, for me, I constructed a fantasy that was … not quite right. One that would have a lot of the inevitable problems, waiting there for me to find.” Raven frowned a bit. “I had my assistant build in points of conflict, places where I would either see through the facade or where there’d be some cognitive dissonance.”

“But … okay, it’s been a year, and I know it’s not all that, because sometimes,” I paused. “Sometimes it’s been nice, right?”

“Sometimes,” Raven admitted. “Less so, now. Three months ago I requested a shift in my hedonic treadmill when it came to Uther, just to speed things along. The highs are getting less high. I’m getting … bored. It hurts to say that about someone I have feelings for, even if he’s just a character played by an actor.”

I stayed silent, but I was thinking about the Aerb version of Arthur, and how Raven was going to have a meeting of some kind with him. I wondered how that fit into what she’d said, and whether she was really doing things in a healthy way.

“So eventually you’ll break up,” I said. “And you’ll move on.”

“I think so,” said Raven. “I think the last year with him has been … instructive. You can think of it as an extended send off, if you’d like, the goodbye that I never got to have with him on the Long Stairs.”

I nodded. “I don’t think he would have wanted to stay in the Long Stairs for a year.”

“No,” sighed Raven. “I suppose not. And he never thought of me in the way I wanted to be thought of.”

I left it at that, and we sat in the back in silence for a bit. The others up front were sharing knock-knock jokes of generally terrible quality, given that most of them were made up on the spot, and Raven leaned forward so she could join in. Apparently, she had a ton of them.

The Ongoing Adventures of Valencia the Red

Most people in the Mid-Uppers were there for the complete transhumanism or the lack of intellectual or creative scarcity, but not so for Valencia the Red. No, Valencia was a relatively rare specimen of the Mid-Uppers, someone who liked the neighborhood, so to speak, but also enjoyed a fairly mundane human existence. The assistants had made a wonderful place for them that Valencia could always imagine Juniper having a hand in, with a large, stately home up on a hill, rambling woods with a meadow in the middle, a stream running close by, and various places beyond which were destined to become a part of the family traditions, like a beach with dunes they could go to in the summer, and a cabin on a lake they could stay at, and various other things that were sometimes there and sometimes not, depending on the seasons. Their family heaven could be as big as it needed to be, but Valencia liked things relatively small and cozy.

“Mummy, why did they call you Valencia the Red?” asked Juniper. She was four and a half years old, and still learning to read. They sometimes went to the library twice in a day, using the big oak door in the living room whose dial could call up all kinds of places.

“I had a bright red suit of armor to protect me,” said Valencia. “It had big, pointy spikes on it, and I was the only one who could wear it without being hurt.”

“Okay,” said Juniper. She looked like she wanted to ask another question, and she was holding onto her little book.

“Yes dear?” asked Valencia.

“Mummy, why did people want to be hurt?” asked Juniper, twisting her mouth a bit.

“Oh, they didn’t sweetie, it was in a time when things happened even though no one wanted them to happen,” said Valencia. “All kinds of things.”

“But why did god do that?” asked Juniper.

“This was a time before god,” said Valencia. “I’m not sure that you even remember those times.”

Juniper stayed, swaying slightly, a tremulous expression on her face. “Mummy, is god going to disappear?”

“No, sweetie,” said Valencia. “I know god personally, and he’s going to stay here, watching over us, forever.”

“Oh,” said Juniper. The worry went out of her like a candle being blown out. “Okay mummy.”

“That book isn’t too scary for you, is it?” asked Valencia, but Juniper had already turned and was going off to read some more.

“No, mummy!” called Juniper without looking.

In addition to the library books, there were perhaps thirty books that had been written by Valencia with the help of her assistant, most of them with splendid illustrations. That was the kind of thing that was easy to do in the Mid-Uppers, where amazing art could be had by the basketful, freely and instantly. Valencia understood why people might want their heaven to not be absolutely flooded by the kinds of customized masterpieces that assistants in the Mid-Uppers could churn out, but it was definitely not the kind of life she wanted to live.

Valencia moved through the house, making sure that everything was as it should be. Juniper was reading, which it seemed like she was going to devote her entire life to, Amy was out in the woods with their blink dog, and Harry was being bathed by their semi-‘spian nanny, which largely involved watching him to make sure that he didn’t drown while he played in the water for as long as he was allowed. There was, naturally, no chance of children drowning, whether in bathtubs or otherwise.

Jorge was in his workshop, learning woodworking, which he was doing without enhancements. While they lived in the Mid-Uppers, they went down to the lower heavens on a regular basis for one reason or another, and the Authority had laid down some general rules for how that worked, mostly in service of preserving the feeling of the heavens for the people who wanted to live there and to align everyone’s preferences. The Middle Heavens, where Juniper and Mary mostly resided, had a woodworking association that Jorge had taken an interest in, but he had learned woodworking in an instant, on a whim, and wasn’t allowed to take that skill or knowledge with him to association events or meetings. He found it a bit frustrating, but had resolved to learn woodworking the ‘proper way’, so that he would be able to do more when he visited.

For her part, Valencia was almost entirely unenhanced. If she needed things done, she had the assistants do it, rather than having modifications to her person. The garden in the back was one example. It would have been entirely possible for her to learn gardening instantly with a modification, or to give herself a Knack, which some people preferred. Instead, Valencia had opted to have the assistants help her, and watched with interest as they built the raised beds, put in the dirt, and planted the seedlings. Sometimes she would use magic to get things done, and she fancied herself a bit of a witch, with a broomstick and a wide-brimmed pointy hat.

There was a lot of joy in the rhythm of the seasons, in the cold of winter, the beating sun of summer, the crisp autumns and earthy springs, and the plants of the garden had their own rhythms, which Valencia took some pleasure in. It was the time of cucumbers and raspberries, and the apple trees weren’t quite there yet. Valencia did her best to keep their food seasonal, but it was a half-hearted sort of effort, especially in the winters, when canned or fermented vegetables got old in a hurry. There were limits to how much stock Valencia was going to put in realism. Realism wasn’t the point, not by itself. The point was an appreciation of the world and a personal grounding within it.

“The spells are holding,” Valencia said to the small black cat, which had followed her out to the garden. “Keeping those nasty crows away.”

“I miss the crows,” said the cat.

“Well, I’m sure you can take a walk through the woods and visit them there,” said Valencia. She bent down to look at how the cucumbers were coming along, and decided that the largest of them could stand to go for another day. Too large and they lost some of their flavor. It was a delicate balancing act.

“Amy ate the blueberries this morning,” said the cat.

“Ah,” said Valencia, looking over the bushes. All the blue ones were gone, leaving only the purple ones, which could be eaten, but were too tart. “Did she enjoy them?”

“She enjoyed them in the unthinking way that a child enjoys eating something sweet while moving on to other adventures,” said the cat.

“Well, that means that we might not have enough to make a blueberry pie today,” said Valencia, sighing. “But, I suppose, I could magic some up with a duplication spell. I’ll need a yew wand, some chalk, and a sprig of chamomile.” She made the ingredients up off the top of her head, but they had the right kind of feeling to them, and with the children occupied, it felt like a good time to go out and have an excuse to experience the woods.

“Perhaps that will have to wait,” said the cat, stretching out slightly and extending his claws into the dirt. “Mary would like to visit.”

“Oh, well, by all means,” said Valencia. “Will she be coming through the door?”

“She’ll be flying in,” said the cat, looking to the sky. “Now, if that’s alright with you.”

“Yes, of course,” said Valencia. It wasn’t unusual for them to have visitors to their property, but typically they liked to have some notice, and except for emergencies, not that there were true emergencies anymore, there needed to be explicit consent from either Valencia or Jorge.

Mary rode a broomstick, flying high over the maple trees, and landed with a rush of air in the garden, which briefly billowed up her skirt. She was radiantly beautiful, made more so by the wide smile on her face.

“I always forget how chilly flying can be,” said Mary, grinning ear to ear.

Valencia wrapped her in a hug. “You’re free to take the door.”

“Nonsense,” Mary replied, squeezing tight. “If you’re a witch here, then I’m a witch too.” She pulled back. “I even brought my wand with me.” She turned to the side to show her wand, which she was using to hold her hair in place. That was only possible because she’d chosen a short, thin length of wood. “Is Jorge still bitten by the woodworking bug? I was hoping that I might get him to make me a new one.”

“He’s in the workshop right now,” said Valencia. “No Juniper?”

“No,” said Mary, shaking her head and still smiling. “He’ll be by later, I think he might have needed some time to himself to process the whole thing.”

“What whole thing?” asked Valencia.

“I am,” said Mary, “At this very moment, pregnant.”

Valencia shrieked in delight, then wrapped Mary in another hug. “Oh that’s wonderful, I hadn’t even known you were, well — trying is probably not the right word.”

“No, it is,” said Mary. “I wanted it to be as natural as possible. I’m even going through the whole nine months of it.”

“Jorge and I are thinking of another,” said Valencia. “Should we coordinate? Would that be weird?”

“I wouldn’t want you to have another baby on my account,” said Mary, momentarily faltering. “Though it would be good to have a close friend our daughter’s age.”

“You know already?” asked Valencia, slightly taken aback.

“We’re not that traditional,” said Mary. “No pain for the childbirth, no chance of complications, I’m not insane, and once was enough. And obviously we’ll have a happy, healthy child.”

Valencia nodded. It sometimes cast a pall over things, to talk about how things used to be, even by inference. “Well, I’m thrilled, I sometimes wish that we’d waited a bit, so we wouldn’t be the only parents.”

“You meet up with Lisi and Reimer and their children, right?” asked Mary.

“Oh, of course,” said Valencia. “They’re good friends, partly because of the history, partly because Jorge is so agreeable. He could make friends with a brick. And we have other friends and playgroups. But tell me about the baby, I want to know everything.”

“There’s not even that much to tell,” said Mary. “Juniper is nervous, but he thinks that it’s a good kind of nervousness, and obviously there’s no risk. With his own parents being how they were, I imagine he’s just thinking back to worse times and trying his best to make sure he can do better for his own child.”

“Are the Narrator and the Fenns thinking of having children?” asked Valencia. “They’ve lasted together a lot longer than I thought they would.”

“I’m not sure that children are the kind of future that she wants. I’m not sure that’s what happiness means for her,” said Mary. “Which is a shame, because for all his low-key anxiety about it, Juniper has been enthusiastic, and I’m hard-pressed to think the same wouldn’t be true for the Narrator.”

“Well, would you like to stay for dinner?” asked Valencia. “I think it will be pork, cucumber salad, and perhaps potatoes. You can keep me company while I cook.”

“I was going to make the rounds,” said Mary, looking somewhat regretful. “Though I suppose I can commandeer some clones for that task.”

“Juniper would like to enter the property,” said the cat, in his mild tone.

“Of course,” said Valencia, giving Mary a puzzled frown.

“Oh no,” said Mary. “I think he might have been making —”

But at that moment, Juniper appeared in the woods, dropping down from the upper branches of the maples and landing deftly on a root that rose from the ground to catch him. He had said, quite a bit ago, that if Valencia and Mary were going to play at being witches, then he was going to have a magic system of his own, and apparently the one he’d settled on involved trees.

He had a satchel over his shoulder, and a full beard. From the satchel, he pulled a small pot, which he lowered to the ground so a sapling could uproot itself and clamber inside. Once that was done, he slipped the pot into the satchel and held his arm still for a moment so the sapling could twist and wrap around it. From the bottom of the satchel, a small toad with a garden on its back climbed up to sit in the pot. The toad wasn’t a constant companion to Juniper, and had its own annex of their house, but it always came when it was time to visit Valencia.

“Juniper,” said Valencia. Her hands had gone to her hips, and she found herself using the voice she sometimes used with her children when scolding them, not that it was a common occurrence. “Did you bring gifts for my children?”

“I did!” Juniper exclaimed as he strode forward. He looked happy and healthy, and a bit more at ease with himself. There was still a bit of darkness there, by Valencia’s reckoning, and a tendency to brood, but there was far less to brood about these days. He’d excised any outright depression.

“Juniper,” said Valencia. “If it’s another screaming spoon, I swear to — well, to the Authority that,” Valencia hesitated. “Alright, I don’t swear it, but please don’t let it be another screaming spoon.”

“Finding out is half the fun,” smiled Juniper. “What kind of uncle would I be if I didn’t let the kids have the joy of discovery?”

The screaming spoon had, in Juniper’s defense, been one of Amy’s favorite toys. There was a little face on the handle, Juniper’s own, and it would make a mock scream along with some dialogue if it was put in something too hot, too cold, too mushy, too sticky, or in someone’s mouth. ‘Oh gross!’ the spoon would say, ‘Get me out of your mouth, you’re getting SPIT all over me!’ or ‘Who made this soup so hot! It burns!’ or ‘Stop banging me against the table! Ouch!’ Amy, at four, had found it utterly hilarious. For Valencia, the screaming spoon wore thin after the first meal with it, and eventually, after a week of the screaming spoon yelling its way around the house, Juniper had been forced to come back and change it so that only children could hear it.

“Congratulations, by the way,” said Valencia, giving Juniper a hug. He squeezed her tight and lifted her off her feet, if only for a moment. There was a nice smell to him, something of the forest floor.

“You’ll have to give us some pointers,” said Juniper. “Your kids are turning out so well.”

“It’s hard to raise bad kids in the heavens,” said Valencia. “But of course I’ll be there for them.” She paused. “I suppose I’ll be an aunt, won’t I?”

“I suppose so,” said Mary. She was still smiling, the same as she’d been when she’d first arrived. She looked at Juniper. “Did you want to stay for dinner? I have clones to go make the rounds, did you want to get a temporary split?”

“Sure,” said Juniper. “Done.”

They spoke together in the garden for a bit, and Juniper made interested noises at the cucumber plants. He had a garden of his own in the middle heavens, though he was doing things more by hand than Valencia was. It was part of a spurt of worldbuilding, as things often were for him, in this case a way of getting some sense of what life was like for pre-industrial farmers. He had a setting focused on farming and plantlife ready to go.

While Juniper was giving himself a tour, Amy appeared in the garden, with her hand on their blink dog, Blinkers.

“Blinkers, you were right!” said Amy. She beamed at Mary, her namesake, of a sort. “Hi auntie.”

“Hello, little one,” said Mary. “Are you staying out of trouble?” She had a way of taking on a cool and mysterious demeanor with the girls, which they loved.

“Always,” answered Amy.

“But getting into a little trouble is something good girls do, from time to time,” said Mary with a smile.

“Well, I do get in a little trouble,” said Amy.

“I got you a gift,” said Juniper, reaching into his satchel and pulling out a length of red fabric. “It’s a cape.”

“What does it do?” asked Amy, taking it into her hands and looking at it with wide eyes.

“Now that would be telling,” said Juniper. “Go on, try to work it out. I’ll give you a hint though: it’s better when you’re fast.”

Amy affixed the cape around her shoulders, then took off, with Blinkers the blink dog following close behind her.

“They’re getting to the age where it might be better to make multiples,” said Valencia.

“They’re entads, sorry,” said Juniper. “Each one is unique.”

“Juniper,” said Valencia.

“Fine, fine,” replied Juniper. “I’ll consider it.”

When Amy came back into view, there was a storm of leaves following behind her, rolling and tumbling. “Mom, I’m the god of leaves!”

“It should give you a fair bit of control,” Juniper called to her. “Try getting a boost when you jump!”

Amy picked up speed, then jumped, and the leaves came rushing under her, pushing her tumbling high into the sky, which elicited a shriek of joy. She landed with a thump on the ground, and something in Valencia’s brain sent a momentary jolt of panic that was swept away to the side when Amy climbed to her feet.

“Ow,” said Amy, brushing herself off. She’d fallen nearly twenty feet, and there wasn’t a scratch on her.

“She feels pain?” asked Juniper, suddenly tense.

“She asked to turn it on, and the Authority agreed,” said Valencia. “It’s at a very low level, fleeting, and only in specific circumstances.”

“Hmm,” said Juniper.

Amy was already running again, with the leaves following her.

“I don’t like it,” said Juniper.

“It’s always odd to me, seeing the places where he disagrees with the Authority,” said Mary. “Usually it’s in a place where he agrees with the general principle but not the logical conclusion.”

“I just think she’s young for it,” said Juniper. “And … I hadn’t thought that we’d have children who are traditionalists.”

“You’re seeing it through the wrong lens,” said Valencia. “She’s a child, she read about pain in books, she’s been exposed to it, and she wanted to try it for herself. I’m sure she’ll be able to articulate it better when she’s older, but I imagine there’s something grounding that comes with a tiny bit of negative feedback from your body when you’ve made a mistake or suffered a failure.”

“Yes,” said Mary. “But Juniper doesn’t have to like it.”

They watched as Amy moved across the grass, fast as the wind, with the blink dog behind her. She jumped into the air and the leaves pushed her again, tossing her high, and this time she landed without incident.

When they went inside, Juniper the Younger had to be prompted to stop reading, then prompted again to give her aunt and uncle a hug. There was something very timid about her, which Valencia couldn’t quite account for, and she’d had conversations with Jorge about whether or not it might be better to petition the Authority on her behalf, or perhaps talk with her about it. It was, perhaps, just a phase, but even as a baby, Juniper the Younger had startled easily and been a bit more sensitive than her sister.

“I have a gift for you, Younger,” said Juniper the Elder. He always referred to her as ‘Younger’ when he met her. It had taken him some time to get used to having a namesake, but once he’d adjusted, he’d begun to spend more time with her than with her sister. That might have been because she was a more subdued child though.

“A gift?” asked Juniper the Younger.

“A gift,” Juniper the Elder repeated. He reached down into his satchel and withdrew a gleaming silver sword.

“Joon,” said Valencia with a sigh. “You are not giving my four-year-old daughter a sword.”

“I’m actually four and a half,” said Juniper the Younger. She used the word ‘actually’ a lot.

“It’s a safety sword,” said Juniper. “It cannot cut, cannot hurt a single living thing, except for the boojums.”

The Younger looked at the Elder with wide eyes. “What’s a boojum?” she asked.

“It’s a monster,” said Juniper the Elder. “A very scary monster with thick black teeth and a twisted skull, and eyes like wrinkled lemon seeds. Now, your mother is a witch of some power, and she’s warded your family home and the outlying areas against the boojums, but if you go to certain realms beyond, that’s where you’ll find the boojums.”

“In the library?” asked Juniper the Younger.

“No,” said Juniper the Elder. “Not the library, nor places where other people are. A boojum can only be found when you’re alone, and only when you seek them out. If you choose to accept the sword, then you will be the one tasked with seeking them out.” He drew back slightly. “But if you don’t accept it, then I’ll find some other child to give it to.”

Juniper the Younger took the sword from him. It gave off a faint glow in her hands.

“Good,” said Juniper the Elder. “Now, the sword has several magical properties that make it good for fighting boojums. One is that it can make light, like a flashlight.”

“Or a spell?” asked Juniper the Younger.

Juniper the Elder nodded. “Yes, like one of your mom’s spells. Now, the other two things you need to know are that it will give off an angry red glow if a boojum is near, and if you want it to, it will teach you how to fight. You can pull it from the air or return it to the air at a moment’s notice. Beyond that, for every boojum you kill, it will grant a new ability.”

Juniper the Younger was holding the sword, which was perfectly sized to her young hands, and looking at the designs that covered it. She turned to leave, and Valencia stopped her.

“What do you say?” asked Valencia.

“Thank you,” said Juniper the Younger, not looking back.

“I really, really hope you know what you’re doing,” said Valencia to Juniper the Elder. “Did you run prognostics?”

“I had the idea, then ran prognostics. I made the suggested tweaks,” said Juniper. “According to the Authority, given the information that it has access to, it’ll be good for her. It’s a way of conceptualizing the fact that there’s danger in the world, and that she can be proactive about that danger.”

“Not much danger,” said Valencia. “Juniper, if she has nightmares, I’m banning you from more ‘gifts’.”

“Do your children have nightmares?” asked Juniper.

“You know what I mean,” said Valencia.

“It was an honest question,” said Juniper. “I know you like to keep a grounding in the world. Baths instead of instant cleaning, that kind of thing.”

“I would not let my child get hit by a rock so I could have the joy of being able to comfort them,” said Valencia, crossing her arms.

“Annoying each other already?” asked Mary as she came over. She had a new wand, something that Jorge had likely made, and it was a slender, handsome thing that gave Valencia a pang of envy.

“Juniper thinks I’m a bad parent,” said Valencia with a pout.

“Why does she think that?” asked Mary, grinning.

Valencia sighed. “In my defense, when I named her, Juniper the Elder was dead.”

“I don’t think you’re a bad parent,” said Juniper. “I just think that we’ll probably have very different parenting styles, which is probably down to us having different concepts of what a good heaven is like.”

“Speaking of parenting,” said Valencia, looking at Juniper’s satchel. “Your toad is missing.”

Juniper looked down. “Ah, shit.”

“Language,” said Valencia.

“I have an amulet,” said Juniper, pulling something out from his shirt as he looked around on the ground. “It’s the Amulet of Bad Words. If I say a bad word, the children will hear something else. Farkle or fungi or something.”

“Do you need help finding the toad?” asked Valencia.

“Nah,” said Juniper. “He’s around here somewhere.” He got down on his hands and knees to look under the chairs and tables. “I’m going to look outside real quick.”

“It’s like a game they play,” said Mary with a sigh as she watched Juniper leave. “The toad does it on purpose, I think.”

“I think he’ll make a good father,” said Valencia.

“He’d better,” said Mary. “The Authority approved us as parents, which puts a limit on how bad we can be, not that I’m going to depend on that.”

“Do you think he’ll enjoy it as the ultimate act of creation?” asked Valencia.

Amaryllis laughed. “No, I don’t think that aspect of it would ever even cross his mind. I think for Juniper, at least in his mind, before it’s happened, parenthood is more akin to being a Dungeon Master, shepherding a player who is ultimately in control of her own destiny, and hoping that she has fun with things.”

Valencia nodded. “Or perhaps, this once, it won’t revolve around games and worldbuilding?”

“Perhaps,” replied Amaryllis with a smile.

Multitudes

The primary question of heaven was different for everyone. For some it was ‘how do I deal with other people?’ and for others it was ‘what is my purpose?’, but for Bethel, it was ‘who do I want to be?’

The question was a fairly common one, and it was something that everyone in the heavens grappled with from time to time, in one way or another.

All of Bethel’s powers were meaningless in the heavens. Anyone could have them, if they wanted to ascend high enough. A number of powers had been stripped right out, since they weren’t available to anyone, or if not stripped, then rendered ineffective by requiring consent. There was no more going into someone’s dreams, no more looking at someone’s insides, no more tearing things apart. It was a relief, in a way, in another way, a sadness. One of the most annoying things that had been removed was the ability to accelerate time for others, which wasn’t possible in the heavens, since the Authority thought that it would result in a race to the bottom. There were exceptions, because the Authority was keen on evaluating everything on a case by case basis, but for the most part living two hours for the one hour everyone else was living was forbidden unless you were doing two things at once with a temp clone or memory-sharing arrangement or something more exotic.

The powers, then, were irrelevant. It was everything else that mattered, the pieces of her mind, the thoughts that she was inclined to think, and who or what she valued. All that was malleable. It was malleable for the mortal species as well now, at least in the middle heavens. But the relationship to the pieces of her mind was different for Bethel, for whom those pieces had specific histories and names, names like Loyal Recurve, or Soskanna, or the Diadem of Focused Intent … or the Eternal Golden Braid.

Some people found it easy to change who they were. They went to the middle heavens and simply declared, “I do not wish to be angry anymore,” and the Authority would ask them whether they were sure, and they would say “Yes,” and that would be that. People would strip out all kinds of things, ‘negative’ emotions like envy, greed, guilt, depression, and anxiety. The Narrator had cut out jealousy without even thinking about it too much, because his Fenns liked to sexually indulge themselves with Thespians from time to time. It was simple, for some, to say of themselves ‘no, this piece of me does not belong’. They felt no anxiety or discomfort about the change.

It was different for Bethel. She was more familiar with the idea of having things added to her and having them removed, and had done much of that even before the heavens. But to be able to decide, from infinite variations, what should be her, what should constitute the pieces of her mind, what might stay and what might leave … It was paralyzing. Her assistant had advice, of course, the assistants were perfectly capable of laying out your options for you, but they were incapable of pulling the trigger on their own, so to speak, not unless you told them to do as they pleased. That, of course, was its own kind of decision, the decision to not make a decision.

Bethel had demurred, and the assistant hadn’t pushed it, or continued the conversation in any way, which Bethel assumed was a vote of confidence in her ability to figure it out on her own, or a recognition that she wasn’t opening the floor to a debate. For the most part, Bethel didn’t like the assistants. She hadn’t let them into her mind, and rarely spoke with them. In a way, her relationship with Valencia had been one of being managed, and while she’d understood the necessity of that, she didn’t feel the need to allow someone to do that in the heavens.

“I understand self-determination as a continual problem,” Valencia had said, while her children ran around the house, playing a game of hide and seek with their teleporting dog.

Very early on, Valencia asked whether Bethel still wanted to be their house, and after some thought on the matter, Bethel had declined. It was, quietly, the end of an era. For all the time they’d spent together, they had never quite been friends. Valencia had been too much of a therapist and too much of a tightrope walker. The only thing they really had in common was the past, and that got further away every day. Bethel’s only other connection from those times was to Amaryllis, who visited once a week like clockwork, in a way that made Bethel suspect that it was an obligation that Amaryllis had written into a calendar somewhere.

“Is there no solution?” asked Bethel.

“I don’t think so,” said Valencia. “We are always deciding who we are. Now is the time for the largest decisions, like what to keep and what to get rid of, but the question is never entirely going to go away, not if you keep experiencing new things. Unless you’re stuck in a rut, you’re always changing, and the question is always there. You’re always answering it.”

It hadn’t particularly been what Bethel had wanted from the conversation. She also wasn’t certain that Valencia’s framing was the correct one. That phrase, ‘a rut’, seemed to carry so much of a connotation that it could be safely ignored.

For a time, Bethel stood empty. She was not idle: she made changes to herself, though they were only physical in nature. It was a foolish thing to do, to create and furnish rooms that had no occupants, to plan the grounds around her without taking into consideration those who would use them. The combination of entads she had on Aerb had meant that she had already been able to change form almost at a whim, but in the heavens, the limits were completely stripped off.

She tried everything, and sometimes had Thespians there to test things out, moving through the rooms, sleeping on the beds, and offering their thoughts and opinions. It was an eye-opening experience, in part because there was such a vast difference between these people, who the assistant assured Bethel were representative of randomly selected people who would be amenable to living inside her.

When Bethel had been on Aerb, she’d designed based on things she’d seen or read about in books, without usually thinking about it on a deeper basis. She had invented things of her own, experimented with rooms of immense size once she was able, and it had all been … well, in hindsight, uninformed was the word she chose to use.

Much of that first year in the heavens was spent learning, sometimes with an assistant as her instructor, other times by looking through books or wandering through city streets, which were often created just for her. Everything was so interconnected, or had been. Houses had been constrained by available materials and labor, but beyond that, elements of the society which the people were embedded in, and those, in turn, were informed by different considerations, like their ancestral environments, their biology, their technology, and the cruft that built up in any society over time.

“Many houses incorporate aspects of holiness into them,” a Thespian instructor said. “To understand certain aspects of houses, you’ll also have to understand aspects of religions and other cultural customs. In Meribak they follow the Golden Ratio as dogma, building their houses so that each room has the proper ratio to the next. In Leggan, they have a small recessed shrine in the foyer. And in Terrest, a pentagram is positioned in a place of prominence above the dining room table. Houses are designed with these curiosities in mind, though it’s often a matter of extent, and the consideration of the costs involved.”

Bethel played with making herself authentic in certain ways, which required imagining a context in which she might have been built by mortal hands, and a whole geography around her, with quarries that the stone would have been taken from, and woods where the timbers would have been harvested, and cities where those raw materials would have been worked and refined, guilds where the workers would have trained with apprentices, or colleges where they would have taken instruction from professors. She imagined cultures and societies and individuals embedded within them.

And, of course, there was no need to do any of this. None of the Thespians had complained that she wasn’t authentic enough. Presumably the group of real people who might have recognized inauthentic constructions was small, and the subset who might have been bothered by it even smaller. Out in the heavens, beyond all material considerations, people were surely making houses with no regard for physical reality whatsoever, unless they were the poor souls who had stuck themselves in the lower heavens.

Eventually, Bethel sent a long, rambling letter to Juniper, expressing interest in his viewpoint. Not the original Juniper, of course, with whom the Incident had happened, nor the Narrator, who had dictated it, but the Juniper from the Other Side. She hadn’t known whether she should expect a response, but she got one, and a week later, he was standing in her foyer. She had fretted over what body to present to him, and eventually decided that she would take the form she had in Orrangush, when she’d been a sweets shop with a home upstairs. She liked a muscular form, one that eschewed femininity to some degree, and with this Juniper, there was no need to appear as any particular thing to let him know that she wouldn’t hurt him, that she wished she could change things, that — well, there was no need.

“The sentient house,” said Juniper, once he arrived. He took a moment to regard her. “I was surprised to get your letter.”

He was different in a large number of ways, with a steel behind his gaze, and a kind of cockiness that Bethel took an instant dislike to. There was a plethora of information on what this other Juniper had done on the Other Side, including a relatively detailed book written by one of his companions, but Bethel had read none of it. Those kinds of stories of adventuring heroes had never interested her. She wondered whether he was equally ignorant of her, and hoped that he was.

“You said that you needed my help,” said Juniper, raising an eyebrow. “With worldbuilding.”

“Yes,” said Bethel. “You construct worlds, don’t you?”

“Is that something you think is core to a Juniper?” he asked, voice mild. There was something chilly about him, though not entirely in a bad way.

“I do,” she said.

“It is,” he replied with a shrug. “But I won’t tell you anything that an assistant couldn’t, which means that I’m not really here for that. I’m here because you were thinking of him.”

“I was,” Bethel admitted. “But I would still like that conversation, if you’re available.”

The Other Juniper nodded. “I came because I thought it might be interesting. You said that the topic for discussion was houses.”

“I’m not sure that I care so much about houses,” said Bethel.

“No?” asked Juniper, arching an eyebrow.

“I care about the ways in which we reflect the world around us,” replied Bethel, choosing her words carefully. “If you gave someone a house, only a house, you would be able to determine so much about the world outside the house. It would understand the people. The house is a shadow cast by the existence of the people and their material considerations, their history, their religion, and all other things. But the people themselves are shadows cast by biological reality, by society, by culture, by the very same material considerations. If you took a person, just a person, you could discover his entire society, the entire geography, possibly from his body alone.”

“Or from speaking to him,” said Juniper. “And I don’t mean that to be facetious, I mean that language arises from biology and relevant concepts embed them into the language on the basis of material determination.” He stared at her with cold eyes. “All of it has changed now, but the people are still there, free from those tethers. They’re shadows, free from the light which created them, and still casting shadows of their own. The shadows they cast are more stark now, in some respects.”

Bethel cocked her head to the side. “Are they?”

“There is absolutely no need to worry about material, process, labor, or even the constraints of physical reality,” said Juniper. “There is no need to worry about biological reality. So when people choose their forms, and their homes for their forms, it reflects them all the more sharply. There are no longer accidents of circumstance, it’s all by intent, even if it’s just the assistants pulling in relevant pieces. If you wanted to talk about it in terms of shadows, the shadows are sharper, because there’s only one object in front of the light.”

Bethel watched him. “You’re much different from him.”

“I had it easier, in many ways, and harder, in others,” said the Other Side Juniper. “I was also at it for longer.” He looked around the house, around Bethel. “Do you mind taking me on a tour?”

“Oh, this?” asked Bethel, using her form to look at the room and the things within it, then the rest of the house beyond. “This is nothing, just a trifle. A possibility.” In reality, she had put as much thinking into what kind of house she should be as she put into what her body and clothes should be like. “I wasn’t thinking of critique, if that was your inclination.”

“No, only comment,” replied Juniper. “May I?”

“Of course,” replied Bethel. She looked around the foyer, which had gray slate tile flooring and a mat by the door. There was a bench, with shoes under it, and beside it, a row of hooks with coats on them, and a wooden chest that could be opened up for other things. “This is the foyer, obviously, a place to don or remove outdoor clothing, especially in the winter.”

“A floor designed to be easily cleaned,” said Juniper, looking down at the tile. He looked up at her. “You said in your letter that you found yourself inventing stories about the houses you were choosing to become. A foyer like this is more common in places with winter climates, or with messy conditions, because there’s more difficulty in braving the exterior or in keeping the interior clean. The ultimate extension of this would be an airlock.”

“I don’t know that I need you to explain foyers to me,” said Bethel.

“No?” asked Juniper. “I was hoping that we might generalize.” He held his hands behind his back. “You wanted to talk about homes and the context they sit in, and by extension, you wanted to talk about yourself, and the context you sit in. You wanted to discuss the ways that the context of the heavens can or should shape you. You’re trying to determine who or what you should be, what house can be made from the raw materials of the heavens and the people who live there, and what exterior you might make of your mind.”

This wasn’t quite what Bethel had written in her letter, but his distillation and interpretation of it seemed to fit, seemed to sing. Her recent obsession with the craft of building and the ways in which homes were embedded in societies came into focus. It was, of course, interesting in its own right, but this Juniper had identified the precise way in which it was personal. Bethel idly wondered whether the assistants might have been able to give her the same insight, and decided that they probably could have and simply didn’t, either because she hadn’t asked, because they thought it wouldn’t make her happy, or because it was an incorrect but compelling reason. Or perhaps they hadn’t said it because she felt frosty toward them, and wouldn’t have taken the insight in the same way. She had told them to shut up a few times.

“I didn’t have an Amaryllis,” said Juniper. “I think that accounts for the largest difference between the Earth Juniper and myself, even more than the two different worlds we came from. I had no one to serve as my crutch, no one to drive things forward.” He paused. “It seemed as though you were wondering.”

“Mmm,” said Bethel. She turned from him and walked through the archway into the living room, which was laid out with a sliding glass door to one side that led to the deck that jutted off the side of the house. It was a large room, with many places to sit, and a fireplace against one wall. “The living room,” she said, perhaps unnecessarily.

“You’ll need to find your purpose first, before you can decide what kind of home you are,” said Juniper.

“Are you not interested in the tour?” asked Bethel, raising an eyebrow.

“I am,” said Juniper.

He looked around, at the couch and chairs, then at the small desk, and finally to the doors and windows. Did he notice the orientation of the house, north-facing so that the largest windows could capture as much sunlight as possible? Did he notice the sealing around the sliding door to keep the draft out in the winter? The way the furniture was positioned around the fireplace? It was hard to say. Her senses had been dulled, at least when it came to other people. She was no longer capable of tracking the saccades of the eyes or their precise fixation points. She couldn’t hear his heart in his chest, or watch the movement of blood through his body. It had been quite some time since she had done anything like that, even on Aerb, but to have it so plainly ripped away was … well, a matter of what was implicitly consented to in the heavens. She could have asked him for that level of access, but it seemed likely he would refuse.

“The elemental functions of the house no longer matter,” said Juniper. “Warmth, cooling, storage, bathing, food, privacy, all gone if you want them to be.” He gestured at the doors, then at the fireplace, then at the roof. “If people want those needs, it’s because of nostalgia and unedited psychology. If they want those needs fulfilled in the specific ways of a house, it’s for those same reasons.”

“Do you say that in a dismissive way?” asked Bethel.

“No,” said Juniper. “It’s just something that I’ve been thinking about. I'm still largely human. I like the feeling of warming myself by a fire, or cooling myself in the shade, but I’ll readily admit that it’s a matter of patterns in my mind and a desire for simplicity and tradition. Some people rebel against the new reality and deny what they’re actually seeking, refusing to soothe their needs, or perhaps unaware of their needs. Alternatively, they make up excuses for things they simply feel, letting those feelings guide them into a familiar reality.”

“I don’t know my own needs,” said Bethel. “I think about having a family in me, as I’ve always wanted, and … I had that, with Valencia and Jorge.”

“She was the non-anima?” asked Juniper.

“Yes,” replied Bethel. “But even when I had that idyllic life, the one that I had always wanted …” she paused. “I felt like I should be doing something. I felt like I couldn’t relax. I was restless, which is not a comfortable thing for a house.”

“And that’s why you haven’t taken on a new family?” asked Juniper.

“I’m five hundred years old,” said Bethel. “I spent much of my life down in a pit, ruminating. Spending a year or two trying to work out who I am or who I want to be feels prudent. Besides, I have the Thespians and the assistants, and occasional visitors.” Two of them, in fact.

“You’re aware we don’t know each other?” asked Juniper. “When I leave here, it’s unlikely I’ll come back. If you haven’t been speaking to your assistants because of your relationship with the Authority, you can speak with me. Sometimes it’s better to say something out loud to a disinterested third party.” There was, again, a chilliness to him. The original Juniper was distant sometimes, but in a much less intentional way.

Bethel thought about this. “I hold no power in the heavens. I cannot act on others without consent, and all my most powerful abilities are freely replicated,” said Bethel. “I have no utility to anyone. Those who want a magical house can have one simply by asking for one. There is no longer anything unique about me, aside from my history.”

“The terrible thing about the heavens is that if we’re miserable in them, it’s our own fault,” said Juniper.

“I’m not miserable,” said Bethel. “But I don’t think it would be wise to have people living inside me until I have decided on a self to be.”

“I don’t think that’s true,” said Juniper. “You’re not going to hurt anyone.”

“I might,” said Bethel. “Not in the ways I’ve hurt people in the past, but by making a commitment that I cannot keep. That I might do, if I have no solid foundation for myself.”

Juniper shrugged. “Lean on the assistants. Allow them in. Let them tell you what would best help you become the person you were meant to be.”

“It does not surprise me that you suggest I lay everything down for the Authority,” said Bethel.

“For all our differences, I’m still a Juniper,” said Juniper, smiling. “But in refusing his help, you’re doing yourself no favors. Speak with the assistants, and they’ll point you in the right direction.” He looked around. “To the bedroom?”

Bethel narrowed her eyes. There was something familiar in the way he was standing. “Are you having thoughts of fucking me?” she asked.

The Other Juniper looked her over. “Of course. If you wanted to skip the flirtation and pleasantries, I would be fine with that. Or we could finish the tour first.”

Bethel regarded him. “I’ve stripped out all sexual desire from myself.” She gestured to her body. “This form is incapable of feeling sexual pleasure. I have no genitalia. And besides, with you … there are bad memories.” She hesitated to call it trauma, lest she paint herself the victim.

Juniper snapped his fingers, and changed in an instant, becoming unrecognizable. He was still a rather tall man, with broad shoulders and firm muscles, but the structure of his face had completely changed, his skin was a bit darker, and his hair hung in curls.

“It’s easy to forget that people can do that,” said Bethel, regarding him.

“I know what happened between the two of you,” said this new man, who bore no resemblance to Juniper. “I know too, in general terms, the lesson of his time on Aerb. We cannot let the bad taint the good. We cannot eternally hang on to misery.”

Bethel knew all this. It was what she had worked on with Valencia for so long. Yet there was a lingering sadness, and perhaps some of that came with an understanding that the actions of the past could never truly be made up for. The party took a trip or vacation twice a year, and while Amaryllis had extended an offer the second time they’d done it, Bethel had known that it was a bad idea, and an offer extended only with the expectation that it would be refused. Amaryllis and Valencia were the only two she was close to anyway, for a certain value of ‘close’.

“And I would change myself to be receptive to the offer,” said Bethel. “And we would fuck, and then you would leave, is that it?”

“I spoke to Amaryllis before I came here,” said the Other Juniper. “We don’t speak often. She doesn’t take a liking to me, funnily enough. But when I asked about you, she said that you had swung too far in the opposite direction, that you feared happiness. It’s a bad thing, to have a fear of happiness and indulgence. Your mistake with the original Juniper —”

“I don’t call it a mistake,” said Bethel. “Calling it that takes agency away from me.”

The Other Juniper nodded. “Following that, you learned the value of restraint. But now, in these times, restraint has little value. Trepidation over whether you might hurt other people is virtually worthless. You need to relearn how to have fun.”

“By fucking you?” asked Bethel, looking him up and down. There was no desire, but there was some desire for desire.

“If that doesn’t appeal, perhaps you could indulge in other ways,” he said. “I would consent to being tortured, if you would like. Twenty-four hours, say, to strip the skin from my flesh and my flesh from my bones.”

Bethel stilled her breath. “Why would you offer such a thing?”

“I think you might find it instructive,” he said with a shrug. “I think you might enjoy it. I’m sympathetic. There’s limited ability to do real good in the heavens, and this might be one way for me to help someone.”

“But you would turn the pain down,” said Bethel. “You would only pretend to feel.”

“No,” he replied, shaking his head. “I would consent to suffer. You could have the assistants report on my subjective experience. They would not lie. I would not forget the pain after the fact, perhaps only dull the effects of the pain on my psyche.”

Bethel stared at him. “Perhaps another time,” she said. “On both accounts.”

“Another time,” he nodded. “The rest of the tour, then, unless you’d like some time to think?”

“I would like the time, yes,” nodded Bethel. “I’d like to be alone. Thank you, for your perspective.”

“Don’t spend too much time thinking,” he replied. “The student of failures learns faster than the student who has only heard his master’s words.”

He vanished without much fanfare, and Bethel felt suddenly, unaccountably empty, in a way that hadn’t hit her like the emptiness of the previous year.

“Assistant,” said Bethel.

“Yes?” asked a blandly attractive woman who popped into existence beside Bethel’s human form.

“I would like … help,” said Bethel.

“I will help in any way we can,” replied the assistant. The obsequious nature of the assistant had been what Bethel had requested, almost right from the start, but it was beginning to grate.

“Be the way I would want you to be,” said Bethel.

She shifted slightly. “I can’t read your mind.”

Bethel hesitated. What was she afraid of? The Authority was Juniper, or close enough, and he already knew everything important about her. Everyone who remained even remotely close to Bethel had allowed the Authority into their minds to some extent, and surely the Authority could construct a mostly-correct model of her from that. Perhaps the fear was that the assistant would work, and would melt away all of her inner pain and hesitation.

“Fine,” said Bethel. “Go ahead.”

The assistant relaxed into herself, and then went through several subtle changes to her face and body. She became, in some ways, reminiscent of Valencia, and in other ways like a female mirror of Juniper. Bethel also noticed, almost immediately, that her sensorium was functional with respect to this assistant, with the entire inner biological working splayed out for Bethel to inspect. Before the assistant had been biologically dead, a projection and nothing more.

“You can call me Winsome, or Winnie for short,” said the assistant, smiling slightly. “Now then, I’ve been waiting for you to use me as a resource. We’ll start slow, obviously, but you need to be reintroduced to society. There are a number of social organizations that I think you’d be a good fit for, specifically, the entad wing of the slave species coalition, which holds regular meetings. Beyond that, I’d like to move people into you as soon as possible. I have a number of candidates lined up who, like you, suffer from hesitance of varying degree.”

“They don’t want to be happy,” said Bethel.

“They want to be happy, but suffer in various ways because they refuse to take meaningful steps to allow themselves happiness,” replied the assistant. Winnie. Bethel did like the name.

“Very well,” said Bethel. “Then I’ll have to make myself ready for them. I don’t suppose you can tell me a bit about these potential tenants?”

“Of course,” replied Winnie with a smile. “What kind of assistant would I be if I couldn’t?”

And from there they were off, talking about these people, and the things they did, the ways they related to the world, and their personal histories.

Bethel began to build a new home.